<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Christian constancy crovvned by Christ A funerall sermon on Apocalyps 2.10. preached at the buriall of M. VVilliam Winter, citizen of London; together with the testimonie then giuen vnto him. By Thomas Gataker, B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2004-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A01528</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 11653</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S102884</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99838646</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99838646</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">3032</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01528)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3032)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1099:07)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Christian constancy crovvned by Christ A funerall sermon on Apocalyps 2.10. preached at the buriall of M. VVilliam Winter, citizen of London; together with the testimonie then giuen vnto him. By Thomas Gataker, B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Sibbes, Richard, 1577-1635.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[8], 31, [1] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Iohn Hauiland for William Bladen, and are to be sold at the signe of the Bible, at the great north doore of Pauls,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1624.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Editor's dedication signed: R. Sibbs.</NOTE><NOTE>The first leaf is blank.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Winter, William, --  citizen of London.</TERM><TERM>Sermons, English --  17th century.</TERM><TERM>Funeral sermons.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2003-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Olivia Bottum</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2003-12</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A01528">
<STC T="S">11653</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99838646</BIBNO>
<VID>3032</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>CHRISTIAN CONSTANCY CROWNED BY CHRIST.</P>
<P>A Funerall Sermon on APOCALYPS 2.10.</P>
<P>Preached at the buriall of M. WILLIAM WINTER, Citizen of LONDON; Together with the Testimonie then giuen vnto Him: By THOMAS GATAKER, B. of D. and Pastor of ROTHERHITH.</P>
<P>LONDON, Printed by IOHN HAVILAND for WILLIAM BLADEN, and are to be sold at the signe of the Bible, at the great North doore of <HI>Pauls.</HI> 1624.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL M<SUP>r</SUP>. ROBERT OFFLY MASTER of the company of Habberdashers, and the right Worshipfull Sir IOHN GARRET Knight, Mr. Alderman HAMMERSLY, Mr. Alderman WHITMORE, Mr. Alderman RANTON, and other worthy fathers and brethren of the said Company, all prosperitie in this world, and happinesse in the world to come.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Right Worshipfull,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">A</SEG>Lbeit the expressions of a gra∣cious heart by liuely voice breed deeper impressions, (God attending his own or∣dinance of preaching with a more speciall blessising) yet writing hath in this respect a preroga∣tiue, that holy truths thus conueyed to the world spread further, and continue longer.
<PB REF="3"/>
Those therefore deserue well of the Church that this way impart those things to pub∣like and future vse, by which God wrought on the hearts of the hearers for the present. In which respect this funerall Sermon prea∣ched out of loue and honour of the graces of God in a poore, yet well esteemed Chri∣stian (Master WINTER) may gaine accep∣tan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, as being not onely for matter sound, for handling cleere, but for the times seaso∣nable. For what more necessarie in these times, wherein many are ashamed of the downeright profession of that religion by which they hope to be saued, than to presse constant faithfulnesse in known truths, vn∣to which all promises are intailed? Particu∣lar points haue beene much and long vrged amongst vs, it is very needfull that constant clea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing to all those blessed truths likewise be inforced. And from what stronger in∣couragement can this be, than from a crown of life here promised to the crowne of all graces, Perseuerance? Since the fall, one dan∣gerous disease of the soule, is vnsetlednesse in good purposes, especially when either dis∣couragements or alluremēts are offered. But
<PB REF="3"/>
what wil not a soule break thorow, that hath in the eie of it a crowne held out to all that hold out to the end▪ by him who hath both obtained it for vs, and keepeth it for vs, and vs for it? There is a mutuall passage of trust between God and vs (for thus graciously he condescendeth to vs.) We trust him with the saluation of our soules, he trusteth vs with his truth, which if by grace we be in∣abled to keepe, it will keepe vs▪ and raise vp our hearts to an expectation of all good frō our faithfull and good God, euen at that time when our soules gaspe for comfort, at the houre of death. And at the day of iudge∣ment the sentence will passe, not according to greatnesse of parts and place, but accor∣ding to faithfulnesse, Well done, not learned, wise, rich, but faithfull seruant, &amp;c. This Ser∣mon intreating of things thus vsefull, is pre∣sented by me, as intreated by the widow of the late deceased (Master WINTER) and some others whom I respect, and to you as chiefe of that Company whereof he was a poore member: and this by willing consent of the author, my reuerend &amp; ancient friend of whom I am not willing to take this occa∣sion to speake: his long, faithfull, learned la∣bours
<PB REF="4"/>
in the Church haue made him suffi∣ciently knowne. He gaue her full power of the copy for her vse. Which in her behalfe, and at her desire, I offer vnto your worships as a testimony of her respect, as likewise if there be a blessing in your hands in the be∣halfe of the Orphans of such as haue beene of your Company, I was not vnwilling to take this aduantage of presenting her estate to your mercifull considerations, conside∣ring she traineth vp a sonne at the Vniuersi∣tie for the future seruice of the Church. It is a speciall blessing of God where he hath gi∣uen power and a willing mind to do good, to offer likewise the opportunity of fit ob∣iects that bounty be not misplaced; which here vndoubtedly you shall haue, and the blessing of the fatherlesse and widow shall come vpon you. The Lord leade you on in a course of faithfulnes to which we are here encouraged, that in the end you may receiue the crowne of life which is here promised.</P>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>Graies Inne,
<DATE>Ian. 2. 1623.</DATE></DATELINE>
<SIGNED><HI>Yours in all Christian seruice,</HI> R. Sibbs.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>CHRISTIAN CONSTANCIE crowned by CHRIST.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<Q><BIBL><HI>APOCALYPS 2.10.</HI></BIBL>
<P>Be thou faithfull vnto death, and I will giue thee a crowne of life.</P></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG>T shall be needlesse to make stay vpon any curious <HI>Ana∣lysis,</HI> either of this whole <HI>Chapter</HI> in <HI>generall,</HI> or in <HI>particular</HI> of that <HI>Epistle,</HI> whereof my Text is a <HI>par∣cell.</HI> It containeth an en∣tire <HI>Sentence</HI> of it selfe, and may well therefore be handled by it selfe.</P>
<P>They are the words of our Sauiour to the <HI>An∣gell</HI> or <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Frustra est <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Origenes, qui de Spiritibus coelesti∣bus interpretatur <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Luc. h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m.</HI> 13. <HI>&amp;</HI> 3<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></NOTE> <HI>Pastor</HI> of the <HI>Church</HI> <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vers.</HI> 8.</NOTE> of <HI>Smyrna:</HI> and they diuide themselues into <HI>two parts,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Parts</HI> 2.</NOTE>
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>a precept.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>a promise.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P><PB N="2" REF="5"/><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Precept.</HI></NOTE>The <HI>precept</HI> is in those words, <HI>Be thou faithfull vnto death:</HI></P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Promise.</HI></NOTE>The <HI>promise</HI> in those, <HI>And I will giue thee a crowne of life.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Part</HI> 1.</NOTE></P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Branches</HI> 2.</NOTE>There is the <HI>worke</HI> in the one; the <HI>reward</HI> or <HI>wages</HI> in the other.<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. <HI>Dutie.</HI></NOTE></P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">2. <HI>Stint,</HI></NOTE>In the <HI>precept</HI> we may obserue,
<LIST>
<ITEM><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Extent.</HI></NOTE>1. The <HI>dutie</HI> required, <HI>fidelitie</HI> or <HI>faithfulnesse: Be thou faithfull:</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Part</HI> 2.</NOTE> and</ITEM>
<ITEM><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Branches</HI> 2.</NOTE>2. The <HI>stint,</HI> or <HI>extent</HI> of it; <HI>Vnto death.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg">1. <HI>Giuer.</HI></NOTE>In the <HI>promise</HI> likewise we may consider,
<LIST>
<ITEM><NOTE PLACE="marg">2. <HI>Gift.</HI></NOTE>1. The <HI>giuer; Christ: I will giue thee.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Part</HI> 1.</NOTE>2. The <HI>gift; a Crowne</HI>; and that <HI>of life.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST></P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Branch</HI> 1.</NOTE>For the <HI>first branch,</HI> the <HI>dutie</HI> required or enioyned;<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Dutie.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Be faithfull.</HI> The word <HI>faithfull,</HI> is ambiguous,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Fidelitie.</HI></NOTE> and may be taken two waies; and <HI>in a twofold sense</HI> is it giuen to the godly. For as the word <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>Faith</HI> is taken sometime for <HI>cre∣dulitie,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Faith two∣fold. Creduli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie, Confidence.</HI></NOTE> and sometime for <HI>fidelitie</HI>; sometime for <HI>trust,</HI> and sometime for <HI>trustinesse</HI>; some∣time for <HI>confidence</HI> in another, and sometime for <HI>faithfulnesse</HI> to another: In the <HI>former sense</HI> it is taken in those <HI>phraeses</HI> so vsuall; <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Act.</HI> 24.25.</NOTE> <HI>Faith in Christ,</HI> and <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Act.</HI> 3.16.</NOTE> <HI>Faith in his Name:</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Fidelitie. Faithfulnesse.</HI></NOTE> In the <HI>latter sense</HI> it is taken in those words of our Sauiour, <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 23.23.</NOTE> <HI>You neglect iudgement, mercy,</HI> and <HI>faith,</HI> or <HI>fidelitie</HI>; and in those of the Apostle, <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Tit.</HI> 2.10.</NOTE> <HI>Let seruants shew all faith</HI> (that is,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><P><HI>Faithfull two waies.</HI></P>
<P><HI>In regard of Beliefe and Confidence.</HI></P></NOTE> <HI>faithfulnesse</HI>) <HI>to their Masters.</HI> So <HI>Gods Saints and seruants</HI> are termed <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>faithfull</HI> in a two∣fold respect: sometime in regard of their <HI>faith</HI>; that is, their <HI>beliefe and confidence in Christ:</HI> <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iohn</HI> 20.27.</NOTE> <HI>Be not faithlesse, but faithfull</HI>; saith our Sauiour to
<PB N="3" REF="5"/>
<HI>Thomas:</HI> And, <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 6.15.</NOTE> <HI>What part hath the faithfull with the Infidell?</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>In regard of Fidelitie and Faithfulnesse.</HI></NOTE> saith the Apostle; that is, <HI>the beleeuer with the vnbeleeuing.</HI> Sometime in regard of their <HI>fidelitie and faithfulnesse vnto Christ:</HI> <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 24.45.</NOTE> <HI>Who is a wise and a faithfull seruant?</HI> saith our Sauiour. And, <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 7.27.</NOTE> <HI>I haue receiued mercie of God, to be faithfull</HI>; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aith the Apostle: which of the former <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><HI>Non quia <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ram, sed ut essem, ne meritum fidei Dei misericordiam prae∣veniat. Aug. de grat. &amp; lib. arb. c.</HI> 6. <HI>&amp;</HI> 14. <HI>&amp; de praedest. sanct. c.</HI> 2. <HI>&amp;</HI> 3. <HI>De fide iustificante in∣telligens.</HI></NOTE> some mis-ex∣pound. In this latter sense (as I take it) is the word here to be taken. For so is <HI>Antipas</HI> <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>contra∣ctum ex <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>: sicut <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Lucius, Lu∣cas. Ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>emidorus, Artemas. Numeri∣us, Numas, &amp;c. vise Var. de <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing. Lat. l.</HI> 7. <HI>&amp; Scalig. ad Catul.</HI></NOTE> a little after ter∣med <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vers.</HI> 13.</NOTE> <HI>Christs faithfull Martyr:</HI> and what is here said of being <HI>faithfull to death,</HI> is in the next <HI>Epistle</HI> called, <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vers.</HI> 26.</NOTE> <HI>the keeping of his workes to the end.</HI></P>
<P>So that the <HI>Point</HI> then of <HI>Instruction</HI> that wee obserue hence,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Mea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing. Point</HI> I.</NOTE> is this; that</P>
<P><HI>Fidelitie or faithfulnesse is required of all Chri∣stians.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Faith in Christ</HI> must be seconded with <HI>faithful∣nesse vnto Christ.</HI> As we must haue <HI>Faith in him,</HI> so we must keepe <HI>Faith to him.</HI> For <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Apoc.</HI> 14.17.</NOTE> those that are <HI>with him,</HI> are <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>elect, called,</HI> and <HI>faithfull.</HI> And as some in this <HI>Booke</HI> are commended in this kinde for their <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ver.</HI> 19. <HI>C.</HI> 14.12</NOTE> <HI>patience and faith:</HI> so some are said else∣where, to be <HI>condemned, for breaking their faith,</HI> to wit, formerly plighted vnto him.</P>
<P>Now that we may the better conceiue,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Necessitie of Fidelitie.</HI></NOTE> and see the <HI>necessitie</HI> hereof:<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 1.</NOTE></P>
<P N="1">1. Consider we what <HI>tearmes of relation</HI> there are betweene <HI>Christ</HI> and vs. <HI>Fidelitie</HI> and <HI>loyaltie</HI> is in more speciall manner required <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Prou</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.17 <HI>Ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</HI> 3.3. <HI>Ier.</HI> 3.20.</NOTE> in the <HI>Wife</HI> toward the <HI>Husband</HI>; and in <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Tit.</HI> 2.10.</NOTE> the <HI>Seruant</HI> and <HI>Sub∣iect</HI> toward his <HI>Master,</HI> his <HI>leige Lord,</HI> and his <HI>So∣ueraigne.</HI> But <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ephes.</HI> 5.23.</NOTE> <HI>Christ</HI> is our <HI>Husband,</HI> our <HI>Head,</HI>
<PB N="4" REF="6"/>
and euery <HI>Christian soule</HI> is his <HI>Spouse:</HI> <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><HI>Hosh.</HI> 2.19, 20.</NOTE> <HI>I haue espoused thee vnto me,</HI> saith he, <HI>in mercie and in fide∣litie.</HI> Hee is <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 8.6.</NOTE> our <HI>Lord</HI> and <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 23.8.</NOTE> <HI>Master:</HI> <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iohn</HI> 13.13.</NOTE> <HI>You call me Lord and Master</HI>; saith he, <HI>and you say well; for so I am.</HI> We ought therefore to beare all <HI>loialtie</HI>▪ to shew <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 4.1, 2. 1 <HI>Pet.</HI> 4.10.</NOTE> all <HI>fidelitie</HI> and <HI>faithfulnesse</HI> vnto him. I might adde, that as <HI>Christ is Gods,</HI> so <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 6.19, 20.</NOTE> <HI>wee are Christs.</HI> <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 3.23.</NOTE> <HI>You are Christs,</HI> saith the Apostle, <HI>and Christ is Gods.</HI> As <HI>Christ</HI> therefore is to <HI>God,</HI> so should <HI>we</HI> be to <HI>Christ.</HI> But <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Heb.</HI> 4.2.</NOTE> <HI>Christ was faithfull in all things to God his Father:</HI> and <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vt enim i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se fide∣lis est in reddendo, ita fidelem exigi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> de promisso, Chrysost. nom. de fide, spe, char.</HI></NOTE> <HI>faithfull</HI> there∣fore should we bee likewise in all things to him. Hee was <HI>faithfull</HI> to <HI>God</HI> for vs: and so should we also be for him.</P>
<P N="2"><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 2.</NOTE>2. The <HI>faith</HI> that must saue vs, must be <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. 1 <HI>Tim.</HI> 1.5. 2. <HI>Tim.</HI> 1.5.</NOTE> <HI>faith vnfained.</HI> But <HI>faith</HI> seuered from <HI>fidelity,</HI> is <HI>no faith,</HI> but a meere <HI>fancie.</HI> <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Fides enim ab eo dicitur, quia id fit quod dicitur. Ex Cicer. de repub. l.</HI> 4. <HI>offic. l.</HI> 1. <HI>&amp; ad Ti∣r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n. ep.</HI> 10. <HI>Noni∣us de propr. serm. Aug. de mend. c.</HI> 20. <HI>&amp; ad Hieron. ep.</HI> 6. <HI>Herv. in Rom.</HI> 7. <HI>Haimo ibid.</HI> 1. <HI>&amp;</HI> 5. <HI>Ergo ubi non fit quod dicitur, non est fides. Petr. Cāt. de ver. abbrev. c.</HI> 7.</NOTE> <HI>Faith without faithfulnesse</HI> is <HI>a false, a counterfeit faith</HI>; like <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Plut. de <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ulat.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Copper coine</HI> that hath the <HI>lustre,</HI> but not the <HI>worth</HI> of good <HI>Gold.</HI> It is <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><HI>Infidelis quaedā fiducia. Bern. de temp.</HI> 50.</NOTE> <HI>a faithlesse faith,</HI> saith <HI>Bernard</HI>; and <HI>a trust with∣out truth,</HI> (<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ierem.</HI> 7.8.</NOTE> <HI>You trust in a lie</HI>; saith <HI>Ieremie</HI>;) where∣by men expect that <HI>God</HI> should keepe <HI>couenants</HI> with them, when they haue no care to keepe the like with him. <HI>Rabsakehs</HI> Argument against <HI>Eze∣kiah</HI> had beene good, if his words of <HI>Ezekiah</HI> had beene true. Little cause could <HI>Ezekiah</HI> haue <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai</HI> 36.7.</NOTE> <HI>to trust in God,</HI> had he <HI>taken downe his high places,</HI> and <HI>demolished his altars.</HI></P>
<P N="3"><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 3.</NOTE>3. When we surcease to keepe <HI>faith</HI> with God, we free him from performance of his <HI>promises</HI> to
<PB N="5" REF="6"/>
vs. For howsoeuer it be true indeed that the Apo∣stle saith, <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Tim.</HI> 2.13.</NOTE> <HI>Though we bee vnfaithfull,</HI> or, <HI>though</HI> <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Vide notas Piscat.</HI></NOTE> <HI>we distrust,</HI> rather; <HI>yet doth God abide faithfull; nor can he deny himselfe.</HI> <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Rom.</HI> 3.3.</NOTE> <HI>Mans distrust</HI> or <HI>increduli∣tie cannot annull his fidelitie.</HI> And it is a deuillish po∣sition that the <HI>Romanists</HI> hold, and such as cutteth asunder the very si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ewes of humane societie: that <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Fidem cum hae∣reticis non esse ser∣vandam. Videantur quae ex Simanch. institu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. catholic. habentur in. The∣sib. Romano-Cathol. à D. Thom▪ Mort<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣no editis. &amp; in A∣lex.</HI> Cookes More worke for a Masse-Priest, <HI>num.</HI> 7.</NOTE> <HI>Faith is not to bee held with Heretikes.</HI> For euen <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Etiam infideli re∣ctè servatur fides. Taxatq<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Cic. offi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. l.</HI> 3. <HI>Atrei illud apud Accium. Ne∣que do infideli, ne∣que dedi, cuiquam fidem.</HI></NOTE> <HI>with the vnfaithfull is faith to bee held.</HI> Howsoe∣uer, I say, we may not <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Plut. in Lysand. &amp; Aemyl.</HI></NOTE> <HI>play the Creetes with Creti∣ans</HI>; that is, lie and dissemble, because others so doe: nor in regard of any mans wickednesse or vngodlinesse otherwise, hold our selues discharged of such <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Gen.</HI> 21.32. <HI>&amp;</HI> 26.28, 29. <HI>&amp;</HI> 31.44, 53.</NOTE> bonds and couenants as we stand obli∣ged in vnto him. Yet where <HI>agreements</HI> betweene parties are founded and grounded on <HI>conditions</HI> or <HI>couenants</HI> (for I stand not now on the precise di∣stinction of <HI>Law-tearmes</HI>) to be mutually and en∣terchangeably performed on either side, <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Frustra sibi fidem quis postulat ab eo seruari, cui fidem à se praestitam ser∣vare recusat. Boni∣fac. PP. in</HI> 6. <HI>reg∣lur.</HI> 75. <HI>Frangen∣ti fidem fides fran∣gatur eidem. Fidem frangenti l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>citum est fidem frangere. Petr. Fous reg. Iur. ff. de inoffic. testam. Quanquam hoc revera non est fidem fallere.</HI></NOTE> he that in such case breaketh first, doth thereby free the other partie. Nor is it any <HI>vnfaithfulnesse</HI> therefore in God, (whose <HI>promises</HI> of <HI>life</HI> and <HI>saluation</HI> are so <HI>conditionall</HI>) to denie to make his promises good vnto those,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 4.</NOTE> that haue no care to keepe touch with him. <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Heb.</HI> 8.9.</NOTE> <HI>They kept not couenant with mee, and I re∣garded not them: saith the Lord.</HI></P>
<P N="4">4. As there is nothing among men generally more odious, than <HI>falshood in friendship; infidelitie</HI> in those that wee are in <HI>league</HI> and <HI>amitie</HI> withall: <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Viri f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>deris tui praevaricati sunt. Obad.</HI> 7.</NOTE> <HI>Thy confederates,</HI> saith the Prophet, <HI>haue dealt
<PB N="6" REF="7"/>
treacherously with thee.</HI> And, <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ps.</HI> 55.12, 13, 14.</NOTE> <HI>It was not a profest enemy,</HI> saith <HI>Dauid, that did me this wrong: for then could I well haue brooked it: but it was thou, my guide, my companion, my sworne brother</HI>; as we say. So there is nothing that God taketh to heart more, or can worse endure, than <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esay</HI> 24.5. <HI>Ier.</HI> 3.20. <HI>&amp;</HI> 5.23. <HI>&amp;</HI> 11.10, 11.</NOTE> <HI>disloialtie</HI> and <HI>breach of couenants</HI> in those that bee in league with him. <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ierem.</HI> 34.17, 18.</NOTE> <HI>Those,</HI> saith hee, <HI>that haue violated the couenant which they solemnly made with me, when they</HI> <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ritus, qualis ille Genes.</HI> 15.9, 10, 17.</NOTE> <HI>cut the calfe in twaine, and passed betweene the two sides of it; I proscribe them to the famine, the sword, and the plague; and their carkases shall lie rotting aboue ground vnburied.</HI> <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Eccles.</HI> 5.5.</NOTE> Better not <HI>to make couenant</HI> with God at all, than <HI>to make, and not keepe.</HI></P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Vse</HI> 1. <HI>Examination.</HI></NOTE>From hence then may wee learne how to trie and examine the <HI>sinceritie,</HI> and the <HI>soundnesse</HI> of our <HI>Faith.</HI> <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 13.5.</NOTE> <HI>Trie your selues,</HI> saith the Apostle, <HI>whether you be in the Faith: whether</HI> you <HI>bee sound or</HI> <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>vnsound.</HI> (The word would not be translated <HI>reprobates,</HI> as we commonly vse that <HI>tearme.</HI>) Here is a <HI>Touchstone</HI> to trie it by. If our <HI>Faith</HI> and <HI>Con∣fidence in Christ</HI> be accompanied with <HI>fidelitie</HI> and <HI>faithfulnesse vnto Christ:</HI> if we be carefull as well to obserue what hee requireth of vs, as to expect what he promiseth. It is <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Chrysostom. in</HI> 1. <HI>Cor. hom.</HI> 2. <HI>Fides Deum indiuiduat.</HI></NOTE> <HI>the Nature of Faith,</HI> saith <HI>Chrysostome, to single out God</HI>; to make him as <HI>Thomas</HI> speaketh, <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iohn</HI> 20.28.</NOTE> <HI>My Lord, and my God:</HI> and as to <HI>single out God</HI> himselfe, so to apply his <HI>promises</HI> in particular to the <HI>faithfull</HI> partie: <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Galat.</HI> 2.20.</NOTE> <HI>Who hath lo∣ued me,</HI> saith the Apostle, <HI>and giuen himselfe for me.</HI> But wee must know withall, that true Faith is carefull as well to apply <HI>Gods</HI> <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>precepts,</HI> as his
<PB N="7" REF="7"/>
<NOTE N="“" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>promises.</HI> <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 27.8.</NOTE> <HI>When thou saist, Seeke my face; my soule answereth thee againe, Thy Face, Lord, will I seeke.</HI> Yea, to that end saith <HI>Chrysostome,</HI> doth the Apostle make that particular application of <HI>Gods grace and goodnesse</HI> to himselfe, <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Chrysost. ad Stelech. &amp; in Gen. hom.</HI> 34.</NOTE> to imply thereby his owne particular <HI>engagement to God</HI> for it. And it is no true <HI>Faith</HI> that regardeth not the one as well as the other. Hence it is, that it is said of some, that <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Act.</HI> 6.7.</NOTE> <HI>they became obedient to the faith:</HI> and of the <HI>Romanes,</HI> that <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Rom.</HI> 6.17.</NOTE> <HI>they had from the very heart obeyed the forme of Doctrine deliuered vnto them:</HI> or (if you will) <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>that they were bound vnto.</HI> Who are cōmended also more than once for their <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Rom.</HI> 1.5. <HI>&amp;</HI> 16.26.</NOTE> <HI>obe∣dience of faith,</HI> or their <HI>faithfull obedience.</HI> Which <HI>faithfull obedience</HI> is <HI>a sure note of sound faith</HI>; nor can it be <HI>true faith</HI> where such <HI>obedience</HI> is wanting. Then may wee know our <HI>Faith</HI> to be sound and sincere, when our <HI>faith in Christ</HI> breedeth and pro∣duceth in vs a <HI>faithfulnesse vnto Christ,</HI> a careful∣nesse to please him, <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><HI>Rom.</HI> 8.9, 14. <HI>Galat.</HI> 2.20. <HI>&amp;</HI> 5.25.</NOTE> a willingnesse to obey him, to be guided and ruled by him.</P>
<P>But alas,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Vse</HI> 2. <HI>Conuiction.</HI></NOTE> how many will bee found, to haue <HI>no true faith,</HI> who yet make profession of Faith, if they be brought to this <HI>Touchstone,</HI> if they come to this <HI>triall.</HI> Euery one is ready to say with him in the Gospell, <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Mark.</HI> 6.24.</NOTE> <HI>I beleeue, Lord.</HI> But, <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Thess.</HI> 3.2.</NOTE> <HI>All men,</HI> saith the Apostle, <HI>haue not faith.</HI> No: <HI>all haue not Faith,</HI> that make profession of Faith. How ap∣peareth that, may some say? Surely, because as the same Apostle saith else-where, <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><HI>Rom.</HI> 10.17.</NOTE> <HI>All obey not the Gospell:</HI> <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Thess.</HI> 1.8.</NOTE> all obserue not the <HI>rules</HI> of it. For how many <HI>professe the faith of Christ,</HI> that yet are whol∣ly <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ephes.</HI> 4.18. <HI>Philip.</HI> 3.18, 19. <HI>Rom.</HI> 16.18. <HI>Christum l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ngua si crepat, cum vita neget, non est fides, sed hypocrisis. Cy∣priani nomine de dupl. martyr.</HI></NOTE> <HI>estranged from the life of Christ?</HI> How many
<PB N="8" REF="8"/>
thousands (millions, I might say) bee there, that hauing <HI>giuen vp their names vnto Christ,</HI> and <HI>made solemne vowes and couenants in Baptisme</HI> with him, neuer so much as once thinke on (much lesse haue any care of performing or making good) those so∣lemne <HI>vowes and promises</HI> that then they made, the <HI>bonds</HI> they entred into in their <HI>Baptisme?</HI> And how are they <HI>Christians</HI> that <HI>keepe no faith with Christ?</HI> And yet will such be counted <HI>Christians</HI> as well as the best: and are readie enough to vaunt of, and presume on their <HI>Christendome,</HI> as if <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ita quidam om∣nibus fidem Christi∣anam etiam cum mala vita tenenti∣bus salutem pro∣mittebāt: teste Aug. de Ciuit. l.</HI> 21. <HI>c.</HI> 21.</NOTE> in re∣gard thereof they were sure to doe well. But, to omit that this their <HI>confidence,</HI> is like that before touched vpon of the <HI>Iewes,</HI> which <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ierem.</HI> 7.8.</NOTE> the <HI>Prophet</HI> telleth them, <HI>should neuer stand them in stead:</HI> I would gladly know of some such, what it is that maketh him <HI>a Christian. My faith,</HI> peraduenture thou wilt say,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Vse</HI> 3. <HI>Admonition.</HI></NOTE> <HI>in Christ.</HI> Yea, but that <HI>Faith,</HI> as hath beene shewed, that is not accompanied with <HI>faithfulnesse,</HI> is no true, it is but <HI>a false and a counter∣feit faith:</HI> Nor can <HI>a false and a counterfeit faith</HI> make (at the best, and the most) but <HI>a counterfeit Chri∣stian;</HI> <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Christiani nomi∣ne, non vita, non moribus. Aug. in Psal.</HI> 30.</NOTE> <HI>a Christian in Name,</HI> but <HI>not in deed.</HI></P>
<P>If therefore we desire <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Aliud est enim esse quod diceris, ali∣ud dici quod non <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s. Chrysost. n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m. de sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, fid. char. Quid autem proderit ap∣pellari quod non es? quid nomen prodest, ubi res non est? Aug. in</HI> 1. <HI>Ioan.</HI> 5. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n. Chrys<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st. orat.</HI> 38.</NOTE> to be <HI>counted</HI> what we are <HI>called,</HI> let vs approue the sinceritie of our <HI>faith in Christ</HI> by our <HI>fidelitie and faithfulnesse vnto Christ.</HI> If we desire to haue benefit by our <HI>faith in him,</HI> let vs be carefull to keepe <HI>our faith with him.</HI> If we looke that he should keepe <HI>couenants</HI> with vs, let vs be sure that we keepe <HI>couenant</HI> with him. <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 25.10.</NOTE> <HI>All the waies of God are mercy and truth,</HI> saith the Psal∣mist, but to whom? <HI>to those that keepe his Couenant and his Testimonies.</HI> And, <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 103.18.</NOTE> <HI>The mercy of God is
<PB N="9" REF="8"/>
for euer and euer, vpon those that keepe Couenants with him, and that thinke vpon his Commandements to doe them.</HI> But it is an vnequall thing for vs, to expect that he should keepe couenants with vs, when we haue no care to keepe the like with him. An vnreasonable thing were it for <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><HI>Hosh.</HI> 2.5, 8, 9.</NOTE> <HI>a Wife</HI> to re∣quire meanes of maintenance from her <HI>Husband,</HI> when she liueth disloially, and keepeth with ano∣ther man: or for a <HI>Seruant</HI> to expect the <HI>Wages</HI> co∣uenanted from his <HI>Master,</HI> when he keepeth no <HI>co∣uenants</HI> at all with his <HI>Master,</HI> when he refuseth to doe his <HI>worke.</HI> Nor haue they any reason to ex∣pect <HI>Life</HI> from <HI>Christ,</HI> when they die, that haue no care to keepe <HI>Faith</HI> with <HI>Christ,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Branch</HI> 2. <HI>Extent.</HI></NOTE> while they liue.</P>
<P>But how long must this <HI>faithfulnesse</HI> of ours be continued? <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Non ad annum, vel ad tempus, sed in aeternum divi∣no te mancipasti famulatui. Bern. e∣pist.</HI> 254.</NOTE> Not for <HI>a day or two</HI>; as some for∣mally would seeme to obserue it, when they re∣paire to <HI>Gods board</HI> once a yeere; no, nor for <HI>a yeere or two</HI> onely; but, as in the mutuall plighting of <HI>Faith</HI> in <HI>Wedlocke</HI> it is wont to be said, <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Rom.</HI> 7.2. 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 7.39.</NOTE> <HI>till death vs doe part</HI>; so long as life lasteth, <HI>vnto death,</HI> <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Clem. Alex. in protraept.</HI></NOTE> <HI>to the last gaspe:</HI> as it is afterward expounded, <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vers.</HI> 25.</NOTE> <HI>vntill I come;</HI> <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vers</HI> 26.</NOTE> <HI>vnto the end.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Christian fidelitie must continue to the last.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Point</HI> 2.</NOTE></P>
<P>So <HI>Dauid,</HI> <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 119.112.</NOTE> <HI>I haue applied mine heart to fulfill thy statutes alwaies, euen to the end.</HI> And, <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Hebr.</HI> 3.6.</NOTE> <HI>His house we are, if we hold fast the confidence, and the reioy∣cing of hope to the end:</HI> and, <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Heb.</HI> 3.14.</NOTE> <HI>we are partakers of him,</HI> (or, <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>i. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, ut Cap.</HI> 1.9. h. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Rom.</HI> 8.17. <HI>socij. consortes. Pis∣cat.</HI></NOTE> <HI>fellow-heires with him</HI>) <HI>if we keepe firme</HI> <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, <HI>i. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>: quae <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> esse dicitur, cap.</HI> 11.1. <HI>Idem. principium autem sive initi∣um fidei, i. quam profiteri c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pimus, &amp; qua initiati su∣mus fide.</HI></NOTE> <HI>the confidence begun in vs to the end.</HI> And looke what is there said of our <HI>confidence</HI> in, the same is required in our <HI>faithfulnesse vnto Christ,</HI> in <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vers.</HI> 26.</NOTE> <HI>the
<PB N="10" REF="9"/>
keeping of his workes</HI>; that must also be <HI>to the end.</HI> For euen one branch it is also of <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 44.17, 18.</NOTE> our <HI>Faith vnto Christ,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Necessitie of Perseuerance</HI></NOTE> <HI>to hold fast our faith in Christ,</HI> and the pro∣fession of it, against all <HI>oppositions,</HI> and all <HI>opposites</HI> whatsoeuer.</P>
<P>Now as the <HI>necessitie</HI> before of this <HI>fidelitie,</HI> so the <HI>necessitie</HI> of such <HI>constancie</HI> and continuance may appeare;<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 1.</NOTE> if we shall consider, that</P>
<P N="1">1. <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><HI>Non perseuerare cultus est mutilus. Bern. epist.</HI> 24 <HI>&amp;</HI> 165. <HI>&amp; de temp.</HI> 56.</NOTE> <HI>Not to perseuere is a curtailed sacrifice; a mai∣med seruice,</HI> and such as God therefore will not accept of. <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><HI>Leuit.</HI> 22.21, 22.</NOTE> No <HI>maimed</HI> beast might be presented for sacrifice. That that was offered to God must haue both <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 69.31.</NOTE> <HI>horne</HI> and <HI>hoofe:</HI> yet it must not want so much as <HI>the taile:</HI> for <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><HI>Leuit.</HI> 3.9.</NOTE> <HI>the taile-peece</HI> by name is in the sacred <HI>Rituals</HI> disposed of. It being there∣by intimated, say <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><HI>Caudam hostiae offerre praecipimur, ut omne bonum quod incepimus, e∣tiam perse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eranti sine compleamus. Greg. mor. l.</HI> 1. <HI>c.</HI> 40. <HI>Bene immolat, qui sacrificium bo∣ni operis ad finem perducit. Idem in Euang.</HI> 25. <HI>Caput cum cauda offerri jubetur, quia sine perseuerantia nihil placet. Rad. Ardens. in</HI> 1.40 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> some of the <HI>Ancients,</HI> that <HI>no holy course of life is accepted,</HI> if it be <HI>not concluded and closed vp with a good end.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Indicium maxi∣mum est malae men∣tis st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctuatio. Sen. epist.</HI> 120.</NOTE> <HI>Inconstancie</HI> and <HI>instabilitie</HI> is <HI>an Argument of vnsoundnesse and insinceritie.</HI> <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Prou.</HI> 17.17.</NOTE> <HI>A friend,</HI> saith <HI>Salomon, loueth for euer.</HI> And, <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Aristot. rhet. l.</HI> 2. <HI>c.</HI> 21. <HI>&amp; Eudem. l.</HI> 7. <HI>c.</HI> 2. <HI>Non est amicus jugiter qui non amat. Amicitia quae aliquando desmere potuit, nunquam vera fuit. Martin. Dum. de morib. ex Aug. ad Iulian. Com. de poen. d.</HI> 2.</NOTE> <HI>Hee was neuer a true Friend,</HI> saith the Heathen man, <HI>that euer ceaseth to be a Friend.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 2.</NOTE> In like manner, those that be <HI>true-hearted</HI> to God, will keepe constantly with him. <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 78.8, 10, 37, 57.</NOTE> Nor were they euer <HI>sincere</HI> and <HI>vpright with him,</HI> that euer leaue and giue ouer their loialtie vnto him.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 3.</NOTE></P>
<P N="3">3. <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Christus perseve∣ravit pro te. Tu ergò pro illo perseveres. Bern. de temp.</HI> 56. <HI>&amp; de <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on. deser. Ibi tu figas cur∣sus tui metam, ubi Christus posuit suam. Idem. ep.</HI> 254.</NOTE> <HI>Christ perseuered for vs</HI>▪ and therefore
<PB N="11" REF="9"/>
<HI>ought we to perseuere for him.</HI> Such <HI>a Friend</HI> was he to vs, as <HI>Salomon</HI> describeth. <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iohn</HI> 13.1.</NOTE> <HI>Whom he once loued,</HI> saith the <HI>Euangelist, he loued them to the last.</HI> Hee was not <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Heb.</HI> 12.2.</NOTE> <HI>the Beginner onely,</HI> but <HI>the Finisher of our saluation.</HI> He held out to the last gaspe, till <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Consummatū est. Iohn</HI> 19.30.</NOTE> <HI>all were consummated,</HI> till all were done that was to be done for the full effecting and the finishing of it.</P>
<P N="4">4. It is <HI>a Rule</HI> in the <HI>Ciuill Law,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 4.</NOTE> that <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Factum no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> dici∣tur, quod non per∣severat. Pet. Fon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Reg. Iur.</HI></NOTE> <HI>it is as nothing that holdeth not.</HI> Yea that, <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Nihil dicitur fu∣isse factum, quam∣diu aliquid agen∣dum superest. Ibid. ex Cod. Iustin. In∣cassum bonum agi∣tur, si ante termi∣num vitae desera∣tur. Greg. m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r. l.</HI> 2. <HI>c.</HI> 40. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Basil. Cas. hom.</HI> 5.</NOTE> <HI>Nothing is held done,</HI> because all that is done is as good as nothing, as <HI>not done, as long as ought remaineth to bee done.</HI> <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Testamentum <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> perfectum fuerit, nullum est. Gloss. ad Grat. de poen. d.</HI> 3. <HI>ex Cod. Iustin.</HI></NOTE> <HI>A will vnfinished is no will: a deed,</HI> vnlesse it bee <HI>signed, sealed,</HI> and <HI>deliuered,</HI> is <HI>no deed.</HI> In a Lease made vpon condition of diuers Acts, either suc∣cessiuely to be done, or yeerely to be reiterated, if all but one be done, and that onely omitted, or all be obserued for many yeeres together, but default then be once made, <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Nisi totum solua∣tur, nihil soluitur. Neque enim abso∣lutus est debitor, qui multa reddit, sed qui omnia Greg. Mor. l.</HI> 22. <HI>c.</HI> 6.</NOTE> that one faile, or once fai∣ling, is enough to make all the rest of no effect, and to cause a forfeiture of the whole.</P>
<P N="5">5. <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Cedunt prima po∣stremis. Tacit. An∣nal. l.</HI> 13. <HI>Vltima primis cedunt. Bern. de pass. Dom. c.</HI> 14.</NOTE> <HI>The former part</HI> of our life <HI>yeeldeth vnto the latter:</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 5.</NOTE> and <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vita posterior priori praeiudicat. Hieron. ad Furiam.</HI></NOTE> <HI>the latter part</HI> of our life <HI>carrieth it away from the former.</HI> <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ezech.</HI> 18.21, 22.</NOTE> <HI>If the wicked man,</HI> saith God, <HI>returne from his wicked courses, all his for∣mer iniquities shall be forgotten, and shall be mentio∣ned no more.</HI> And on the other side, <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ibid.</HI> 24. <HI>Neque enim ex praeteritis, sed ex praesentibus judicantur. Hieron. in Ezech. c.</HI> 26. <HI>vides profunda oblivione sepeliri, quae perseuerantia non insignivit. Bern. de grad. obed.</HI></NOTE> <HI>If the righ∣teous man,</HI> saith hee, <HI>giue ouer his good courses; all the righteous deeds that hee hath done shall doe him
<PB N="12" REF="10"/>
no good; but for the euill that then hee doth, shall he die.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 6.</NOTE></P>
<P N="6">6 <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Terminus ad quē dat appellationem. Non quaeruntur in Christianis initia vel exord<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a, sed fi∣nis &amp; perseveran∣tia. Paulus male co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣pit, sed benè fini∣vit. Iudas benà coe∣pit, sed malè fini∣vit. Ex Hieron. Bern. ad sororem. c.</HI> 20.</NOTE> <HI>The end of each thing is all in all.</HI> <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 37.37.</NOTE> <HI>Marke the end of the iust man.</HI> And, <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 73.17.</NOTE> <HI>I saw the end of these men.</HI> It is that that maketh or marreth all. <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us finis bonus est, ipsum quoque bonum est. Bern. in Psal.</HI> 91. <HI>ser.</HI> 17.</NOTE> <HI>Euerie thing,</HI> we say, <HI>is well, that endeth well.</HI> And indeed, <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">H. Smith on <HI>Psal.</HI> 90.12. <HI>Tota vita discendum est mori. Sen. de brev. vit. c.</HI> 7.</NOTE> <HI>the maine end and aime of our whole life,</HI> should be this, <HI>to make a good end of our life</HI>; to put a good conclusion to it, <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Pet.</HI> 3.14.</NOTE> <HI>that we may be found</HI> then <HI>holy and vnblameable in peace.</HI></P>
<P N="7">7. <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Perseverantia sola virtutum coro∣natur. Bern. epist.</HI> 32. <HI>&amp;</HI> 109. <HI>&amp;</HI> 129. <HI>&amp;</HI> 353. <HI>&amp; de <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</HI> 56. <HI>&amp;</HI> 114.</NOTE> <HI>It is perseuerance alone that carrieth away the Crowne.</HI> Vnlesse we be <HI>faithfull to death,</HI> there is <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Finis, non p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gna, corona<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Id<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m. de pass. Dom. c.</HI> 14. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Themistocles. Plut. apoph.</HI></NOTE> no <HI>Crowne of life</HI> for vs.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 7.</NOTE> <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><HI>Heb.</HI> 12.1.</NOTE> <HI>Christianitie</HI> is com∣pared to <HI>a race.</HI> <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 9.24.</NOTE> <HI>In a race,</HI> saith the Apostle, <HI>all that runne, win not.</HI> Those onely get the <HI>Garland</HI> that get first to the <HI>Goale.</HI> But in this spirituall <HI>Race,</HI> saith <HI>Chrysostome,</HI> <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Non qui primus ven<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>t, sed quicunque pervenerit. Chrys. nomine de fide, spe, char. tom.</HI> 4.</NOTE> <HI>not he that commeth first,</HI> but <HI>each one that holdeth out to the last,</HI> is crowned. <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 24.13. <HI>Marke</HI> 13.13. <HI>Non qui <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>perit, sed qui perseveraverit. Bern. de grad. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. Non in hoantibus, sed p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rseverantibus praemium promittitur. Isidor. de sum. bon. l.</HI> 2. <HI>c.</HI> 7. <HI>Nec coepisse, vel facere, sed profi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere virtutis est. Hier. Gloss. ad Matt.</HI> 10.</NOTE> <HI>He that perseuereth to the end, shall be saued.</HI> <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Galat.</HI> 3.4.</NOTE> He that doth not, loseth all that hee hath done. <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Basil. Caes. hom.</HI> 5. <HI>Nec ad bravium victoriae pervenit, qui in magna parte sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctaculi velociter currit, si juxta metas veniens, in hoc quod reliquum est, deficit. Greg. mor. l.</HI> 22. <HI>c.</HI> 6.</NOTE> <HI>Com∣ming but a foot short, may make a man misse the prize,</HI> and lose the wager he ran for. As <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Basil. Caes. ibid. Nec ad quaelibet de∣s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nata loca pergentibus <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ndo pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>desset longum iter carpere, si non etiam totum valerent consummare. Greg. ibid.</HI></NOTE> in <HI>iournying</HI> al∣so,
<PB N="13" REF="10"/>
a man doth but lose all his labour,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 8.</NOTE> if he get not to his iournies end.</P>
<P N="8">8. <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Deus aeter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us: praemia aeterna. Quid levitati &amp; aetern<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tati? Aug.</HI></NOTE> <HI>God himselfe is eternall,</HI> from whom wee expect our <HI>reward:</HI> and the <HI>reward</HI> that we looke for, is it selfe also <HI>euerlasting.</HI> But <HI>what hath leuitie and inconstancie,</HI> saith <HI>Augustine, to doe with eterni∣tie?</HI> <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Aeternitatis <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ma∣ginem perseveran∣tia prae se fert. So∣la est cui aeternitas redditur. Bern. de consider. l.</HI> 5.</NOTE> Our fidelitie must therefore hold out to the last, if we desire to haue an euerlasting reward. Yea most equall it is, that we continue to the end, if we looke to enioy that <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Gaudium in fine, sed gaudium sine fine. Id<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m de di∣vers.</HI> 19.</NOTE> <HI>ioy and blisse in the end,</HI> that shall be <HI>without end.</HI></P>
<P>And,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Vse</HI> 1. <HI>Information.</HI></NOTE> is it so then, that without such perseue∣rance nothing in this kinde is auaileable? How mi∣serable then and deplorable is the stare of those that with <HI>Ephesus,</HI> <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Apoc.</HI> 2.4, 5.</NOTE> <HI>forsake their first loue</HI>; that with the <HI>Galatians,</HI> <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Galat.</HI> 5.7.</NOTE> <HI>run well a while,</HI> but then <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Frusta velociter currit, qui prius∣quam ad metas ve∣nerit, deficit. Greg. mor. l.</HI> 2. <HI>c.</HI> 40.</NOTE> giue ouer; that <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Galat.</HI> 3.3.</NOTE> <HI>begin in the spirit, and end in the flesh</HI>; that <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Luke</HI> 9.62. <HI>Retro post aratrum aspicit, qui post ex∣ordia boni operis ad mala revertitur quae dorel▪ quit. Gre. in Ezech.</HI> 1. <HI>hom.</HI> 6.</NOTE> <HI>put their hand to Gods plough▪ and then looke backe againe,</HI> as <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Luke</HI> 17.32. <HI>Gen.</HI> 19.26.</NOTE> <HI>Lots Wife</HI> did toward <HI>Sodome</HI>; that with <HI>Demas,</HI> <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Coloss.</HI> 4.14. <HI>Phil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m.</HI> 24.</NOTE> <HI>follow Paul</HI> a while; but then <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Tim.</HI> 4.10.</NOTE> <HI>leaue him</HI> againe <HI>to embrace the world</HI>; that <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Pet.</HI> 2.20, 21, 22.</NOTE> <HI>ha∣uing escaped the defilements of the flesh, and the world, by the acknowledgement of our Lord and Sa∣uiour Iesus Christ, doe afterward turne away from the holy Commandement,</HI> and <HI>returne</HI> <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>Prou.</HI> 26.11.</NOTE> <HI>like Dogges to their vomit,</HI> to their former filth, and <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ambus est, &amp; poeticum spirat.</HI></NOTE> <HI>like swine after washing to the wallowing againe in the mire?</HI> They are not onely in as bad ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e as before, (and yet were <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ephes.</HI> 2.1, 2, 3. <HI>&amp;</HI> 4.17, 18.</NOTE> that bad enough) but in worse case now than euer. <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Pet.</HI> 2.20. <HI>Matt.</HI> 12.45.</NOTE> <HI>Their latter estate,</HI> saith S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Peter,</HI> is <HI>worse than their first was.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="14" REF="11"/><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Vse</HI> 2. <HI>Admonition.</HI></NOTE>And let it admonish vs therefore <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vers.</HI> 25. <HI>Chap.</HI> 3.11.</NOTE> <HI>to hold fast what we haue;</HI> <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Acts</HI> 11.23.</NOTE> <HI>to cleaue vnto God with full purpose of heart</HI>; and <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Hebr.</HI> 6.11.</NOTE> <HI>vse all diligence, to keepe firme our assurance of hope to the end.</HI> For as it were better for vs neuer to haue entred into <HI>Couenant</HI> with God, than <HI>to make Couenants</HI> with him, and <HI>not to keepe</HI> them: So <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ille plus delin∣quit, qui interrup∣tam causam dimit∣tit, quam qui nun∣quam ad illam per∣veni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Bromyard in oper. trivio ex Au∣thent. collat.</HI> 8. <HI>de Litig.</HI></NOTE> it had beene better for vs neuer to haue made shew of obseruing them, if at any time after we cease and giue ouer the obseruation of them againe. And therefore <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Pet.</HI> 3.17.</NOTE> <HI>seeing that wee know these things,</HI> saith <HI>S. Peter</HI>; since that we see and haue heard what <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us praeiculum ad deteriora rede∣undi. Sen. ep.</HI> 72. <HI>Iohn</HI> 5.14. <HI>Gravi∣us aegrotant, qui cum levati morbo viderentur, in eum de integro incidunt. C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c. famil. l.</HI> 12. <HI>ep.</HI> 30.</NOTE> the <HI>danger</HI> of it is, <HI>let vs take heed lest we be drawne away by the error of the wic∣ked; and so fall from our stedfastnesse and our faith∣fulnesse to our Lord Christ Iesus.</HI></P>
<P>And because, as <HI>Gregorie</HI> saith, <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Quid ista prode∣rit praenosse, si non contingat evadere? Greg in Euang.</HI> 36.</NOTE> <HI>it is to little pur∣pose for vs,</HI> to <HI>be informed how dangerous it is, if wee be not taught how to preuent the danger:</HI> It shall not be amisse to adde some few <HI>Rules</HI> for the furthe∣ring of vs vnto perseuerance in those religious courses that either we are to enter, or are in some measure entred into already.</P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg"><P><HI>Rules for Furtherance. Meanes of Perseuerance.</HI></P>
<P><HI>Meanes</HI> 1.</P></NOTE>Wouldst thou therefore <HI>continue faithfull to Christ thy Master,</HI> and <HI>hold out</HI> in thy <HI>Christian course to the end?</HI></P>
<P N="1">1. <HI>Enter with resolution.</HI> <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Luke</HI> 14.28, 29, 30.</NOTE> Cast vp thine ac∣counts before hand. <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Et aequissimum <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>era; &amp; ad ini∣quissimum te para. Sen. ep.</HI> 24.</NOTE> Fore-cast the worst, and prepare for it. <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Luke</HI> 14.33.</NOTE> <HI>Vnlesse a man,</HI> saith our Sauiour, <HI>leaue</HI> (<NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Quantum ad affectum, licet non quantum ad effectum. Lu∣dolf. de Vit. Christ. proposito tenus. Adrian. qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dlibet. q.</HI> 10.</NOTE> <HI>in resolution</HI> at least) <HI>all that euer hee hath,</HI> <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Luke</HI> 14.26.</NOTE> <HI>father and mother, and wife, and children, and land,
<PB N="15" REF="11"/>
and liuing, and his owne life too; he can be none of my Disciple.</HI> The want of this is that, that maketh many a one turne head and set saile backe againe, so soone as they see stormes towards, and opposi∣tion begin to be made: they neuer were minded to goe further, than they found the way cleare before them. It fareth with them as with those <HI>that goe to sea vpon pleasure,</HI> <NOTE N="“" PLACE="marg"><HI>Nondum era<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tempestas, sed ja<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> inclinatio maris, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> subinde crebrio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> fluctus. Cepi guber<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>natorem rogare, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> me in aliquo litor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> exponeret. Senec epist.</HI> 53.</NOTE> who no sooner see a blacke cloud rise, or finde the sea begin to worke, especial∣ly <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Nausea me segni torquebat. Instit itaque gubernatori &amp; illum, velle nollet, coegi ut l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tus peteret. Ibid.</HI></NOTE> if they begin to grow Sea-sick with it, but they are crying by and by to make backe with all haste to the shoare; whereas <HI>the Merchant</HI> or <HI>Sea-man</HI> <NOTE N="†" PLACE="marg"><HI>Cui propositum <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> navem▪ in portun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> perducere. Idem e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pist.</HI> 85.</NOTE> that is <HI>bound for his Port,</HI> will not be driuen backe with a storme or two, (hee looked before for it) with a little foule weather, or a little sea-sicknesse, but goeth on through faire and foule,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Meanes</HI> 2.</NOTE> till hee hath made his voiage, till he haue gotten to his Port.</P>
<P N="2">2. <HI>Labour for sinceritie.</HI> Endeuour to bee that inwardly, that thou makest profession of outward∣ly. Else there is no hope of continuance. For <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Greg▪ Naz. Nihil fictu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> diuturnum. Amb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> offic. l.</HI> 2. <HI>c.</HI> 22▪ <HI>Caduca sunt quae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> cunque fucata sun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Cyprian. ad Donat▪</HI></NOTE> <HI>no∣thing</HI> that is <HI>counterfeit,</HI> will <HI>last long. Counterfeit pearles</HI> may make <HI>a faire shew</HI> for some time; but their <HI>lustre</HI> will <HI>not last.</HI> And this is one maine cause of the <HI>Apostasie</HI> of many, they were neuer but <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 78.37. <HI>Hosh.</HI> 6.4.</NOTE> <HI>hollow-hearted</HI>; they were neuer sound at the heart. <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Mattth.</HI> 13.20▪ 21. <HI>Nam quod ra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> dicatum est etiam ardente Sole ares<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> cere non potest. So<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le nutritur &amp; vi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rescit, non arescit Aug. in Psalm.</HI> 43▪ <HI>&amp; in</HI> 1 <HI>Ioan. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI> 3.</NOTE> <HI>The seed on the stonie ground,</HI> therefore <HI>wi∣thereth away</HI> when the heat of the yeere commeth, because <HI>it had no root.</HI> And therefore <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Tim.</HI> 4.1.</NOTE> <HI>many shall fall away,</HI> when <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Tim.</HI> 3.1.</NOTE> <HI>the dangerous daies come,</HI> that had made a goodly shew of profession before; because they had (when they were at the very best) <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Tim.</HI> 3.5.</NOTE> <HI>an out∣ward shew and semblance of godlinesse</HI> onely, but
<PB N="16" REF="12"/>
<HI>inward power of it.</HI> Yea, that is one cause why <NOTE PLACE="marg">Reade the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of <HI>Sanders</HI> and <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ndleton,</HI> in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Acts and Mo∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ments.</NOTE> many that haue seemed very forward men in <HI>times of peace,</HI> haue in <HI>times of persecution</HI> fallen cleane away, when some others that made no such great shew before, haue stucke close to it. There was <HI>an outward blase</HI> onely in the one, that was therefore by and by blowen out: there was <HI>an inward sparke</HI> in the other, that being blowne vp by the bellowes and blast of opposition, hath broken forth, and blased out to the won∣derment of those, that little looked for such things from such, as had made no greater flourish be∣fore.</P>
<P N="3"><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Meanes</HI> 3.</NOTE>3. <HI>Be carefull to</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Tim.</HI> 1.19.</NOTE> <HI>keepe a good Conscience.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ebr.</HI> 13.18.</NOTE> <HI>Hol∣ding the mysterie of faith in a good conscience</HI>; saith the Apostle; <NOTE PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Tim.</HI> 3.9. 1. <HI>Tim.</HI> 1.19.</NOTE> <HI>which some casting away, haue made shipwracke of Faith.</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Perkins</HI> of Con∣science.</NOTE> Hee compareth <HI>Conscience</HI> to <HI>a Ship</HI> or <HI>a Barke</HI>; and <HI>Faith</HI> to <HI>Treasure</HI> therein imbarqued; <NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Rectè itaque con∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ra Papam ratio∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>natur Nilus ep. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ess.</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> which must needs therefore mis∣carrie, if the <HI>Ship</HI> or <HI>Barke</HI> be castaway. And in this <HI>Barke, Sinnes against Conscience</HI> make foule breaches, which if they be not speedily repaired, (and that is not easily done neither) may soone vndoe all. Better it is to preuent them, than to hazzard the making of them good againe. The rather, because when they are growne frequent once, they bring a kinde of retchlesnesse with them. It is with our <HI>Conscience,</HI> as it is with our <HI>apparell.</HI> While it is fresh and faire, new, or new washt, we are very charie what wee leane against, where we sit, or what we touch with it; but when it is once soiled or sullied, we haue no such regard
<PB N="17" REF="12"/>
of it, we little passe what we doe with it, wee care not now where we cast it.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Meanes</HI> 4.</NOTE></P>
<P N="4">4. <HI>Slight no sinne</HI>; make light of no euill course. For to omit that <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Nihil leve quo Deus laeditur. Sal∣vian. de provid. l.</HI> 2.</NOTE> <HI>no sinne</HI> is <HI>light</HI> or <HI>little</HI> in it selfe. Some may seeme <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 7.3, 4.</NOTE> <HI>motes,</HI> and bee so tearmed in comparison of some other. But there is none but may well be deemed <HI>a beame,</HI> being considered in it selfe. As the <HI>earth,</HI> though but <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Terram hanc cum populis, &amp; urbibus, fluminibus, atque ambitu maris pun∣cti loco ponimus, ad universa referen∣tes. Sen. ad Marc. c.</HI> 20.</NOTE> <HI>a center</HI> or <HI>a point</HI> to the <HI>heauens,</HI> yet is an huge bodie of it selfe, <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ier.</HI> 31.37. <HI>Am∣bitus terrae totius, quae nobis immensa videtur, ad magni∣tudinem universi∣tatis instar brevis obtinet puncti. Am∣mian. hist. l.</HI> 15.</NOTE> by no art or skill of man exactly measurable. And againe, that in euery sinne, great or lesse, there is <HI>ranke poison</HI>; there are <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Peccatum quod∣que in se &amp; ex na∣tura sua mortale esse docet Gersees de vit. spirit. lect.</HI> 1. <HI>Idemque fatetur Ioan. Fisher Roff. Ep. in re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut. Lu∣ther. ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ic.</HI> 32. <HI>V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣dentur Vasquez. in Thom. tom.</HI> 1. <HI>disput.</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>42 <HI>num.</HI> 7<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> <HI>no sinnes</HI> that are <HI>in themselues not mortall,</HI> as the <HI>Popish</HI> sort imagine: <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 15.55, 56.</NOTE> <HI>a deadly sting</HI> there is in euery sinne; which <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI> 10.23. <HI>&amp;</HI> 14.9.</NOTE> may not therefore be dallied with. Not to stand, I say, vpon these things; euen those <HI>little sinnes,</HI> as wee reckon them, if wee giue way to them, will make way soone for greater. The <HI>Deuill</HI> vseth them (it is the comparison of <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Autor Oculi mo∣ralis.</HI></NOTE> an ancient Writer) as <HI>Theeues,</HI> some <HI>little Boy</HI> that they put in at a win∣dow; who though hee can doe no great matter of hurt himselfe, yet when he is once in, can open, the doores and let them in, that may both rob the house and kill all that are in it. Or <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Idem. ibid.</HI></NOTE> as <HI>Hunt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> doe their <HI>little Beagles,</HI> which they ply <HI>the D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere</HI> withall till he be heated and blowen, and then clap they on their <HI>great Buck-hounds</HI> that may pull him downe and plucke out his throat. And indeed, in these smaller matters <HI>decay of grace</HI> first discoue∣reth it selfe, as <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Easly</HI> on <HI>Esay</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.5.</NOTE> <HI>the decay of a tree,</HI> appeareth first in the <HI>washie boughes</HI> or the <HI>twigs,</HI> and so by little
<PB N="18" REF="13"/>
and little goeth on further into the bigger armes, and at length pierceth into the <HI>maine bodie.</HI> And as we say, that <HI>a mans truth and honestie may be seene</HI> as well <HI>in a small matter,</HI> as in a greater: So <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Luke</HI> 16.10, 11.</NOTE> euen in these trifling things also, as they are commonly esteemed, as well as in weightier, may a mans vnfaithfulnesse be discouered. He hath hardly a faithfull heart vnto <HI>Christ,</HI> that counteth any thing <HI>a trifle that may tend to his dishonour</HI>; as <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Tim.</HI> 6.1. <HI>Tit.</HI> 2.10. <HI>Rom.</HI> 2.24.</NOTE> <HI>all sinne,</HI> in <HI>a Christian</HI> man especially, more or lesse doth.</P>
<P N="5">5. <HI>Be iealous of thine owne weaknesse▪ trust not</HI> too much <HI>to thine owne strength.</HI> <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><P><HI>Matth.</HI> 26.33, 34, 35. <HI>Iohn</HI> 13.37. <HI>Praesumps<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t nescio quid, quod in illo nondum erat. Aug. in Psal.</HI> 55. <HI>Pos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e se putavit, quod nondum potuit. Ber. de temp.</HI> 88.</P>
<P><HI>Meane</HI> 5.</P></NOTE> It was <HI>Peters</HI> ouer-sight, and we know how <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 26.73, 74.</NOTE> fouly he fell. And his example is left vpon record <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uina majo∣rum si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> cautela mi∣norum. Greg. mor. l.</HI> 33. <HI>c.</HI> 15. <HI>Scr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ae sunt enim rui∣nae priorum ad cau∣tel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m poster<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erum. Rad. Ardens post Trinit.</HI> 9. <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> naque debet red∣dere, non s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>qu. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> error ali<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nus. C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s∣siod. Var. l.</HI> 7. <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p.</HI> 2.</NOTE> to make vs the more warie. For this is the ruine of not a few; <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><P><HI>Multos imp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dit a firmitate praesump∣tio firmitatis. Aug. de verb. D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m.</HI> 13. <HI>Infirmior is est, qui suam non conside∣rat infirmitatem. Greg. registr. l.</HI> 6. <HI>indict.</HI> 15. <HI>ep.</HI> 4.</P>
<P><HI>Meanes</HI> 6.</P></NOTE> that they presume too much of their owne might, and so are bold to offer themselues vnto those prouocations and temptations, that proue many times their vtter ruine. They are <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Stella in Luc. c.</HI> 11.</NOTE> like <HI>sicke folkes,</HI> who when they haue had a good day or two, think that they are perfectly well againe, and make bold to cast off their sicke kerchiefe, or put on thinner apparell, or venture out into the fresh aire, and by such meanes fall into relapses, which they hardly, or neuer (it may be) recouer againe.</P>
<P N="6">6. <HI>Shun euill occasions.</HI> <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><HI>Non vitat peccatum, qui non vitat occasiones peccatorum. Stell. in Luc.</HI> 11. <HI>&amp; Me∣lanchth. loc. commun.</HI> 22. <HI>Exponens se periculo peccati mortalis, peccat mortaliter. Gerson∣de vit. spirit. lect.</HI> 4.</NOTE> <HI>He shunneth not sinne</HI> as he should, <HI>who is not carefull to eschew the occasi∣ons of sinne,</HI> as well as the sinne it selfe. By care∣lesnesse
<PB N="19" REF="13"/>
in this kinde many fall into relapses. Which S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Peter</HI> also intimateth, when he saith of some that <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Pet.</HI> 2.20.</NOTE> <HI>hauing escaped the defilements of the world, by the acknowledgement of Christ,</HI> that is, by the profession of <HI>Christianitie; by being</HI> <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Sae∣pe familiaritas im∣plicavit. Saepe oc∣casio peccati volun∣tatem fecit peccan∣di. Isidor. Soliloq. l.</HI> 2.</NOTE> <HI>entangled, they come to be the second time ouercome.</HI> As <HI>Dauid</HI> saith of himselfe, <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ps<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l.</HI> 142.3.</NOTE> <HI>In the way that I walke, haue they hid their snare for me. Satan</HI> hath his <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Omne iter istius vitae plenum laque∣ort mest. Ambr. de bon. mort. c.</HI> 6.</NOTE> <HI>snares</HI> and his <HI>ginnes</HI> set <HI>in all our waies</HI> for vs, in our meat, our drinke, our apparell, our recreation, our lawfull delights, our trading, our trafficke, our buying and selling, &amp;c. In regard whereof, as those that <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iob</HI> 22.10.</NOTE> <HI>walke among snares,</HI> we had need <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Prou.</HI> 4.25, 26.</NOTE> <HI>tread wa∣rily,</HI> and <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ephes.</HI> 5.15.</NOTE> <HI>walke wisely,</HI> and <HI>circumspectly,</HI> and <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Hebr.</HI> 12.13.</NOTE> <HI>make straight steps to our feet.</HI> Remembring that <HI>Satan</HI> preuaileth more against those that make any conscience of their courses, by the vnlawfull, im∣moderate, or inordinate vsage of things in them∣selues lawfull, than by the practise of things meere∣ly euill and vnlawfull in themselues. And that it is safer, and easier by much ordinarily, <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Nam vitare pla∣gas in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>moris ne la∣ciaris Non ita dif∣ficile est, quàm cap∣tum retibus ipsis Exire, &amp; validos veneris perrumpe∣re nodos. Lucret. de rer. nat. l.</HI> 4.</NOTE> <HI>to passe by the snare,</HI> than <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><HI>Non avis utiliter viscatis ef<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ugit alis: Non bene de laxis cassibus <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>xit aper. Saucius arrepto pi∣scis retinetur ab ha∣m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Ovid. art. l.</HI> 1.</NOTE> <HI>to winde out</HI> when we are once wrought in. You know what was <HI>Eues</HI> ouerthrow. <HI>Satan</HI> suggested vnto her, that though shee were forbidden to eat of it, yet it was not vnlawfull to looke on it. And so by <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Gen.</HI> 3.7. <HI>Oculos tendo, non manum. Non est interdictū ne videam, sed ne comedam. Bern. de humil. grad.</HI> 4.</NOTE> gazing on it, she came to haue a liking to it, and from taking liking to it, fell to a longing after it, she had <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Etsi culpa non est, culpa tamen occasio est <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> &amp; indicium est commissae, &amp; causa commit tendae. Bern. ibid.</NOTE> tasted it in her heart, ere it came into her hand, and so at length by ea∣ting
<PB N="20" REF="14"/>
of it, <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Hausit virus pe∣ritu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a, &amp; perituros paritura. Ibid.</HI></NOTE> she tooke in that that proued the bane both of her and hers. In regard whereof, the Pro∣phet promiseth eternall happinesse with God to that man alone, <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esay</HI> 33.14, 15.</NOTE> who not onely <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 15.2.</NOTE> <HI>speaketh truly and walketh vprightly,</HI> but <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut.</HI> 16.19. <HI>Ne iniquos accepto mu∣nere, si non <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ve∣rit, ingratus; si foverit, i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>quus ha∣beatur. Autor ocul. mor. c.</HI> 6.</NOTE> <HI>shaketh his hands</HI> also <HI>from taking of gifts,</HI> and <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Sep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> spinis aures tuas. S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rac.</HI></NOTE> <HI>stoppeth his eare from hea∣ring of bloud,</HI> and <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iob</HI> 31.1. <HI>Psal.</HI> 119.37. <HI>Vitijs no∣bis in animum per o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ulos est v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a. Quint<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l. declam. I∣taque <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Clem. Alex. paedag. l.</HI> 3. <HI>c.</HI> 11.</NOTE> <HI>shutteth his eies from seeing of euill:</HI> shunneth those things as well that may bee occasions of euill, as the euill, whereof they may be occasions, it selfe.</P>
<P N="7"><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Meanes</HI> 7.</NOTE>7. <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Luke</HI> 18.1. <HI>Rom.</HI> 12, 12. <HI>Coloss.</HI> 4.2. 1 <HI>Thess.</HI> 1.17.</NOTE> <HI>Bee frequent in praier</HI> vnto God for sup∣port. <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 26.41.</NOTE> <HI>Watch and pray,</HI> saith our Sauiour, that <HI>you may not enter into temptation. Watch &amp; pray</HI>; because <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 127.1.</NOTE> all our <HI>watching</HI> will be of no force or efficacie at all without <HI>praier.</HI> For <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ephes.</HI> 6.10, 11, 13.</NOTE> from <HI>God</HI> it is, that <HI>strength</HI> must bee had to <HI>stand stedfast</HI> and firme: <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><HI>Rom.</HI> 8.37. <HI>Phil.</HI> 4.13.</NOTE> it is <HI>his power</HI> that must support vs. <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Pet.</HI> 1.5.</NOTE> <HI>We are vp∣held by the power of God through Faith,</HI> saith the Apo∣stle. It is the <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ephes.</HI> 3.16. <HI>Colos.</HI> 1.11.</NOTE> <HI>power of God</HI> then that must enable vs to perseuer: and it is <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ephes.</HI> 6.18.</NOTE> <HI>praier</HI> that must procure this <HI>power.</HI> This holy exercise therefore we must be diligent in, if we desire thus to hold out; pray∣ing, as <HI>Dauid</HI> doth in the <HI>Psalme;</HI> <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 86.11.</NOTE> <HI>Lord, teach mee thy waies, that I may walke in thy pathes: O knit mine heart vnto thee, that I may feare thy Name.</HI> As on the other side wee may obserue, that when men grow negligent herein, a generall <HI>decay of grace</HI> vsu∣ally ensueth. <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 14.3, 4.</NOTE> <HI>They are all gone aside, &amp;c.</HI> saith the <HI>Psalmist: While they call not vpon God.</HI> And how can we hope to haue strength thus to stand, if we be not carefull to seeke it, where it is only to be had?</P>
<P N="8"><PB N="21" REF="14"/>8. <HI>Keepe the feare of God fresh</HI> in thy soule.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Meanes</HI> 8.</NOTE> <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 86.11.</NOTE> <HI>Knit mine heart vnto thee,</HI> that I <HI>may feare thee,</HI> saith the <HI>Psalmist.</HI> The <HI>feare of God,</HI> if it be fresh in vs, will make vs keepe home with him, <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Deut.</HI> 10.20.</NOTE> cleaue and cling close to him, bee afraid to stirre but an inch (as we say) from him, <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Deut.</HI> 6.2, 13. <HI>&amp;</HI> 5.29. <HI>Eccles.</HI> 12.13.</NOTE> be carefull to vse all meanes of retaining his fauour, of approuing our selues and all our courses vnto him, and <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iob</HI> 1.1. <HI>&amp;</HI> 31.13, 14, 21, 22. <HI>Nehem.</HI> 5.15. <HI>Prou.</HI> 8.13. <HI>&amp;</HI> 16.6.</NOTE> of es∣chewing whatsoeuer may either offend him, or sauour of any disloialtie and vnfaithfulnesse in vs towards him. <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><HI>Qui op<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ratur ut accedamus, id<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m o∣peratur ne disceda∣mus. Aug. de bon. persever. c.</HI> 7.</NOTE> <HI>God,</HI> saith <HI>Augustine, that hath wrought on vs to bring vs home to him, must also worke in vs, that we depart not againe from him.</HI> But this he doth by meanes; which hee pointeth at, when he saith by the <HI>Prophet,</HI> <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rem.</HI> 32.40</NOTE> <HI>I will put into their hearts such feare of me, that they shall neuer depart againe away from me.</HI> <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Fides facit formi∣dinem: sormido fa∣cis solicitudinem: solicitudo parit per∣severantiam. Ter∣tull. ad Marc.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Faith breedeth feare,</HI> and <HI>feare breedeth care</HI>; and <HI>carefulnesse causeth perseue∣rance.</HI> The <HI>Deuill</HI> could neuer preuaile with our <HI>first Parent</HI> to withdraw her from <HI>God,</HI> till he had <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Gen.</HI> 3.4.</NOTE> wrought this <HI>Feare</HI> out of her. Nor had he euer beene able so to preuaile with her,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Meanes</HI> 9.</NOTE> had she beene carefull to keepe this <HI>Feare</HI> fresh in her soule.</P>
<P N="9">9. <HI>Take heed of standing still.</HI> Thinke not with thy selfe, that hauing runne thus long, thou maist now stand still a while; or hauing gotten thus far, thou maist now sit downe and breathe thee. <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</HI> 3.17.</NOTE> <HI>Take heed,</HI> saith S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Peter, l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st you bee drawne aside, and fall from your stedfastnesse.</HI> And if you aske him, what you must doe to preuent it: <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ibid.</HI> 18.</NOTE> <HI>But grow,</HI> saith he, <HI>in grace.</HI> <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vnum <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> duobus necesse est, aut sem∣per proficere, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t prorsus desicere. Bern. de divers.</HI> 36. <HI>Qui non proficit, deficit; qui non progreditur, regre∣ditur. Nolle profi∣cere, deficere est▪ Idem epist.</HI> 25.4.</NOTE> If we be not growing, we are de∣caying:
<PB N="22" REF="15"/>
if we be not making on, wee are going amaine back. As <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Non aliter quam qui adverso<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> flu∣mine l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mbum Re∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s subigit, si brachia forte remi∣sit, Atque illum in praeceps pron<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> rapit <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>veus amni. Virg. georg. l.</HI> 1. <HI>&amp; Apud G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll. noct. Attic. l.</HI> 10. <HI>c.</HI> 29. <HI>Vide Greg. mor. l.</HI> 11. <HI>c.</HI> 8.</NOTE> in <HI>rowing vp a Riuer,</HI> that run∣neth with a strong current, if the Oares doe but stay, the Boat falleth backward. There is no stay∣ing of our hands: <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hil stat, nihil sixum manet. Aug. in Ioan.</HI> 31.</NOTE> There is no standing at a stay. <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Inter profectum &amp; desectum nihil medium invenitur. Bern. ep.</HI> 254.</NOTE> <HI>Betweene mending and pairing there is no medium,</HI> saith <HI>Bernard.</HI> <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Damnum parata sentient, si para<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e cessaveris. Pelag. ad Demetr.</HI></NOTE> <HI>That we haue will be gone, vnlesse we striue to get more.</HI></P>
<P N="10">10. <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><HI>Mica.</HI> 6.8.</NOTE> <HI>Walke in humilitie.</HI> When we haue done all this, <HI>take heed of pride:</HI> (Remember <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Chron.</HI> 26.16.</NOTE> <HI>Vzziah</HI>; remē∣ber <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Chron.</HI> 32.25, 26.</NOTE> <HI>Ezekiah:</HI>) It is a deadly <HI>poison</HI> that spoileth and killeth all where it commeth;<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Meanes</HI> 10.</NOTE> so dangerous, that <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 12.7.</NOTE> of another <HI>poison</HI> is a <HI>counter-poison</HI> confe∣cted, to preserue S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Paul</HI> from it. And <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a quaecunque iniquitas in malis operibus exercetur, ut fiant: superbia verò bonis operibus insidiatur ut pere∣ant. Aug. epist.</HI> 109.</NOTE> we are ne∣uer more in danger of it than when we haue done most, and made greatest progresse in the professi∣on and practise of pietie. For it is as <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Quod de fisco Iulianus Imper. Fiscus ut lien. Ammian. hist. l.</HI> 25.</NOTE> the <HI>spleene</HI> in the bodie, that groweth most when the other parts waste; <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Mul∣tis quippe vitia conculcasse, &amp; virtutes acquisivisse fit occasio superbiae. Rad. Ardens post Tri∣nit.</HI> 5.</NOTE> it groweth fastest oft, when other euils decay, and out of the decay of them, sucketh matter to feed &amp; foster it selfe with. This therefore must be carefully eschewed and auoided. When wee haue done well, wee must take heed, how in that regard we begin to think highly of our selues. <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Humilitas est conservatrix virtutum. Et qui sine humilitate caeteras virtutes congregat, qua<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i pulverem in ventum portat. Idem. ibid. ex Greg. mor.</HI></NOTE> If we doe so, all is gone, <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><HI>Qui gloriantur vitia devicisse se, ipsi devincuntur. Ardens ibid.</HI></NOTE> we are vndone. Be af∣fected rather as <HI>Paul</HI> was. After hee had gone so
<PB N="23" REF="15"/>
farre, done so much: <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 11.5.</NOTE> <HI>I make account, that I come not short,</HI> saith he, <HI>of the very chiefe Apostles.</HI> Yea, <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 15.10.</NOTE> <HI>I haue laboured more than them all.</HI> For, <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Rom.</HI> 15.19.</NOTE> <HI>from Ierusalem round about, euen vnto Illyricum,</HI> (that is, from <HI>Syria</HI> to <HI>Sclauonie</HI>) <HI>haue I plentifully preached the Gospell:</HI> Yet, <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Phil.</HI> 3.14.</NOTE> <HI>I forget,</HI> saith he, <HI>what is past.</HI> I regard no more what I haue done, than as if yet I had done nothing, or had cleane forgotten what I did. <HI>And</HI> <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ibid.</HI></NOTE> <HI>I put on forward to what is be∣fore; pressing on toward the high calling of God in Christ Iesus.</HI> He did as <HI>men in a race</HI> that <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Instat equis auri∣ga suos vincenti∣bus, illum Praeteri∣tum temnens. Ho∣rat. satyr.</HI> 1.</NOTE> looke not backe to see how many they haue out-stript, or how farre they haue gotten, but haue their eies fixed on those that haue got ground of them, and on the ground before them, that they are to mea∣sure, ere they can come to the marke. Let vs <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>More viatorum nequaquam debe∣mus aspicere quan∣tum jam iter egi∣mus, sed quantum superest ut peraga∣mus: ut paulisper fiat praeteritum, quod indesinenter &amp; timidè adhuc at∣tenditur suturum. Greg. mor. l.</HI> 22. <HI>c.</HI> 6. <HI>Oblivis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere omne praeteritum: &amp; quotid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>è incho∣are tepu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a: ne pro praesenti die, quo debes servire Deo, praeteritum impu∣tes. Pelag. ad De∣metr.</HI></NOTE> not consider so much how far we haue gone, and how many others come short of vs, but <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Summun illud bonum imitari <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o∣nemur: quod quan∣tumvis quis in hac vita vires proten∣derit, neutiquam tamen consequi po∣terit. Stella in Luc.</HI> 1.</NOTE> how farre we are to goe, and how farre wee come farre short of that <HI>Christian perfection,</HI> that we should all striue and contend to attaine vnto. And as our Sauiour aduiseth vs, <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Luke</HI> 17.10. <HI>Vide Chrysost. in Oziam serm.</HI> 3.</NOTE> <HI>When we haue done all that we can, let vs say, that we are but vnprofitable seruants; we haue done no more,</HI> nay <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iob</HI> 9.3. <HI>Rom.</HI> 7.17, 23. <HI>Galat.</HI> 5.17.</NOTE> farre lesse, <HI>than we ought to doe,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Meanes</HI> 11.</NOTE> than was our dutie to haue done.</P>
<P N="11">11. <HI>Consider we the short stint of time,</HI> that this laborious course is required of vs; it is but <HI>till death.</HI> And since that our <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 39.4, 5. <HI>&amp;</HI> 89.47. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Hippocr. aphor.</HI> 1. <HI>Quid tam circumcisum, tam breve, quam hominis vita longissima? Plin. ep.</HI> 7. <HI>lib.</HI> 3.</NOTE> <HI>life</HI> here is <HI>not long</HI>;
<PB N="24" REF="16"/>
(it is but <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Plut. paedag. Punctum <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st quod vivimus, &amp; adhuc puncto minu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Sen. ep.</HI> 49. <HI>Minorem portio∣nem aetas nostra quam partem pun∣cti habet, si tempo∣ri comparetur om∣ni. Id<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m ad Marc. c.</HI> 20.</NOTE> <HI>a point,</HI> saith the Heathen man, or <HI>lesse than so,</HI> that we liue here) that emploiment can∣not be long that must end with it. For what can be <HI>long</HI> in that, that is <HI>not long</HI> it selfe? It is but <HI>till death</HI> onely that our Sauiour <HI>Christ</HI> requireth this of vs. It is <HI>a note</HI> of <HI>stint,</HI> as well as of <HI>extent,</HI> here. Not that our <HI>fidelitie</HI> &amp; <HI>loialtie</HI> vnto <HI>Christ</HI> shall not last longer; but <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inem dico qua vita ista finitur, in qua tantumm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>do periculum est, ne ca∣datur. Aug. de per∣sever. c.</HI> 1.</NOTE> because after that there will be <HI>no difficultie in our loialtie, no danger of disloialtie,</HI> if till then we hold out.<NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 13.41. <HI>Vbi omni &amp; hoste &amp; peste carebimus. Aug. nom. de con∣tinent. c.</HI> 14.</NOTE> All scandals, stumbling blocks and impediments being then remoued; and all oc∣casions of prouocation and temptation to the con∣trary being thē vtterly abolished. It is but for <HI>a spurt</HI> therefore, to speak of, that this is required of vs, it is but <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><HI>Propone profundi temporis vastitatē, &amp; universum com∣plectere: deinde hoc, quod aetatem vocamus huma∣nam, compara im∣menso; videbimus quam exigu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m sit, quod optamus, quod extendimus. Sen. ep.</HI> 9<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. <HI>Omnia hu∣mana brevia &amp; caduca sunt, infi∣nui temporis nullum spatium occupantia. Idem ad Marc. c.</HI> 20.</NOTE> <HI>a spurt,</HI> in comparison of that that after en∣sueth. And who would not for a spurt, for a short brunt endure any difficultie, any hardnesse, to liue at hearts ease for euer after? Who would not serue, euen <HI>an hard</HI> and <HI>an vnkinde Master,</HI> and much more then so kinde and liberall a one as <HI>our Lord and Master Christ</HI> is, (that <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 20.28. <HI>Philip.</HI> 2.7. <HI>Luke</HI> 22.27.</NOTE> <HI>came to serue</HI> vs and for vs, ere he <HI>required</HI> this <HI>seruice</HI> of vs) with <HI>all fidelitie</HI> and <HI>diligence</HI> for a day or two, that hee might after be <HI>a free man,</HI> yea <HI>an happy man</HI> for euer? <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vt non sit hîc necessarium Epicuri solamen illud, Si longus, levis est; Si gravis est, brevis est. Cic. Tuscul. l.</HI> 2. <HI>Sen. epist.</HI> 24. <HI>&amp;</HI> 30. <HI>&amp;</HI> 78. <HI>&amp;</HI> 94. <HI>Moras &amp; I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lius in epigr.</HI></NOTE> It is <HI>not long,</HI> and it is but <HI>light,</HI> that is <HI>required</HI> of vs, in respect of that that is <HI>expected</HI> for it, and is <HI>promised</HI> thereunto. For <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 4.17. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Chrys. de compunct.</HI> 1.</NOTE> <HI>this light hardship that is
<PB N="25" REF="16"/>
but for an instant,</HI> saith the Apostle, <HI>procureth vn∣to vs an exceeding excessiue euerlasting weight of glorie.</HI></P>
<P N="12">12. <HI>Be oft</HI> <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Op<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s te terret, merce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e vide. Aug. de verb. Dom.</HI> 6.</NOTE> <HI>eying,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Meanes</HI> 12.</NOTE> and meditating on <HI>the roiall reward,</HI> that is both here and else-where propoun∣ded and promised to all those that thus perseuer. This made <HI>Moses</HI> hold out the rather, and <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Heb.</HI> 11.25, 26. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Chrys∣tom.</HI> 8. <HI>ser.</HI> 13.</NOTE> <HI>en∣dure</HI> not <HI>constantly</HI> onely, but <HI>cheerefully, chusing rather to suffer hardship with the people of God, than to enioy some sinfull delights for a season</HI>; and <HI>estee∣ming the reproach, that for Christs sake hee suffered, greater riches than all the Aegyptian treasures; be∣cause he had an eie to the recompence of reward.</HI> And <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 4.8, 10, 16, 18.</NOTE> <HI>therefore we faint not,</HI> saith the Apostle, though <HI>we bee straitned on euery side</HI>; and <HI>beare about with vs in our bodie the dying of the Lord Iesus, being de∣liuered vp daily for him to death; because wee looke not on the things that are seene, but on the things that are not seene: for the things that are seene, are tem∣porall; but the things that are not seene, are eternall.</HI> For though <HI>Gods children</HI> be <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Galat.</HI> 4.7.</NOTE> <HI>no hirelings,</HI> to serue him onely for <HI>hire</HI> sake, but out of <HI>loue,</HI> <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g. Nazianz. de Bapt.</HI></NOTE> <HI>dutie,</HI> and <HI>good-will</HI>; yet are they animated and encouraged, the rather to doe that they doe the more <HI>cheere∣fully, comfortably,</HI> and <HI>constantly,</HI> when they consi∣der what <HI>a blessed issue</HI> their <HI>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bours, endeuours</HI> and <HI>sufferings</HI> are like, nay, are sure to haue, if they hold out in them. For, <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Galat.</HI> 6.9.</NOTE> <HI>we shall reape in due time,</HI> saith the Apostle, <HI>if we faint not:</HI> Yea, of our Sa∣uiour himselfe it is said, whom we are will<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d there∣in also to imitate, that <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Heb.</HI> 12.2, 3.</NOTE> <HI>For the glorie set before him, he endured the Crosse, and set light by the shame
<PB N="26" REF="17"/>
of it, and is now seated at the right hand of God.</HI> And <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Heb.</HI> 10.35.</NOTE> <HI>cast not therefore away your confidence,</HI> saith the Apostle,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Considerati∣ons</HI> 2.</NOTE> <HI>nor giue ouer,</HI> say I, <HI>your fidelitie,</HI> that you owe <HI>vnto Christ</HI>; since that <HI>it hath so great recom∣pence of reward.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Consider.</HI> 1. <HI>Losse.</HI></NOTE></P>
<P>Yea, consider we as well what we <HI>lose,</HI> if wee <HI>giue ouer,</HI> as what we <HI>win</HI> and <HI>gaine,</HI> if we <HI>perseuer.</HI></P>
<P>For the former; <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Apoc.</HI> 3.11. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Chrysost. in Matth. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>m.</HI> 24.</NOTE> <HI>Hold fast what thou hast,</HI> saith our Sauiour, <HI>lest the Crowne be taken from thee.</HI> And it is <HI>a Question</HI> canuased to and fro among the <HI>Schoolemen,</HI> <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vide Thom. Sum. par.</HI> l <SUP>a</SUP>. 2 <HI>ae. q.</HI> 88. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 4. <HI>Dura<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d. in sut. l.</HI> 2. <HI>d.</HI> 33. <HI>q.</HI> 3. <HI>Al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>x. Ales sum. p</HI> 1. <HI>q.</HI> 39. <HI>m.</HI> 3. <HI>a.</HI> 4. §. 1. <HI>&amp; p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI> 2 <HI>q.</HI> 114. <HI>m.</HI> 3. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Chrysost. in Matth. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>om.</HI> 23.</NOTE> whether is <HI>the greater euill to forgoe the ioyes of heauen,</HI> or <HI>to vndergoe the paines of Hell.</HI> But how soeuer it be, an heauy thing it will be, if we faint and faile now, hereafter to thinke, as he some∣time said, who for a draught of drinke in distresse gaue vp his command; <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>; <HI>Ly∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>macl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> apud Plut. in ap p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>b. vel u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>idem in prac. salubr.</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>For what a trifling matter haue wee bereft our selues of a great command, of a Crowne, of a Kingdome? For what a toy</HI> (to speake of) <HI>haue we depriued our selues of eternall felicitie?</HI></P>
<P>For the latter; <HI>Bee faithfull,</HI> saith our Sauiour here, <HI>vnto death, and I will giue thee a Crowne of life.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>latter clause</HI> whereof, containing a free and a large <HI>promise,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Consider.</HI> 2. <HI>Gaine.</HI></NOTE> annexed to the <HI>precept,</HI> which hi∣therto we haue handled, albeit it might well mini∣ster much <HI>matter</HI> of further <HI>Consideration,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Part</HI> 2. <HI>Promise. Motiue.</HI></NOTE> yet for the present we will consider it onely, as <HI>a Motiue,</HI> in its seuerall <HI>branches,</HI> to induce to, and enforce on vs, such <HI>constant fidelitie,</HI> and <HI>faithfull perseue∣rance,</HI> as we haue shewed to be here required.</P>
<P N="1"><PB N="27" REF="17"/>1. He that promiseth,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Branch.</HI> 1. <HI>Giuer.</HI></NOTE> it is <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vers.</HI> 8.</NOTE> <HI>Christ. I will giue. I will giue that haue power to giue</HI>; that haue <HI>abilitie</HI> and <HI>authoritie</HI> so to doe.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Point</HI> 1.<HI>Ability.</HI></NOTE> <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Mat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h.</HI> 4.9.</NOTE> <HI>I will giue thee all these,</HI> said he sometime to our Sauiour, who had <HI>no pow∣er</HI> to make good what he said: But he that speak∣eth it here, is able to <HI>performe</HI> what he here <HI>promi∣seth.</HI> <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c.</HI> 2.16, 18.</NOTE> <HI>As I haue receiued power, so I will,</HI> saith he, <HI>giue them power.</HI> For <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 28.18.</NOTE> <HI>all power is giuen mee in heauen and earth.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Point</HI> 2. <HI>Fidelitie.</HI></NOTE> And, <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Apoc.</HI> 3.21.</NOTE> <HI>To him therefore that ouer∣commeth, will I giue to sit with me in my Throne; as I haue ouercome, and sit now with my Father on his Throne.</HI></P>
<P>Againe, <HI>I will giue,</HI> who am <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Apoc.</HI> 3.14.</NOTE> <HI>Amen, True</HI> and <HI>Faithfull.</HI> He that is <HI>faithfull to me,</HI> shall finde <HI>me faithfull to him.</HI> <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><HI>Heb.</HI> 10.23.</NOTE> <HI>Let vs keepe the profession of our hope without flitting and wauering,</HI> saith the Apo∣stle, <HI>for he that hath promised is faithfull.</HI> What he saith, he will make good: he will performe what he hath promised. He will doe it? Yea, hee hath done it. He is not like that <HI>Antigonus,</HI> whom they vsed to call <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Plut. in Paul. Ae∣myl.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Antigonus that would giue.</HI> He <HI>will giue</HI>; and he <HI>hath giuen.</HI> We tread but in the steps of those that alreadie <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Hebr.</HI> 6.11. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Clem. Alex. paedag. l.</HI> 3. <HI>c.</HI> 8.</NOTE> <HI>haue inherited these promises.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Point.</HI> 3. <HI>Liberality.</HI></NOTE></P>
<P N="3">3. He will <HI>giue.</HI> What hee doth, is of <HI>free gift,</HI> not of <HI>due debt.</HI> Such is his <HI>goodnesse,</HI> that though <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Rom.</HI> 8.12. <HI>Quicquid es, qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c∣quid pot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bes creanti, d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bes redi∣m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nti. Bern. de di∣vers.</HI> 19.</NOTE> we owe vnto him whatsoeuer we doe or can doe, <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><HI>Rom.</HI> 11.35, 36.</NOTE> nor can wee claime ought as of right from him for all that we doe for him; he oweth vs not so much as <HI>thankes,</HI> as <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><HI>Luke</HI> 17.9.10.</NOTE> himselfe else-where sheweth, for it: yet <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>O magna Dei b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣nitas, cui cum pro conditione reddere d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>beamus obsequia, vt servi Domino, famu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Deo, subiecti potenti, mancipia redemptori, amicitiarum nobis praemia repromittit. Aug. de <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erb. Dom.</HI></NOTE> of his meere <HI>bountie</HI> he will not suffer vs
<PB N="28" REF="18"/>
to goe vnrewarded;<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Branch</HI> 2. <HI>Gift.</HI></NOTE> but of his free goodnesse will giue vs, what we could not otherwise require.</P>
<P N="2"><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Point</HI> 4. <HI>Crowne.</HI></NOTE>2. The <HI>Gift,</HI> or the thing promised, it is <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Tim.</HI> 4.8.</NOTE> <HI>a Crowne</HI>; it is <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Luke</HI> 12.32. <HI>Matth.</HI> 25.34.</NOTE> <HI>a Kingdome.</HI> <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Euripid. Phoeniss. Nam si vi∣olandum est jus, regnandi gratia vi∣olandum est. C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c. of∣fic. l.</HI> 3.</NOTE> Who would not straine hard for <HI>a Crowne?</HI> <NOTE N="“" PLACE="marg"><HI>Perpessi sunt ex∣ercitus inopiam re∣rum omnium, vi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣erunt herbarum ra∣dicibus, &amp; dictu foedis tulerunt fa∣mem. Haec omnia passi sunt proregno, &amp; (quô magis mi∣r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ris) alieno. Sen. op.</HI> 17.</NOTE> Who would not endure much for <HI>a Kingdome?</HI> Who would stay by the way, or giue ouer ere he came at it, if hee saw <HI>a Crowne</HI> at <HI>the goale,</HI> and were sure to haue it, if hee held but out, till he came there?</P>
<P N="3">3. This <HI>Crowne,</HI> it is <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iam.</HI> 1.12.</NOTE> <HI>a Crowne of Life.</HI> It is not like the <HI>Crownes</HI> that worldly <HI>Kings</HI> weare, that cannot <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Plut. de tranq.</HI></NOTE> free them from <HI>diseases,</HI> much lesse saue them from <HI>Death.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Point</HI> 5. <HI>Life.</HI></NOTE> They <HI>may die,</HI> and <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 82.7. <HI>&amp;</HI> 146.3, 4.</NOTE> <HI>doe die,</HI> for all their <HI>Crownes,</HI> and <HI>returne to their dust.</HI> But this is <HI>a Crowne</HI> that giueth <HI>life</HI> to him that hath it. It is <HI>a Crowne</HI> that keepeth him in <HI>life</HI> that wea∣reth it.</P>
<P N="4">4. The <HI>Life</HI> that this <HI>Crowne</HI> giueth (though it be not expressed here) is <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 26.46. <HI>Galat.</HI> 6.8.</NOTE> <HI>an eternall, an euerlasting life.</HI> <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 9.29.</NOTE> <HI>They striue for a corruptible, wee for</HI> <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>an in∣corruptible Crowne,</HI> saith S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Paul.</HI> It is <HI>a Crowne</HI> or <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. 1 <HI>Pet.</HI> 5.4.</NOTE> <HI>a garland of</HI> <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Est spica purpurea verius quam flos. Mirum in eo gaudere de∣cerpi &amp; laetius renasci. Mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eque, postquam defecere cuncti flores, madefactus aqua reviviscit &amp; hibernas coronas facit. Summa eius natura in nomine est, appellato, quoniam non marces∣cat. Plin. hist. nat. l.</HI> 21. <HI>c.</HI> 8.</NOTE> <HI>Amarantum,</HI> or of <HI>Euerlasting,</HI> saith S<SUP>t</SUP> <HI>Peter,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Point</HI> 6. <HI>Euerlasting.</HI></NOTE> alluding to <HI>a Flower,</HI> or <HI>a Tuft</HI> ra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ther, commonly so tearmed. Therefore so tear∣med, because by it, as <HI>wee are</HI> now <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Pet.</HI> 1.4.</NOTE> <HI>kept vnto,</HI> so we shall hereafter be <HI>kept,</HI> and <HI>preserued in, a King∣dome</HI> <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>incorruptible, vntainted, that neuer withereth away, reserued for vs in the Heauens.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="29" REF="18"/>All which laid together;<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Conclusion. Vse. Perswasion, and Encou∣ragement.</HI></NOTE> the <HI>giuer</HI> so <HI>able,</HI> so <HI>free,</HI> so <HI>faithfull</HI>; and the <HI>gift</HI> it selfe so <HI>great; a Crowne, of life,</HI> and <HI>euerlasting life:</HI> so glorious and excellent an estate, <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Rom.</HI> 8.18.</NOTE> that all that euer wee doe, or can endure here, is not worthy once to bee named with it; should <HI>perswade</HI> and <HI>encourage</HI> vs with all <HI>constancie</HI> and <HI>cheerefulnesse</HI> to <HI>goe on</HI> and <HI>hold out</HI> in the <HI>faithfull seruice</HI> of our <HI>Sauiour,</HI> <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 19.2<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, 28. <HI>Marke</HI> 10.28, 29, 30. <HI>Luke</HI> 14, 26, 33.</NOTE> whatsoeuer it should cost vs, though we should lose <HI>libertie, li∣uing, life</HI> by it, and all that euer wee were worth; that so continuing <HI>faithfull vnto death,</HI> he may be∣stow vpon vs <HI>a Crowne of Life.</HI></P>
<P>Now it is,<NOTE PLACE="marg">The Testimonie giuen to M<SUP>r</SUP>▪ <HI>William Winter</HI> de∣ceased.</NOTE> I know, expected that I should, as the manner is, say, somewhat concerning <HI>our Christian brother</HI> deceased, to whose corps we performe now <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Acts</HI> 8.2. 2. <HI>Sam.</HI> 3.31.</NOTE> the last <HI>Christian office.</HI> It shall not be needfull to say much of him to those that knew him, as I sup∣pose the most here did. As <HI>Bernard</HI> saith of one <HI>Humbert</HI>; his whole life was <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Factitium vobi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sermon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m in omni forma sanctitatis Dei servus exhibu∣it. Bern. in obit. Humb.</HI></NOTE> <HI>a reall</HI> and <HI>vitall Ser∣mon</HI> of that, whereof you haue had <HI>a verbal</HI> and <HI>vo∣call</HI> one now; to wit, of <HI>pietie</HI> and <HI>godlinesse,</HI> of <HI>fidelitie</HI> and <HI>faithfulnesse to his Lord and Master Christ Iesus.</HI> Hee had beene <HI>an ancient Professor:</HI> nor was he one (as <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Rom.</HI> 2.24.</NOTE> too many there are) that did <HI>staine</HI> and <HI>blemish</HI> his <HI>Christian profession,</HI> either by <HI>Vnchristian courses,</HI> or <HI>vndiscreet carriages</HI>; but by his <HI>pious</HI> and <HI>prudent behauiour</HI> rather <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><HI>Tit.</HI> 2.7, 8, 10.</NOTE> <HI>graced</HI> and <HI>adorned</HI> it. It had pleased God to endow him with singular <HI>gifts</HI> and <HI>parts</HI> (for a priuate man especi∣ally) of <HI>vnderstanding, memorie,</HI> and <HI>speech</HI>; which hee was not slothfull or negligent to <HI>improue</HI> and <HI>employ,</HI> to the <HI>glorie of Gods name,</HI> and <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Many, I doubt not, may say of him, as <HI>Bernard</HI> of <HI>Humbert, Separa∣vit à nobis dulcem ami<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>, pruden∣tem consil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arium, sor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ē auxiliarium:</HI> God hath taken from vs, a sweet friend, a wise counseller, a strong helper.</NOTE> the <HI>edifica∣tion
<PB N="30" REF="19"/>
of others:</HI> As the maine course of his <HI>life</HI> and <HI>conuersation,</HI> so his ordinarie <HI>speech, conference,</HI> and <HI>communication</HI> being <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Coloss.</HI> 4.8.</NOTE> <HI>seasoned with salt, sauouring of sound sanctification,</HI> and such as might <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ephes.</HI> 4.<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</NOTE> <HI>minister</HI>
much <HI>grace to the hearers.</HI> And albeit, God saw it good to affoord him but a meane estate for <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. 1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 6.4.</NOTE> the <HI>things of this life,</HI> (hee will stirre vp those, I doubt not, that <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Sam.</HI> 9.3, 7.</NOTE> out of their religious disposition and affection to him, will doe for those that hee hath left behinde him) yet he had made him <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iam.</HI> 2.5.</NOTE> <HI>rich in grace</HI>; and by helpe of that <HI>grace</HI> he liued with that <HI>small pittance</HI> <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Quod de Cratete Plut. lib. de tranq.</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> more <HI>cheerefully</HI> and <HI>comforta∣bly,</HI> than many doe with <HI>large</HI> and <HI>ample estates.</HI> Nor saw I him euer more <HI>cheerefull,</HI> than in this his <HI>last sicknesse.</HI> As <HI>Ambrose</HI> said sometime when he lay a dying to his <HI>Millainers;</HI> <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><HI>Non sic vixi, ut <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e pud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at intervos vivere: nec mori timco. qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a bonum Dominum hab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣mus. Ambros. test<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Paul <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o in vita Ambr.</HI></NOTE> <HI>I haue not so liued among you, that I am ashamed to liue longer with you; nor yet am I afraid to die, because we haue a good Ma∣ster:</HI> And <HI>Martine</HI> of <HI>Tours</HI> being now neere his end, when his friends stood abou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> him, lamenting their losse of him, <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Domine, si adhuc topu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o tuo sum ne∣cessarius; non re∣cuso laborem; f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t volu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tas tua. Se∣ver. de Martin ep.</HI> 3. <HI>&amp; Bern. serm. in fest. Mart.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Lord, if I may doe thy people yet any seruice, I thinke not much of my paines, thy will be done:</HI> So was it one of this blessed <HI>Seruant of God</HI> his last speeches vnto me, willing to be disposed of by God, though <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">As <HI>Paul, Philip.</HI> 1.25. As <HI>Simeon, Luke</HI> 2.29.</NOTE> <HI>desirous of departure</HI> in regard of his owne good; <HI>If God haue any more worke for me, I am well content to liue longer, though my life should be neuer so tedious vnto me: But if my worke bee at an end, I am most willing to bee gone, well knowing, though I be altogether vnworthy of ought, what hee hath in store for me.</HI> What should I say more of him, but as it is in my <HI>Text? Hee was faithfull to
<PB N="31" REF="19"/>
Christ his Master vnto Death</HI>; and <HI>hee hath now re∣ceiued from him a Crowne of Life.</HI> Which that we may also, in Gods due time attaine, he vouchsafe vnto vs, <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Apoc.</HI> 1.5, 6. <HI>&amp;</HI> 5.9, 10.</NOTE> who hath <HI>purchased</HI> and <HI>pro∣cured</HI> it for vs, IESVS CHRIST, <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Rom.</HI> 9.<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> <HI>to be blessed for euer.</HI> AMEN.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

