<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="3">An anniuersarie memoriall of Englands deliuery from the Spanish inuasion deliuered in a sermon on Psal. 48. 7,8. By Thomas Gataker B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2005-03 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A01524</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 11648</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S105720</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99841446</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99841446</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">6030</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01524)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6030)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1065:14)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="3">An anniuersarie memoriall of Englands deliuery from the Spanish inuasion deliuered in a sermon on Psal. 48. 7,8. By Thomas Gataker B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[8], 24 p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Iohn Haviland for Philemon Stephens and Christopher Meredith, at the Golden Lion in Pauls Churchyard,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1626.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>Running title reads: Englands deliuerie from the Spanish inuasion.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Sermons, English --  17th century.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2004-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>SPi Global</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-11</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Emma (Leeson) Huber</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2005-01</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A01524">
<STC T="S">11648</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99841446</BIBNO>
<VID>6030</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>An Anniuersarie MEMORIALL OF ENGLANDS DELIVERY FROM The Spanish Inuasion: DELIVERED IN A Sermon on <HI>Psal.</HI> 48.7.8. By <HI>THOMAS GATAKER</HI> B. <HI>of</HI> D. and Pastor of <HI>Rotherhith.</HI></P>
<P>LONDON, ¶ Printed by <HI>John Haviland</HI> for <HI>Philemon Stephens</HI> and <HI>Christopher Meredith,</HI> at the Golden Lion in Pauls Churchyard. 1626.</P>
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>TO THE WORSHIPFVLL HIS VERY LOVING Friend <HI>M. Thomas Chapman,</HI> Sonne and Heire to the Religious Founder of this Exercise.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Worthy Sir,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Hat your selfe, and others with your selfe haue through your means former∣ly by word of mouth heard from me, you shall now vpon your second request receiue here in writing. I should not haue deemed it worthy the reseruation, but that it pleased
<PB REF="4"/>
you (who haue best right to it) to require it. In scatterd notes only (like <HI>Absyrtus</HI> his limmes) I had the summe and heads of it; which I haue againe here recollected, &amp; cast (as neare as I could) into that mould and frame that it was deli∣uered in at first. If much seeme missing of that little grace that it then had, it must be remembred, that the liuelesse letter for viuaci∣tie and efficacie commeth farre short of the liuing voice. As it is, you haue it, and no more then your owne in it, from him, who for your pious building on your worthy Fathers foundation in this kinde, doth deseruedly affect you, and shall alwayes continue</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Yours to be commanded in the Lord, <HI>THO. GATAKER.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>TO THE READER.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">B</SEG>E pleased (good Reader) to vn∣derstand in few words the occa∣sion whereupon this Sermon was preached, and thou wilt iudge it to be a kinde of necessitie to make that publike to the common view, which was first intended for the eare onely of a priuate Auditory. There is, we see, too great and generall a want (in these our dayes) of monuments and memorials of that miraculous deliuerance which God wrought for this Land in <HI>88.</HI> When Tongue and Pen, Pulpit and Presse are silent for that, we may expect the stones to cry out against vs, and to celebrate that praise to God whereof we are neglectiue. But mans memory being a table booke to regi∣ster acts passed, and not able to comprehend all
<PB REF="5"/>
that is to be recorded therein, when new things of note come to be imprinted in it, the old are wip't out: so God affording vs a daily supplie of new preseruations, those other which we haue formerly receiued grow quite out of date, are rased out, and buried in obliuion. Therfore to reuiue this blessing (which ought neuer to be forgotten) amongst the rest in this Land, and for it to eternize Gods praise amongst vs, it hath beene religiously prouided by <HI>M<SUP>r</SUP>. Tho∣mas Chapman</HI> (sometimes a worthy Citizen) that yeerely three Sermons shall be preached in the Church of <HI>S<SUP>t</SUP>. Pancrace</HI> in <HI>Soper-lane,</HI> where he lately liued a well deseruing parishi∣oner: One of the Sermons to be preached <HI>No∣uemb. 17.</HI> in thankfull remembrance of the coronation of that <HI>Virgin Queene ELIZA∣BETH</HI> of famous and neuer-dying memory, with whose gracious gouernment accompanied much happinesse to our kingdome; but this as chiefe of all, <HI>(scil.)</HI> the establishment of that truth of the Gospell &amp; discipline of the Church which we now enioy vnder our dread Soue∣raigne Lord King <HI>CHARLES</HI> (whom God long preserue a religious Defender of this truth and peace amongst vs.) Another Ser∣mon
<PB REF="5"/>
to be preached <HI>August 12.</HI> for our deliue∣rance from that <HI>Spanish Armado</HI> (in which course this Sermon was preached.) A third <HI>Nouemb. 5.</HI> for the preseruation of our King and State from that damnable powder-plot as yet vnparalleld in any age since the world be∣gan. In each of these we may behold Gods goodnesse: first in bringing vs to the glorious light of the Gospell by making that Queene a Mother ouer his <HI>Israel</HI> and a Nurse ouer his <HI>Church:</HI> neither was it lesse goodnesse in him to preserue vs in this happy state, then to con∣ferre it vpon vs; and this he hath done maugre the malice of our enemies, who haue not wan∣ted both power and policie in these their at∣tempts, yet when they were strong and many, our God was mightier than they, and there were more with vs than against vs: when they had laid their plots and traines, God con∣founded the wicked imaginations of those <HI>Achitophels,</HI> and let them fall into the pit they had digged for others. This good man, famous in his generation, in thankfull remem∣brance to God of these three blessings, in his life time solemnly obserued three Sermons, and hath left large Legacies at his death for their
<PB REF="6"/>
continuance vnto posteritie; that in succee∣ding ages fathers may declare vnto their chil∣dren how great things God hath done for vs in the old times before them. By this godly care of his, he hath built himselfe a monument of fame to remaine longer than those <HI>Aegyp∣tian Pyramides,</HI> or that Pillar which <HI>Abso∣lom</HI> reared vp in the Kings dale for the per∣petuitie of his name vpon earth. Thus they that honour God, God will honour them, in seeking the glory of Gods name, God hath made an honourable memoriall of his name to re∣dound vpon his owne head. He was second to none, being the first Founder (of late) of this pious act: but I hope he shall not stand alone, but that there will be many found to se∣cond him hereafter in so good a worke worthy the imitation. So now (Reader) I commit this Sermon to thy perusall: whilest in it thou seest Gods wonderfull workes which he hath done for our Nation, or what good soeuer thou shalt reape else in this Exercise, be thankfull to God and pray for the Author.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB N="1" REF="6"/>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>PSALME 48.7, 8.</BIBL>
<Q><P N="7"><HI>7.</HI> As with an East wind, thou breakest the Ships of Tarshish; so were they destroyed.</P>
<P N="8"><HI>8.</HI> As we haue heard, so haue we seene in the Citie of the Lord of Hoasts, in the Citie of our God: God will establish it for euer. Selah.</P></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">A</SEG>S in all well-gouerned <HI>States</HI> there are publike <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>siue <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Ezr.</HI> 6.2. <HI>Et <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> siue <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Ester</HI> 6.1. <HI>&amp; Ezr.</HI> 4.15. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Hesych. Archiua; quae &amp; Tabularia Ciceroni pro Arch. &amp; Virgi∣lio Georg. l.</HI> 2. <HI>vbi actus publici continentur. Seru.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Registers,</HI> and <HI>Re∣cords,</HI> that the memory of <HI>Iudge∣ments</HI> and <HI>Acts</HI> may not perish: So hath <HI>God</HI> in mans <HI>Soule</HI> ere∣cted a <HI>Register,</HI> to wit, the <HI>facultie</HI> of <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Memoria est vis animae accepta retinens, praeterita repetens, elapsa re colligens. Aug. nom. de sp. &amp; an. c.</HI> 37. <HI>Omnium rerum thesaurus, &amp; custos est memoria. Ibid. c.</HI> 34. Memory is the storehouse of the Soule, and the Regi∣ster of the Minde. <HI>Morton</HI> threefold state of Man, l. 2. c. 4. §. 1. The Memoratiue fa∣cultie is the Gardian and Register of all species and images apprehended by the sense, and reserued and sealed vp by the Imagination. <HI>Charron</HI> of Wisdome, l. 1. c. 12. <HI>Hoc est quod Scalig. de subtil. exerc.</HI> 307. §. 2. <HI>Imaginationis Memoria seruatrix est. Acceptas enim spe∣cies ab imaginatione reponit, conditque in thesauris.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Remembrance,</HI> for the <HI>preseruation</HI> of such <HI>oc∣currents,</HI> as are of <HI>weight,</HI> and may be of <HI>vse</HI> for the <HI>direction</HI> of <HI>mans life.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="2" REF="7"/>But this <HI>Register</HI> is very much abused by the greatest part of those that haue the custody of it. For if the <HI>Records</HI> that the most enter therein, and keepe there, were surueyed, <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">See <HI>Bern. serm. parv.</HI> 1. <HI>Morton ibid.</HI> §. 2. and <HI>Marbury</HI> of Repentance.</NOTE> there would be found filed there large rolls fraught with friuolous and froathie stuffe, of little weight, and lesse vse, yea (it may be) with much <HI>filthy,</HI> and <HI>vnsauoury</HI> matter, <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ephes.</HI> 5.3, 4.</NOTE> not once to be <HI>mentioned,</HI> much lesse to be re∣membred: scarce any script, or scroll of ought, that is ought worth, or worthy to be entred in so<NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Archiuum planè regium, imò etiam diuinum.</HI></NOTE> <HI>royall a Register.</HI></P>
<P>Now if any thing deserue to be there carefully re∣corded, that it may by that meanes be transmitted to <HI>posteritie,</HI> it should be <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 105.5. <HI>&amp;</HI> 111.2, 3, 4. <HI>Malac.</HI> 4.4.</NOTE> <HI>Gods word,</HI> and his <HI>works,</HI> his extraordinary <HI>Acts</HI> especially either of <HI>Iudge∣ment,</HI> or of <HI>Mercy.</HI> For the former, the Prophet <HI>Ioel</HI> willeth the <HI>people</HI> of his time, both to record them themselues, and to cause their <HI>Children</HI> to record them, and them also to relate them to their posteri∣tie. <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ioel</HI> 1.2.</NOTE> <HI>Tell it you to your Children; and let them tell it to their children; and their Children to those that rise in their roome.</HI> Of the latter saith the <HI>Psalmist,</HI> <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>Asaphi Psalm{us}. Iun.</HI> A Psalme of <HI>A∣saph. Reg. Bibl.</HI> for <HI>Asaph. Genev.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Asaph,</HI> or who euer he were; <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 78.5, 6.</NOTE> <HI>He commanded our Fathers to teach it to their Children, that posteritie might know it, and the Children that are yet vnborne might declare it to their Children hereafter; that Gods works might not be forgotten.</HI></P>
<P>In which kinde the pious, and religious <HI>Act</HI> of <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">M<SUP>r</SUP> <HI>Thomas Chapman.</HI></NOTE> the <HI>Founder</HI> of this <HI>Exercise</HI> is very much to be commended, who hauing culled out <HI>three principall Acts</HI> of <HI>Gods extraordinary Mercy</HI> exhibited to the <HI>Land</HI> wherein we liue, as great as any euer vouch∣safed
<PB N="3" REF="7"/>
to any <HI>State</HI> whatsoeuer, hath established a <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> solemne <HI>Anniuersarie Memoriall</HI> of them to per∣petuate them to all posteritie.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Occasion.</HI></NOTE></P>
<P>To my Lot is fallen that <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Octogesim{us} octa∣uus mirabilis annus Clade Papistorum; faustus vbique p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>js. Fulk. in Rhem.</HI></NOTE> <HI>admirable Deliuerance</HI> in 88. from that<NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">The inuincible Nauie. See <HI>Hack∣luits</HI> relation.</NOTE> <HI>Inuincible Armado,</HI> as it was then stiled and termed.</P>
<P>For the remembrance whereof, and of <HI>Gods mer∣cy</HI> in it, I haue made choice to intreat of some <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 48.7, 8.</NOTE> par∣cell of this <HI>Psalme,</HI> not vnbefitting (as you may soone see) the present occasion.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Text.</HI></NOTE></P>
<P>The <HI>Psalme,</HI> is a <HI>Psalme</HI> (not so much <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Piscat.</HI></NOTE> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Summe of the Psalme.</HI></NOTE> as <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, and <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iunius.</HI></NOTE> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>) of <HI>Praise</HI> and of <HI>Tri∣umph.</HI></P>
<P>Of the <HI>praise</HI> of <HI>God,</HI> and his goodnesse to his <HI>Church.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Parts</HI> 2.</NOTE></P>
<P>Of <HI>triumph</HI> ouer <HI>Gods enemies,</HI> and the <HI>enemies</HI> of his <HI>Church.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Part</HI> 1.</NOTE></P>
<P>The <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Verse</HI> 1.-5.</NOTE> <HI>Praise</HI> of <HI>God,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Praise.</HI></NOTE> and his goodnesse to his <HI>Church,</HI> is laid downe from the first verse to the fift.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Part</HI> 2.</NOTE></P>
<P>The speciall ground of this praise <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><HI>Verse</HI> 5.-10.</NOTE> <HI>a victorie</HI> through his assistance atchieued against his <HI>enemies,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Triumph.</HI></NOTE> and the <HI>enemies</HI> of his <HI>Church</HI> is, by way of <HI>triumph,</HI> related from the fift verse to the tenth.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Relation.</HI></NOTE></P>
<P>And in the <HI>Relation</HI> hereof there is,<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. <HI>Attempt.</HI></NOTE></P>
<P>First <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Verse</HI> 4.</NOTE> the <HI>enemies Attempt</HI>; and therein</P>
<P N="1">1. <HI>Praeparatio</HI>; their <HI>preparation;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">1. <HI>Preparatiō.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Conuenerunt pariter; they met together.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. <HI>Expeditio</HI>; their <HI>expedition;</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2. <HI>Expeditiō.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Progressi sunt pa∣riter; they went on together.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, the <HI>issue,</HI> and <HI>euent</HI> of it:<NOTE PLACE="marg">2. <HI>Euent.</HI></NOTE> not like that
<PB N="4" REF="8"/>
of <HI>Casar,</HI> <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Sueton. Caes. c.</HI> 37. <HI>Sic de Pompeio A∣theniens<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE><HI>Veni, vidi, vici; I came, I saw, I ouercame:</HI> but, <HI>venerunt, viderunt, veriti sunt, victi sunt:</HI> they <HI>came,</HI> they <HI>saw,</HI> they were <HI>ouercome,</HI> with <HI>astonish∣ment,</HI> with <HI>feare,</HI> with <HI>defeature.</HI></P>
<P N="1">1. <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Verse</HI> 5.</NOTE> <HI>Contemplati sunt</HI>; they but <HI>viewed</HI> the Land that they came to inuade.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Degree</HI> 1.</NOTE></P>
<P N="2"><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Degree</HI> 2.</NOTE>2. <HI>Obstupuerunt,</HI> they <HI>wondred</HI> that they were able to make head against them.</P>
<P N="3">3. <HI>Conturbati sunt</HI>; they were <HI>troubled,</HI> disaraied, disappointed.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Degree</HI> 3.</NOTE></P>
<P N="4"><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Degree</HI> 4.</NOTE>4. <HI>Festinauerunt</HI>; they made all the <HI>haste</HI> they could to be gone.</P>
<P N="5"><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Degree</HI> 5.</NOTE>5. <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vers.</HI> 6.</NOTE> <HI>Timor eos apprehendit</HI>; they were full of <HI>feare,</HI> &amp; affrightment, when they found not free passage.</P>
<P N="6"><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Degree</HI> 6.</NOTE>6. <HI>Et dolor, vt dolores parturientis</HI>; they were sur∣prised with <HI>paines,</HI> being thus cast into such streights and distresses; like a <HI>woman</HI> in her <HI>trauell.</HI></P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Degree</HI> 7.</NOTE>Lastly, <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><HI>Verse</HI> 7.</NOTE> <HI>Euro conteris naues Oceani,</HI> they were discomfited, and <HI>destroyed,</HI> as the <HI>Ships</HI> of the <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>vnde Grae. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, quasi</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, Brought. <HI>Oceanus, sed pecu∣liariter Mediterra∣neus, à regione Tarsis, i. Cilicia, quam alluit.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Le∣uant Seas</HI> are, when with a furious <HI>East-wind</HI> they are bruised, and battered, and broken to peeces a∣gainst the rocks.</P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Application.</HI></NOTE>If I should say no more, but adde only the words following: <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Verse</HI> 8.</NOTE> <HI>Prout audiuimus, &amp; vidimus; What we haue heard with them, we haue seene done for vs</HI>; it were a very pregnant description of this our deli∣uerance. But somewhat more must be said, that we may learne what vse to make of it.</P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Illustration.</HI></NOTE>The <HI>Relation</HI> of this <HI>Victorie</HI> atchieued for them by <HI>God</HI> (for <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 44.2, 3. <HI>&amp;</HI> 115.1.</NOTE> to him alone it is ascribed) is here <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Verse</HI> 8.</NOTE> further <HI>illustrated.</HI></P>
<P N="1"><PB N="5" REF="8"/>1. By a <HI>report</HI> of what was past:<NOTE PLACE="marg">1. <HI>Report.</HI></NOTE> the words seeme to haue reference not to the <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ab adiuncta prae∣dictione, &amp; promis∣sione diuina. Pis∣cat. Ita &amp; R. Kim∣chi. Amb. Apollin. Aug. Ruffin. Theo∣doret. Euthym. Lomb. Cassiod. Hug. Lyr. Bucer. Brent. Moller. Strigel. Loss. &amp;c. vnde Aug. O beata Ecclesia, quodam tempore audisti; quodam tempore vidisti: audiuit in promissionibus, vidit in exhibitionibus. Verum isti plaerique sensum mysticum sequuntur.</HI></NOTE> <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ab exemplis antegressis. Chrysost. Beza. Buchan. Hessec. Sic Psal.</HI> 44.1. <HI>vtrumque ponunt Calv. Muscul. Iun.</HI></NOTE> <HI>predictions</HI> of Gods Prophets, but to former examples rather of the like done for Gods people: <HI>What we haue heard done in our fore-fathers time for them, we haue seene done in our daies for vs.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. By a promise of further future protection. <HI>God will establish it for euer.</HI></P>
<P>And their <HI>thankfulnesse</HI> followeth in <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Verse</HI> 9.</NOTE> the next <HI>Verse:</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">2. <HI>Promise. Thankfulnes.</HI></NOTE> (that which we through <HI>Gods mercy</HI> suruiue to doe this day) <HI>We recount, or meditate on thy mer∣cy, ô Lord, in the middest of thy Temple,</HI> that is, in the middest of the <HI>Congregation</HI> there gathered to∣gether.</P>
<P>Thus you see briefly the <HI>Summe,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Transition from Distribution to Instructions. Instructiō</HI> 1.</NOTE> and the <HI>Sub∣stance,</HI> as of my <HI>Text,</HI> so of the <HI>former part</HI> of the whole <HI>Psalme.</HI></P>
<P>I come now to some <HI>Instructions</HI> that out of it may be obserued.</P>
<P>The <HI>first</HI> of them is this.
<Q><NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. He∣siod. oper. l. <HI>1.</HI> Prou. <HI>11.27.</HI></NOTE> Quaerunt ruinam, qui ruinam cogitant.</Q>
They bring destruction vpon themselues, that seek the ruine of Gods elect. <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 37.12, 13.</NOTE> <HI>The wicked</HI> (saith the <HI>Psal∣mist) practiseth against the righteous; and seeketh oc∣casion to slay him. But the Lord the whiles laugheth him to scorne: for he seeth that his day is comming.</HI> <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ibid.</HI> 14, 15.</NOTE> <HI>The wicked haue drawne their sword and bent their bow, to ouerthrow, and destroy those, that be of an vp∣right conuersation: But their sword shall be sheathed
<PB N="6" REF="9"/>
in their owne side; and their bow shall be knapt in two</HI> <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Isai.</HI> 41.11, 12.</NOTE> <HI>All that prouoke thee</HI> (saith <HI>God</HI> by the <HI>Prophet Esay to his people) shall be confounded, and brought to nought; all that contend with thee, shall perish. Thou shalt seeke them, and shalt not finde them. All that striue with thee shall be as nothing: all that warre vpon thee, as a thing of nought.</HI> And <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><HI>Zech.</HI> 12.2.</NOTE> <HI>I will make</HI> (saith <HI>God</HI> by the <HI>Pro∣phet Zachary) Ierusalem as a cup of rancke poison to all those that besiege her</HI>; which when a thirstie man lighteth vpon, and swalloweth downe suddenly, hee findeth his bane in that, that hee hoped to quench his thirst with. <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ibid.</HI> 3.</NOTE> <HI>I will make Ierusalem an heauie stone to all people</HI>; such a one as <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 21.44.</NOTE> <HI>shall crush to peeces all that attempt to lift it,</HI> or to remoue it: so shall she teare to peeces all that attempt to stirre her, <HI>though all the nations in the world should ioyne to∣gether against her.</HI> <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><HI>Zech.</HI> 12.6.</NOTE> <HI>I will make the Princes of Iuda like coales of fire among seare-wood, and like a fire∣brand in a sheafe; &amp; they shall deuoure, &amp; destroy all the people that beset them on the right hand, and on the left.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Reason</HI> hereof:</P>
<P N="1"><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 1.</NOTE>1. <HI>Dei qui Ecclesiam impetunt, Deum petunt.</HI> They that fight against <HI>Gods Church,</HI> <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Act.</HI> 5.39. <HI>&amp; Tertull. ad Sca∣pul.</HI></NOTE> <HI>fight against God</HI> himselfe. <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Non tam vos, quàm Christum in vobis persequuntur. Saluian. de prouid. lib.</HI> 8. <HI>cap.</HI> 4. <HI>Patitur enim in vobis Deus. Martial. epist.</HI> 2. <HI>c.</HI> 18.</NOTE> <HI>They persecute not you so much, as Christ in you,</HI> saith <HI>Saluian.</HI> <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Act.</HI> 9.4.</NOTE> <HI>Saul, Saul</HI> (saith our Saui∣our) <HI>why doest thou persecute me.</HI> And in so doing, they doe but as one (saith the <HI>Comick</HI>) <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Verberare nol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lapidem n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> laedas manum. Plaut. Curcul.</HI> 1.3.</NOTE> <HI>that bea∣teth a stone, and spoileth his hand</HI>; or <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><HI>Acts</HI> 9.5. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Aeschyl. Prometh. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Pindar. Pyth.</HI> 2. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Eurip. Bacch. Quae inscitia est, adu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rsum stimulum calces <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Ter. Ph<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rm.</HI> 1.2.</NOTE> <HI>as the beast that
<PB N="7" REF="9"/>
spurneth at the goade,</HI> that he was pricked with; <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Schol. Aeschyl. Si stimulos pugnis cae∣dis, manibus plus dolet. Plaut. Trucul.</HI> 4.2. <HI>vide &amp; Chry∣sost. in Psal.</HI> 11.</NOTE> <HI>he maimeth but his foot</HI> by it, &amp; getteth <HI>a worse wound</HI>; or <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Greg. Naz. ad Eunom.</HI> 5.</NOTE> as the <HI>Boare,</HI> that runneth fiercely vpon the <HI>Speare,</HI> and so receiueth into his body the whole <HI>weapon</HI> that the <HI>Hunts-man</HI> holdeth. <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 2.1, 2.</NOTE> <HI>Why</HI> (saith the <HI>Psalmist) doe the Nations rage, and the people keepe such a coile to no end? The Kings of the earth band themselues together, and the Princes assemble themselues together, against the Lord, and against his Anointed?</HI> Therefore <HI>against the Lord</HI> himselfe, be∣cause <HI>against the Lords Anointed.</HI> And as <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Qui insurgit in Christum Domini, insurgit in Dominū Christi. Sic Psal.</HI> 89.51.</NOTE> <HI>he that riseth against the Lords Anointed, riseth against the Lord by whom hee is anointed:</HI> So they that rise a∣gainst the <HI>Church</HI> of <HI>God,</HI> rise against <HI>God</HI> himselfe, whose <HI>Church</HI> it is; <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 37.29.</NOTE> <HI>Because thou ragest against mee</HI> (saith <HI>God</HI> to <HI>Senacherib) therefore I will put my ring in thy nose, and my bit in thy iawes, and bring thee backe the same way thou camest.</HI> <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 17.8.</NOTE> <HI>Keepe me</HI> (saith <HI>Da∣uid) as the apple of thine eye: hide me vnder the sha∣dow of thy wings.</HI> They that deale with them, deale with those that are as deare vnto <HI>God,</HI> as the very <HI>apple of his eye, that</HI> that the eye-sight consisteth in; And therefore saith <HI>God,</HI> <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Zach.</HI> 2.8.</NOTE> <HI>I will be as a wall of fire about Ierusalem</HI> (hee saith <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Non saxeus, non aheneus, sed igneus, qui &amp; cominus ar∣ceat, &amp; eminus terreat. Theo. in Zach.</HI></NOTE> not, saith <HI>Theodoret, a wall of stone, or of brasse,</HI> but <HI>of fire,</HI> that it may both <HI>fray afar off, and keepe off too at hand</HI>; that may not onely <HI>protect</HI> them, but <HI>destroy</HI> those that assault them) because <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Zach.</HI> 2.5.</NOTE> <HI>he that medleth with you, medleth with me, euen with</HI> <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ad exprimendam teneritudinem p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e∣tatis suae, tenerrimā (sed &amp; charissimā) partem humani corporis nominauit, &amp;c. Saluian. de pro∣uid. l.</HI> 8. <HI>c.</HI> 4.</NOTE> <HI>the apple of mine eye.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Pythag. an Radamanth. Aristot. ethic. lib.</HI> 5. <HI>cap.</HI> 5.</NOTE> <HI>Lex talionis verè lex aequissima.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 2.</NOTE> The Law of
<PB N="6" REF="10"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="7" REF="10"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="8" REF="11"/>
retaliation, or like-recompence, is most equall. <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Pindar. Nem▪</HI> 4. <HI>Quod quisque fecit, patitur. Sen. Herc. fur.</HI> 3.2. <HI>Non est in∣iuria pati, quod prior feceris. Sen. de ira, lib.</HI> 2. <HI>cap.</HI> 30. - <HI>neque enim lex iustior vlla est, quam necis artifi∣ces arte perire sua. Ouid. art. l.</HI> 1.</NOTE> <HI>It is not euill, that they suffer euill, that haue done euill to others.</HI> <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iam.</HI> 2.13.</NOTE> <HI>There shall be iudgement</HI> (saith <HI>S. Iames) without mercy to those that would shew no mercy.</HI> <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Cleon apud Thucyd. l.</HI> 3.</NOTE> It is no cruelty to vse them cruelly, that haue shewed cruelty to others. For <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><HI>Misericordiam qui non praestat al∣teri, tollit sibi. Petr. Chrysol. ser.</HI> 42.</NOTE> <HI>he excludeth himselfe from mercy</HI> (saith <HI>Chrysologus) that denieth it to another.</HI> <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Pythia Glauco apud Herodot. lib.</HI> 6.</NOTE> But they stand guilty of destruction that haue <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Decreuisti facere? iam perfecisti. August. de verb. Dom.</HI> 43.</NOTE> <HI>a purpose to destroy.</HI> For <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><HI>Voluntas faciendi reputatur pro opere facti: &amp; actionis crimine cogitatio condemnatur. Pe∣l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g. ad Demetr.</HI></NOTE> the bare will alone goeth <HI>with God</HI> for the <HI>work,</HI> and the very <HI>endeuour, desire,</HI> yea or <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><HI>Nam scelus intra se tacitè qui cogitat vllum, Facti crimen habet. Iuuen. sat.</HI> 13.</NOTE> <HI>thought,</HI> for the <HI>deed.</HI> <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iosu.</HI> 24.9.</NOTE> <HI>Balak rose, and fought with Israel,</HI> saith <HI>Iosua.</HI> And yet the story saith no∣thing so. But <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Fieri dicitur, quod tentatur aut intenditur. Riber. in Amos</HI> 9.5.</NOTE> <HI>that is said to be done, that is either intended, or attempted,</HI> saith <HI>Ribera.</HI> He did it not, only because he durst not: and the woman (saith the Heathen man) <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Quae quia non licuit, non facit, illa facit. Ouid. amor. lib.</HI> 3. <HI>el.</HI> 4. <HI>Non dicam pudicam, quae aut legem, aut virum timuit: non immeritò in numerum peccantium refertur, quae pudicitiam timori praestitit, non sibi. Sen. de ben. l.</HI> 4. <HI>c.</HI> 14.</NOTE> that <HI>doth not euill, because shee dare not,</HI> when she would do it, if she durst, though <HI>she doe it not,</HI> yet <HI>she doth it.</HI> <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 5.28.</NOTE> <HI>He that looketh but on a woman to lust after her</HI> (saith our Sauiour) <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Clem. Rom. constit. Apost. l.</HI> 1. <HI>c.</HI> 1.</NOTE> <HI>hath already in his heart committed adultery with her.</HI> And, <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>John</HI> 3.5.</NOTE> <HI>He that hateth but his brother,</HI> (saith <HI>S. Iohn</HI>) <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Quantum ad te pertinet, occidisti, quem odisti. Aug. homil.</HI> 42.</NOTE> <HI>hath already murthered him in his heart.</HI> <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Res mira: ille viuit, tu tamen homicida <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; illa casta est, tu tamen adulter es. Aug. de verb. Dom.</HI> 46. <HI>&amp; de</HI> 10. <HI>chord.</HI> 3. <HI>&amp; de temp.</HI> 237. <HI>&amp; homil.</HI> 5. <HI>&amp;</HI> 40. <HI>&amp;</HI> 42. <HI>sed &amp; C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ncil. Tolet.</HI> 11. <HI>c.</HI> 4.</NOTE> <HI>A strange mat∣ter</HI> (saith <HI>S. Augustine) the man is aliue still, and yet thou art a murtherer: the woman is honest, and yet art
<PB N="9" REF="11"/>
thou an adulterer.</HI> <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><HI>Latro est etiam antequam manus inqu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>net, qui ad occidendum arma∣tus est, &amp; habet spoliandi, atque in∣terficiendi volun∣tatem. Sen. de be∣nef. l.</HI> 5. <HI>c.</HI> 13. <HI>Illo <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s homicida venenum quo misces die. Idem de constan. c.</HI> 7.</NOTE> The minding then of destructi∣on, maketh a destroyer. <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Potest aliquis no∣cens fieri, quamuis non noc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at. Omnia scelera ante effectū operis, quantum culpae satis est, per∣fecta sunt. Sen. ibid.</HI></NOTE> He is guilty of it that doth but intend, or attempt to destroy: and de∣serueth himselfe to be destroyed. <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Deut.</HI> 19.19.</NOTE> <HI>If a witnesse</HI> (saith <HI>God) shall rise against a man to take his life away from him, you shall euen doe vnto him</HI> (not, <HI>as he did,</HI> but) <HI>as he would haue done vnto his neighbour.</HI></P>
<P>The second <HI>point</HI> of <HI>Instruction</HI>:
<Q>Creaturae Deo dilectis militant.</Q></P>
<P><HI>Gods creatures</HI> fight for those that are <HI>Gods</HI>; for those that loue him, and whom he loueth;<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Instructiō</HI> 2.</NOTE> against the enemies of his <HI>Church.</HI> <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Exod.</HI> 8. <HI>&amp;</HI> 9. <HI>&amp;</HI> 10.</NOTE> The <HI>Frogs, Flies, Lice, Locusts,</HI> &amp;c. fought for <HI>Gods seruants</HI> against <HI>Pharao,</HI> and <HI>his people.</HI> <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iudg.</HI> 5.20, 21.</NOTE> The <HI>Starres from heauen fought in their courses against Sisera:</HI> and the <HI>riuer Kishon swept his armies away,</HI> as the <HI>Red Sea</HI> had done <HI>Pharao's</HI> be∣fore. <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iosua</HI> 10.13.</NOTE> The <HI>Sunne stood still</HI> to assist <HI>Ioshua</HI> in the pursuit of the <HI>Canaanites:</HI> and <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Joshua</HI> 10.11.</NOTE> the <HI>haile-stones slew more of them</HI> than the <HI>sling</HI> or the <HI>sword</HI> did. <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vers.</HI> 7.</NOTE> And as here <HI>with the East-wind doest thou dash to peeces the Ships of the Mediterranean Sea</HI>;<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Exod.</HI> 14.27, 28. <HI>&amp;</HI> 15.4.</NOTE> So <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Milites nobis qui aderāt, retulerunt, extorta sibi esse de manibus quaecun{que} iaculabantur, cùm à Theodosit partib{us} in aduersarios ve∣hemens ventus iret; &amp; non solum quaecun{que} in eos iaci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bantur concitatissimè raperet, verume<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iam ipsorum tela in eorum corpora retorqueret. Aug. de ciuit. l.</HI> 5. <HI>c.</HI> 26.</NOTE> the winds <HI>fought</HI> for <HI>Theodosius</HI> in that famous battell against <HI>Maximus,</HI> carrying the darts, and arrowes of his companies full into the faces of their enemies, and returning backe those of their enemies vpon their owne bodies: That which euen <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>A Christi nomine al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>enus. Aug. ibid.</HI></NOTE> an <HI>Heathen Poet</HI> admiring, brake out into that speech; <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><HI>O nimium dilecte Deo, cui militat Aether; Et coniurati veniunt ad classicaventi! Te propter gelidis Aquilo de monte procellis Obruit aduersas acies, renoluta{que} tela Vertit in autores &amp; turbine reppulit ha∣stas. Claudianus</HI> 3. <HI>Coss. Honor.</HI></NOTE> <HI>O how highly art thou beloued of God, whom the heauens fight
<PB N="10" REF="12"/>
for; and the Winds as thy confederates come in to assist thee! To thine aid came the boisterous North-wind downe from the Hills, and bare downe before thee the troopes that came against thee, with whirling blasts re∣pelling their speares, and retorting their arrowes, and darts vpon their owners.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Reason</HI> hereof.</P>
<P N="1"><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 1.</NOTE>1. The <HI>Saints</HI> are in league, and confederacie with <HI>God.</HI> <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 50.5.</NOTE> <HI>Gather me my Saints</HI> (saith he) <HI>that haue made a league with me.</HI> Now as <HI>Princes</HI> that are in <HI>league</HI> of <HI>amity</HI> together, may haue the <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Eurip. E∣lectr. &amp; Phaeniss. &amp; Orest. Amicorum inter se communia sunt omnia. Ter. Adelph.</HI> 5.3.</NOTE> free vse of either others forces at need: <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>King.</HI> 22.4. 2 <HI>Chron.</HI> 18.3.</NOTE> <HI>My horses</HI> (saith <HI>Iehosaphat</HI> to <HI>Ahab) are as thy horses; and my people as thy people:</HI> thou mayest vse them as thine owne. So the godly being in league with God, may haue all his forces, and armies for their helpe, and assi∣stance, whensoeuer need shall be. And what are all the <HI>Creatures</HI> but <HI>Gods hoasts?</HI> He is <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><HI>Dominus exerci∣tuum. Amos</HI> 4.13. <HI>verse</HI> 8.</NOTE> <HI>the Lord of Hoasts:</HI> and (as <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vide Dauidem Kimchi in Radic.</HI></NOTE> the <HI>Rabbines</HI> well obserue) hee hath <HI>two</HI> generall <HI>troopes,</HI> as his <HI>horse,</HI> and <HI>foot,</HI><NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></NOTE> <HI>the vpper troope,</HI> and <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></NOTE> <HI>the lower troope,</HI> or <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><HI>Copiae tam infe∣riores, quam su∣pernae. Mercer.</HI></NOTE> <HI>the creatures aboue,</HI> and <HI>the creatures beneath,</HI> all ready prest to be employed, in <HI>warres,</HI> either <HI>defensiue,</HI> or <HI>offensiue,</HI> for the safegard of his <HI>fauourites,</HI> or the <HI>destruction</HI> of their <HI>opposites.</HI> Euen <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 34.7.</NOTE> the <HI>Angels</HI> themselues (saith the <HI>Psalmist) pitch their tents about those that feare God,</HI> &amp;c. <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Piis assident; impios obsident. Ambros. in Psal.</HI></NOTE> <HI>they lye in garrison, about the godly, to defend and deliuer them</HI>; they lie in <HI>campe</HI> against <HI>their enemies</HI> to <HI>offend,</HI> and to <HI>destroy</HI> them.</P>
<P N="2"><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 2.</NOTE>2. What are the <HI>Creatures,</HI> but <HI>Gods Sergeants at Armes</HI> to arrest, and attach <HI>Rebels?</HI> <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 119 91.</NOTE> <HI>All the crea∣tures</HI> (saith the <HI>Psalmist) are at his seruice.</HI> <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 104.4.</NOTE> <HI>The
<PB N="11" REF="12"/>
winds are his messengers, and the fire and flame his ministers.</HI> And <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 148.8.</NOTE> <HI>the haile,</HI> and <HI>snow his officers,</HI> and <HI>the executioners of his word:</HI> they serue him all, and they do his will, though <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Nec operis sunt consciae. Bern. de grat. &amp; lib. arb.</HI></NOTE> they know not what they doe. But they rebell against <HI>God</HI> himselfe (as we haue heard <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Point</HI> 1.</NOTE> before) that are vp in armes a∣gainst any of those that be his:<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 1.</NOTE> whom he hath vn∣dertaken the protection of; and concerning whom he hath giuen so expresse a charge by the <HI>Psalmist,</HI> <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 105.15.</NOTE> <HI>Touch not mine Anointed</HI>; that is, any one of mine holy ones. The place is commonly misvnderstood; not spoken of <HI>Kings</HI> directly (though <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Sam.</HI> 24.7. <HI>&amp;</HI> 26.9, 11.</NOTE> concerning them also, as being in a more speciall maner <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 89.20.</NOTE> <HI>Gods Anointed</HI>;) but to <HI>Kings</HI> (<NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 105.14.</NOTE> <HI>He rebuked euen Kings for their sakes</HI>) in the behalfe of his <HI>Saints,</HI> by him <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 1.21.</NOTE> spiritually anointed to be <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Apoc.</HI> 1.6. <HI>&amp;</HI> 5.10. <HI>&amp;</HI> 20.6. 1 <HI>Pet.</HI> 2.9.</NOTE> <HI>Kings,</HI> and <HI>Priests</HI> to him. These being in such maner his, the <HI>Creatures</HI> are all as his <HI>Purseuants,</HI> and his <HI>Sergeants at Armes</HI> to apprehend, and attach them all that make head against them, and <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Insectantur vos &amp; in vobis Deum. Saluian. de prouid. l.</HI> 8. <HI>c.</HI> 4.</NOTE> against himselfe in them; and either to bring them in, or to make his charge good vpon them, by destroying them, as he did <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 37.36.</NOTE> <HI>Senacheribs hoast,</HI> in the place.</P>
<P>The third <HI>Point</HI> of <HI>Instruction.</HI></P>
<Q>Est ciuitas Dei, Deus quam protegit.</Q>
<P>It is the <HI>Citie of God, that</HI> <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 37.35.</NOTE> <HI>God</HI> thus protecteth.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Instructiō</HI> 3.</NOTE> <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Verse</HI> 8.</NOTE> <HI>In the Citie of the Lord of Hoasts;</HI> (saith my <HI>Text) in the Citie of our God.</HI> And before, <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><HI>Verse</HI> 1.</NOTE> <HI>Great is the Lord, and greatly to be praised in the Citie of our God:</HI> <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><HI>Verse</HI> 3.</NOTE> <HI>In her Palaces it is that God is knowne for a sure re∣treat.</HI> It is <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Zech.</HI> 2.5.</NOTE> <HI>Ierusalem,</HI> that <HI>God</HI> is <HI>a wall of fire</HI> a∣bout. And vpon them it was that <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Apoc.</HI> 20.9.</NOTE> <HI>fire fell downe,
<PB N="12" REF="13"/>
and deuoured them, that beset the beloued Citie.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Reason</HI> hereof.</P>
<P N="1"><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 1.</NOTE>1. It is the place of <HI>Gods residence,</HI> where hee especially resideth, <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 132.14.</NOTE> <HI>This is my rest for euer</HI> (saith he) <HI>Here will I dwell, for I take delight in it.</HI> And <HI>Princes,</HI> though they haue a generall care of their whole <HI>kingdome,</HI> yet <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Sam.</HI> 5.9.</NOTE> a more speciall care of the places of their principall abode.</P>
<P N="2"><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 2.</NOTE>2. It is <HI>Gods inheritance.</HI> <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Deut.</HI> 9.29.</NOTE> <HI>They are thy people and thine inheritance,</HI> saith <HI>Moses.</HI> And we know how loth men are (witnesse <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>King.</HI> 21.3.</NOTE> <HI>Naboth</HI> the <HI>Iisrelite</HI>) to lose, or to depart with their <HI>inheritance,</HI> or any part of it.</P>
<P N="3"><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 3.</NOTE>3. It is <HI>Gods Vineyard.</HI> <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 5.7.</NOTE> <HI>Surely the Vineyard of the Lord of Hoasts is the house of Israel; and the men of Iuda his pleasant plantation.</HI> And his <HI>Vineyard</HI> hee saith <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 27.3.</NOTE> <HI>he will keepe, and watch continually night and day,</HI> without any <HI>moment</HI> of intermission, that <HI>no enemie assaile it,</HI> that none breake into it, to make spoile and hauocke of it.</P>
<P N="4"><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 4.</NOTE>4. It is <HI>Gods Garden.</HI> <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><HI>Cant.</HI> 4.12.</NOTE> <HI>My Sister, my Spouse, is as a Garden inclosed.</HI> And we know how carefull men are of any place to fence and pale in their <HI>Gardens,</HI> whatsoeuer place else, <HI>field,</HI> or <HI>Orchard,</HI> they suffer to lie open. Nor let vs thinke that <HI>God</HI> hath any whit lesse care of his, which hee delighteth so much in.</P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Obiection.</HI></NOTE>But how commeth it to passe then (may some say) that the <HI>Psalmist</HI> complaineth in that man∣ner? <HI>O Lord the Heathen are come into thine in∣heritance, they haue made Ierusalem an heape of stones,</HI> &amp;c.</P>
<P><PB N="13" REF="13"/>I answer.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Solution</HI> 1.</NOTE> 1. <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">The house of God. <HI>Gen.</HI> 28.19, 22.</NOTE> <HI>Beth-el</HI> sometime becommeth <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">The house of vanitie. <HI>Hosh.</HI> 5.8. <HI>&amp;</HI> 10.5</NOTE> <HI>Beth-auen.</HI> <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 1.2<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> The <HI>faithfull Citie</HI> sometime turneth <HI>Harlot.</HI> And it is iust with <HI>God</HI> then <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 50.1. <HI>Ier.</HI> 3.8.</NOTE> to <HI>cast her off;</HI> <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Heb.</HI> 8.9.</NOTE> <HI>Shee kept not couenants with me, and I cast her off, saith the Lord.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. <HI>Gods children</HI> sometime grow <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Hosh.</HI> 4.16. <HI>Tan∣quam indomita iu∣uenca. Quae velut latis eq<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a trima campis ludit exul∣tim, metint{que} tangi. Horat. car.</HI> 3.11.</NOTE> <HI>wanton,</HI> and prouoke <HI>God</HI> to wrath.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Solution</HI> 2.</NOTE> In which case <HI>God</HI> vseth the wicked as <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vtitur Deus cre∣atura rationali, sed maleuola tanquam disciplinae virga. Bern. de lib. arb.</HI></NOTE> <HI>rods,</HI> and <HI>scourges</HI> to correct them with. <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 10.5.</NOTE> <HI>Ashur</HI> (saith <HI>God</HI> by the <HI>Prophet Esay</HI>) is but <HI>the rod of my wrath.</HI> <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Eius consiliis mi∣litant, etiam qui ei{us} consiliis repugnant. Greg. mor. l.</HI> 6. <HI>c.</HI> 14.</NOTE> <HI>Euen they also</HI> (saith <HI>Gregory) worke for him,</HI> yea, and for them (though <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esay</HI> 10.7.</NOTE> they are not aware of it) that in such case <HI>fight</HI> both <HI>against him</HI> and them.</P>
<P N="3">3. Euen in the deepest of their distresses <HI>God</HI> ceaseth not to regard them:<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Solution</HI> 3.</NOTE> <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><HI>Deus suos nō neg∣ligit cum negligit.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Hee neglecteth them not, when hee seemeth most of all to neglect them.</HI> Though <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 49.14.</NOTE> <HI>Sion</HI> complaine that <HI>God had forgotten her:</HI> yet <HI>God</HI> assureth her that <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ibid.</HI> 15.</NOTE> <HI>he could no more for∣get her, than any Mother could her childe.</HI> <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ibid.</HI> 16.</NOTE> <HI>He carried her picture</HI> about him <HI>engrauen on the palmes of his hands, and her wals were euer in his eyes.</HI> And, <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ezek.</HI> 11.16.</NOTE> <HI>Al∣beit</HI> (saith <HI>God) I haue cast them far off among the Hea∣then, and haue scattered them into many countries, yet will I be as a little</HI> <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 8.14.</NOTE> <HI>Sanctuary vnto them in all places,</HI> wheresoeuer they shall become.</P>
<P>And so passe we to the fourth, and last <HI>point</HI> of <HI>Instruction.</HI></P>
<Q>Ecclesia Dei, nunquam dimouebitur.</Q>
<P><HI>Gods Church</HI> maugre the <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 25.19.</NOTE> <HI>malice</HI> of all her <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psa</HI> 3.1. <HI>&amp;</HI> 69 4.</NOTE> <HI>ma∣ny,</HI> and <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 18.17. <HI>&amp;</HI> 69 4.</NOTE> <HI>mighty aduersaries,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Instructiō</HI> 4.</NOTE> shall neuer be vtterly rooted out, or destroyed. <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 125.1.</NOTE> <HI>They that trust in the Lord shall be as mount Sion, that standeth fast, and can
<PB N="14" REF="14"/>
neuer be remoued.</HI> <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 16.18.</NOTE> <HI>Vpon this Rocke</HI> (saith our Saui∣our) <HI>will I build my Church, and the gates of Hell shall neuer preuaile against it.</HI> The <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Apoc.</HI> 2.5.</NOTE> <HI>Candlesticke</HI> may be <HI>remoued</HI> from place to place; but <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 60.19, 20.</NOTE> the <HI>light</HI> it selfe can neuer be <HI>put out.</HI> The <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Apoc.</HI> 12.14.</NOTE> <HI>Woman</HI> may be hunted, and chased into <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Heb.</HI> 11.38.</NOTE> the <HI>Wildernesse</HI>; but neuer dri∣uen vtterly out of the <HI>World.</HI> In the very <HI>Wilder∣nesse</HI> will <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Apoc.</HI> 12.14.</NOTE> <HI>God</HI> prouide a place for her, where she<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> shall be safe; and finde succour, till it please him to bring her abroad againe.</P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 1.</NOTE>The <HI>Reason</HI> hereof.</P>
<P N="1">1. <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Verse</HI> 8.</NOTE> <HI>God establisheth it,</HI> (saith my <HI>Text</HI>) and there∣fore standeth it fast <HI>for euer.</HI> <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 46.5.</NOTE> <HI>God is in the middest of it: and therefore shall it not stir.</HI> Yea <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Zach.</HI> 2.5.</NOTE> he is not in the middest of it only, but round about it too.<NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 125.2.</NOTE> <HI>As the Hilles stand about Ierusalem, so standeth God about his people from henceforth and for euermore.</HI> He is a∣bout it to protect it; in the midst of it to support it. Hee that vpholdeth the <HI>Heauens,</HI> vpholdeth it: for this is indeed his <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Coeli sancti &amp; iusti: sanctae animae omnes, in quibus habitat Deus, &amp; quae factae sunt se∣des eius. Aug. in Psal.</HI> 18. <HI>&amp;</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>9. <HI>&amp;</HI> 67. <HI>&amp;</HI> 96. <HI>&amp;</HI> 122. <HI>Esai.</HI> 57.15. <HI>&amp;</HI> 66.1, 2. <HI>Coelum Ecclesia est. Tychon. in Apoc.</HI> 11.19. <HI>&amp;</HI> 12.1.</NOTE> <HI>Heauen vpon earth.</HI> And as soone may men, or deuils pull downe <HI>Heauen</HI> it∣selfe, as destroy it.</P>
<P N="2">2. <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 16.18.</NOTE> <HI>Christ</HI> himselfe hath <HI>built</HI> it, and he hath foun∣ded it vpon himselfe.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Reason</HI> 2.</NOTE> For <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 10.4.</NOTE> hee is the <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 18.31.</NOTE> only true <HI>Rocke,</HI> the <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 26 4.</NOTE> <HI>Rocke</HI> of <HI>eternity</HI>; the only <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 28.16. <HI>Q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>od Bellarm. bla∣sphemè Papa tribu∣it in praefat. ad lib. de Pont. Rom.</HI></NOTE> <HI>sure foun∣dation,</HI> that his whole <HI>Church</HI> is built vpon. And what he buildeth can by no created power be pul∣led downe againe;<NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 3.11.</NOTE> the <HI>house</HI> that is built vpon that <HI>Rocke</HI> cannot be ouerthrowne. <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 7.25.</NOTE> <HI>Though the winds rose, and the raine fell, and the flouds came, and beat all together vpon that house, yet the frame fell not, because it was founded vpon that Rocke.</HI> It is <HI>Christs Master∣peece</HI>;
<PB N="15" REF="14"/>
that that he would shew his <HI>Deity,</HI> his <HI>diuine Power</HI> in. Would you haue me (saith <HI>Chrysostome</HI> speaking to the <HI>Iewes</HI>) proue vnto you, that <HI>Christ Iesus is God?</HI> what needs it? <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Luke</HI> 21.<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>4. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Chry∣sost. quod Christus Deus. Ejus ipsius, cuius fuerunt ne∣gatores, persecuto∣res, interfectores, vbique sunt testes. Aug. epist.</HI> 59 <HI>&amp; in Psal.</HI> 39. <HI>&amp;</HI> 56. <HI>&amp;</HI> 58. <HI>&amp; de temp</HI> 31. <HI>Nulla turpior ser∣uitus grauiorque, quam seruitus Iu∣daeorum, quam quo∣cunque ierint post se trahunt, &amp; vbi{que} Dominos offendunt suos. Bern. de consi∣der. l.</HI> 1.</NOTE> You your selues <HI>wan∣der</HI> vp and downe, the whole <HI>world</HI> ouer, <HI>preaching, and publishing</HI> his <HI>Deity</HI> to all those that consider in what sort you continue, and yet continue too, euer since that impious act of yours, in the crucifying of him. You goe <HI>branded</HI> with <HI>deepe and conspicuous markes</HI> of his <HI>wrath, and vengeance</HI> wheresoeuer you abide. But would you yet see some other <HI>pregnant proofe</HI> of his <HI>Deity?</HI> Let this one serue for all. <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Chrysost. quod Christus Deus.</HI></NOTE> <HI>What he razeth, none can reare againe; what he reareth, none can raze againe. He pulled downe your Temple, and it could neuer be built againe. He hath built him a Church, and it could neuer be pulled downe againe.</HI> It is a me∣morable story, and the more remarkable, because recorded (besides diuers others of <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><HI>Greg. Naz. in Iulian. orat.</HI> 2. <HI>Chrysost. contr. Iud. orat.</HI> 2. <HI>&amp; quod Christus Deus, &amp; in Matth. hom.</HI> 4. <HI>Ambr. ad Theodos. epist.</HI> 29. <HI>Theodoret. hist. eccles. l.</HI> 3. <HI>c.</HI> 20. <HI>Cassiod. hist. tripart. l</HI> 6. <HI>c.</HI> 43. <HI>&amp; alij.</HI></NOTE> our owne,) by <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ammian. Marcellin. hist. l.</HI> 23.</NOTE> an <HI>Heathen man</HI> also, one <HI>no friend to Christians, a traducer</HI> of <HI>Constantine,</HI> and an <HI>admirer</HI> of <HI>Iulian. Iulian,</HI> that wretched <HI>Apostata,</HI> to spite <HI>the Christi∣ans,</HI> whom he had professed himselfe formerly to be one of, but now hated most extremely, <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Greg. Naz. Chrysost. &amp; Theodor.</HI></NOTE> called the <HI>Iewes</HI> to him, and asked them, why they did not now sacrifice as in times past they had wont to doe. They made him answer, that by their <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Deut.</HI> 12.5, 6, 12, 13, 14.</NOTE> <HI>Law</HI> they might not sacrifice any where but in the <HI>Tem∣ple</HI>
<PB N="16" REF="15"/>
at <HI>Ierusalem:</HI> which since therefore it was rui∣ned, they had ceased to sacrifice, and must so doe till it were reedified. Hereupon <HI>Iulian</HI> told them that they should haue their <HI>Temple</HI> eft-soones built againe, if they would; and to that purpose <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Templum instau∣rare sumptibus co∣gitabat immodicis, negotium{que} matu∣randum Alypio de∣derat. Cùm itaque rei idem fortiter in∣staret, iuuaretque prouinciae rector &amp;c. Ammian. l.</HI> 23.</NOTE> hee sent one <HI>Alypius</HI> into those parts furnished with much treasure for the dispeeding of the worke, and withall caused the <HI>Gouernour</HI> of that <HI>Prouince</HI> to as∣sist him all that might be therein. Nor were the <HI>Iewes</HI> therein backward, <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Theodor. l.</HI> 3. <HI>c.</HI> 20. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Greg. Naz. stelit.</HI> 2.</NOTE> who flocking together out of all quarters, raised a great masse of <HI>money,</HI> and prouided abundance of <HI>materialls,</HI> for the set∣ting forward of so much, and so long desired a worke. But <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Chrysost. contr. Iud.</HI> 2. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Esai.</HI> 14.27. <HI>Ibid.</HI></NOTE> no might, or industry of man is able to preuaile against <HI>God,</HI> or to effect that, that he will not haue done. When all things were prepared now, and they began to fall to their businesse; First there arose <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Theodor. l.</HI> 3. <HI>c.</HI> 20. <HI>Vis magna ventorum repentè spirans, tempestatesque ac procellae subitò factae, quicquid congregatum fuerat, disperserunt. Cassiod. l.</HI> 6. <HI>c.</HI> 43.</NOTE> strange <HI>stormes,</HI> &amp; <HI>whirle-winds,</HI> that dissipated, and spoiled their <HI>materials.</HI> And after that, when yet they attempted to doe something, <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Chrysost. quod Christus Deus. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Ibid. Metuendi globi flammarum propè fundamenta crebris assultibus erumpentes, fecere locum exustis aliquoties operantibus inaccessum. Ammian. l.</HI> 23.</NOTE> fearefull <HI>balls</HI> of <HI>fire,</HI> not falling downe from <HI>hea∣uen,</HI> but bursting out of the very <HI>ground</HI> beneath, and that so oft as they assayed to go on with their <HI>work,</HI> ripped vp what they had wrought, and burnt vp the <HI>work-men,</HI> in so much that none durst any more approch the place, and so the very <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>{que} modo elemento destinatius repellente cessauit inceptum. Ibid.</HI></NOTE> <HI>elements</HI> (saith that <HI>Heathen man) obstinately making head</HI>
<PB N="17" REF="15"/>
against them, they were at length enforced wholly to giue ouer their <HI>enterprize.</HI> Thus was no power of man able to <HI>raise</HI> what he had <HI>ruined</HI>; nor shall any power euer be able to ruine what he hath <HI>rai∣sed.</HI> In stead of the <HI>Temple</HI> that he ruined hath he <HI>erected</HI> his <HI>Church</HI>; which vnlesse the <HI>Rocke</HI> may be remoued that it is built vpon, shall no power of man, or deuill be able euer to ouerthrow. Though all the wicked in the <HI>world,</HI> and <HI>all</HI> the <HI>Deuils</HI> in <HI>hell</HI> to them, conspire together in one, yet as soone shal they be able to driue <HI>Christ</HI> himselfe out of <HI>heauen,</HI> as to destroy vtterly and root out his <HI>Church</HI> here vpon <HI>earth.</HI></P>
<P>Thus you see then these foure <HI>Points</HI> of <HI>Instru∣ction</HI> plainly, and euidently proued vnto you.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Recapitulatiō. Points</HI> 4.</NOTE></P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. <HI>That they seeke their owne ruine, that seeke the ruine of Gods children.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Point</HI> 1.</NOTE></ITEM>
<ITEM>2. <HI>That Gods Creatures are ready prest to assist those that be his.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Point</HI> 2.</NOTE></ITEM>
<ITEM>3. <HI>That it is the Citie of God,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Point</HI> 3.</NOTE> <HI>that God thus prote∣cteth.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>4. <HI>That this Citie,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Point</HI> 4.</NOTE> <HI>or Church of God shall neuer be vtterly ouerthrowne.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>Let vs now proceed to the <HI>Vses</HI> that of these <HI>Points</HI> may be made.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Vses</HI> 4.</NOTE></P>
<P>And <HI>first</HI> this <HI>Text</HI> may be to the <HI>enemies</HI> of <HI>Gods Church,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Vse</HI> 1. <HI>of Point</HI> 1.</NOTE> as <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Dan.</HI> 5.5.</NOTE> those <HI>knuckles of a mans hand</HI> were to <HI>Baltasar,</HI> to <HI>write</HI> them their <HI>destiny</HI>; or as <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ibid.</HI> 24, 25.</NOTE> <HI>Daniel</HI> was to him, to <HI>reade</HI> it vnto them; to informe them, what the end and issue shal be of all their <HI>plots</HI> and <HI>proiects</HI> against the <HI>Church of God.</HI> In plotting, and proiecting the ruine of it, they <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Suo sibi iumento arcessunt malum. Plaut. Amphitr.</HI></NOTE> plot and proiect
<PB N="18" REF="16"/>
but their owne confusion: Nor shall their <HI>plots,</HI> and <HI>proiects</HI> take (as they hope) against it, but they shal take (which they, it may be, little deeme, or once dreame of) against themselues. <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 9.16.</NOTE> <HI>God</HI> will shew himselfe to be <HI>God</HI> indeed <HI>by executing of Iudgement,</HI> in causing them to be <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Apolinar. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Dolscius.</HI></NOTE> <HI>ensnared, and caught in the worke of their owne hands,</HI> <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 9.15.</NOTE> in a <HI>snare</HI> of their owne setting, <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Theodoret. dialog.</HI> 1. <HI>c.</HI> 24.</NOTE> in a <HI>net</HI> of their owne weauing: in cau∣sing <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ester</HI> 7.9, 10. <HI>Prou. Ebr. Cippum occupauit ipse, quē fecit, faber. Drus. decur.</HI> 1. <HI>adag.</HI> 4. <HI>Et Lat. Gestat fa∣ber, quas fecit ipse, compedes. Auson. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Theogn.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Haman</HI> to be hanged on that <HI>Gibbet</HI> himselfe, that for <HI>Mordecai</HI> he had erected, &amp; bringing him, and <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ester</HI> 9.10, 13, 14.</NOTE> his whole House to destruction by those meanes, whereby <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ester</HI> 3.6.</NOTE> he sought the destruction of the whole <HI>Iewish Nation.</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Application.</HI></NOTE></P>
<P>In this kinde may we well say, <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><HI>Verse</HI> 8.</NOTE> <HI>Sicut audiuimus, sic &amp; vidimus; What wee haue heard we haue seene</HI>; both in that deliuerance that through <HI>Gods good∣nesse</HI> this day we suruiue to celebrate, and in <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">The powder-plot &amp;c.</NOTE> di∣uers others also. They that came to sinke vs, were sunke themselues. They that thought to blow vs vp, were some of them blowen vp themselues. They that plotted the ruine, and confusion of our estate, brought ruine and confusion vpon them∣selues, and theirs. <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iudg.</HI> 5.31.</NOTE> <HI>So let all thine enemies perish, O Lord. But let those that loue thee,</HI> and stand for thee, <HI>be as the Sunne when he shineth in his full strength.</HI></P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Vse</HI> 2. <HI>of Point</HI> 2.</NOTE>Secondly, it may serue as to <HI>discourage the Ad∣uersary,</HI> so to <HI>encourage the godly.</HI> As to discourage the wicked from attempting ought against <HI>Gods Church,</HI> (<NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 21.11.</NOTE> <HI>They intended euill against thee,</HI> saith the <HI>Psalmist; but they were not able to effect it</HI>) so to en∣courage those that <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Sam.</HI> 18.17.</NOTE> <HI>fight Gods battels</HI>; they cannot want helpe. <HI>Heauen and earth</HI> fighteth for them.
<PB N="19" REF="16"/>
Though they may seeme the <HI>weaker</HI> side, and to haue <HI>fewer</HI> assistants, yet <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Cor.</HI> 12.9.</NOTE> <HI>Gods power is perfected,</HI> and appeareth most in <HI>mans weaknesse:</HI> And if wee had <HI>eyes</HI> to see it, we might see <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>King.</HI> 6.16. 2 <HI>Chron.</HI> 32.7.</NOTE> <HI>more with</HI> them <HI>than against them:</HI> <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Quocunque se verterit, ibi te vi∣deat. Sen. de benef.</HI></NOTE> which way soeuer they turne themselues, they might see <HI>helpes alwayes at hand</HI>; <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 46.1.</NOTE> <HI>God</HI> himselfe, and all the <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><HI>Job</HI> 5.23.</NOTE> <HI>creatures</HI> of <HI>God,</HI> ready prest at <HI>Gods becke</HI> <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 91.11.</NOTE> to <HI>attend</HI> them,<NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Dan.</HI> 10.12, 13.</NOTE> to assist them, <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 34.7.</NOTE> to <HI>guard</HI> them, <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Iudg.</HI> 5.30.</NOTE> to <HI>fight</HI> for them, <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Exod.</HI> 23.28.</NOTE> to <HI>oppose</HI> those that fight against them.</P>
<P>And here we may againe sing,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Application.</HI></NOTE> <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Verse</HI> 8.</NOTE> <HI>Sicut audiui∣mus, sic vidimus; What we haue heard we haue seene.</HI> <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Quam benè te, ambitio, mersit, va∣nissima, ventus? Et tumidos tumidae vos superastis aquae? Quam benè totius raptores orbis aua∣ros, Hausit inex∣hausti iusta v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rago maris? Theod. Beza.</HI></NOTE> The <HI>winds,</HI> and the <HI>Seas</HI> fought for vs, when time was; the one dissipated and scattered, the other swallowed vp, and deuoured those, that came with hope to haue dissipated, and <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 27.2. <HI>&amp;</HI> 124.3.</NOTE> with open mouth to haue swallowed, drowne, and deuoured vs. <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 124.6.</NOTE> <HI>Blessed be God, that gaue vs not vp as a prey vnto their teeth.</HI></P>
<P>Thirdly, is it the <HI>Citie of God,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Vse</HI> 3. <HI>of Point</HI> 3.</NOTE> <HI>that God</HI> thus <HI>pro∣tecteth?</HI> Then learne we the reason hence why <HI>God</HI> hath in this manner done for vs. It is for his <HI>Church</HI> among vs, his <HI>Name</HI> called vpon, his <HI>Gospell</HI> pro∣fessed by vs, his <HI>worship</HI> retained with vs. And cer∣tainly (obserue we, and we shall vndoubtedly find it to be so that) since <HI>Gods truth</HI> and <HI>Gospell</HI> esta∣blished with vs, and that <HI>Romish Idolatrie</HI> expelled from among vs, this <HI>Iland</HI> of ours hath enioyed the <HI>quietest,</HI> the <HI>peaceablest,</HI> the <HI>most prosperous times,</HI> that euer it did, for so long time together, at any time, that any memory of man, or record of story can be produced of, notwithstanding all the <HI>power</HI> that
<PB N="20" REF="17"/>
that <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Thess.</HI> 2.3.</NOTE> <HI>Man of sinne,</HI> and all his <HI>adherents</HI> were able to raise vp against vs. And as many strange <HI>deliue∣rances</HI> hath <HI>God</HI> vouchsafed vs, as euer any <HI>Nation</HI> vnder the <HI>cope of heauen</HI> had. Oh that our <HI>thankful∣nesse</HI> to <HI>God</HI> were in any good measure proportio∣nable to <HI>Gods goodnesse</HI> towards vs. But it is to be feared, that that of <HI>Saluian</HI> is too too true of vs; <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><HI>Deus bona dat, vt boni simus. Nos vbi bona accepimus, mala cumulamus. Saluian. de prouid. l.</HI> 3.</NOTE> <HI>God giueth vs good things, to make vs good:</HI> but <HI>wee when we haue receiued good from God, returne euill againe to him.</HI> And that of <HI>Hosea,</HI> <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Hosh.</HI> 4.7.</NOTE> <HI>As they were increased, so they sinned against me: and I will turne their glory therefore into shame.</HI> Which if it be so; let vs remem∣ber, that as the same <HI>Saluian</HI> saith, <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ideò deteriores sumus, quia melio∣res essè debemus. Saluian. Ibid.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Therefore are we worse than others,</HI> whom <HI>God</HI> hath not done the like for, though we be no worse, if but as bad only, <HI>because we ought to be better.</HI> So, as the <HI>Centurists</HI> ob∣serue, <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ingentia benefi∣cia, ingentia flagi∣tia, ingentia suppli∣cia. Magdeburg. in prafat. ad Centur.</HI> 5.</NOTE> <HI>great blessings, seconded with grieuous sinnes, will at length draw downe extraordinary iudgements.</HI> And it had beene better for vs neuer to haue had such <HI>deliuerances,</HI> if we be not carefull to shew our selues truly thankfull vnto him, that hath wrought so great <HI>deliuerances</HI> for vs.</P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Vse</HI> 4. <HI>of Point</HI> 4.</NOTE>Fourthly, it may teach <HI>Gods Children</HI> not to be <HI>dismaid,</HI> if the enemies of <HI>Gods Church</HI> seeme some∣time <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Dan.</HI> 8.24, 25. <HI>Apoc.</HI> 13.6, 7.</NOTE> to <HI>preuaile</HI> against it. For <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ier.</HI> 31.35, 36, 37. <HI>&amp;</HI> 33.20, 21, 25, 26.</NOTE> they shall ne∣uer be able to root it out for all that. <HI>Gods Church</HI> is as <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Exod.</HI> 3.2.</NOTE> the <HI>bush,</HI> that <HI>burnt, and consumed not,</HI> as <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>&amp;c. Plut. sympos. l.</HI> 8. <HI>q.</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></NOTE> the <HI>Palme-tree,</HI> that <HI>spreadeth,</HI> and <HI>springeth</HI> vp the more it is <HI>oppressed:</HI> as <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <HI>Sibyll. Mergitur interdum, sed non submergitur vnquam. Merses profundo; pul∣chrior euenit. Luctere; multa proruet integrum Cum laude victorem. Horat. Carm.</HI> 4.4.</NOTE> the <HI>bottle,</HI> or <HI>bladder,</HI> that may
<PB N="21" REF="17"/>
be <HI>dipped,</HI> but cannot be <HI>drowned:</HI> as <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Duris vt ilex tonsa bipennibus per damna, per cae∣des ab ipso ducit opes animum{que} fer∣ro. Ibid.</HI></NOTE> the <HI>Oke,</HI> that taketh heart to grace from the <HI>maimes</HI> and <HI>wounds</HI> giuen it, and <HI>sprouteth</HI> out <HI>thicker</HI> than be∣fore. <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Sanguis Marty∣rum semen Eccle∣siae. plures efficimur, quoties metimur à vobis. Semen est sanguis Christiano∣rum. Tertull. apo∣log. Sparsus est san∣guis iustus: &amp; illo sanguine tamquam seminatione facta seges surrexit Ec∣clesiae. August. in Psal.</HI> 39. <HI>veritas per orbem terrae pullu∣lauit faecundius, cùm in Martyrum sanguine sereretur. Idē Ciuit. l.</HI> 22. <HI>c.</HI> 7.</NOTE> <HI>The bloud of the Martyrs is the seed of the Church</HI>; it springeth againe as <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> est quae re∣paret, seque ipsa reseminet ales. Ouid. met. l.</HI> 15. <HI>Faecunda reparat sic morte iuuentam. Claudianus in Stilic. l.</HI> 2. <HI>De Palma quadam in Chora mirum accepimus, cum Phoenice aue, quae putatur ex huius palmae argumento nomen accepisse, emori, ac renas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i ex seipsa. Plin. hist. nat. l.</HI> 13. <HI>c.</HI> 4. <HI>Hinc error Tertulliani enatus, qui illud Psal.</HI> 92.12. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>Graecè, de aue (non arbore, Hebraicae linguae ignarus) intellexit, quae se funerans renouat, natali fide de∣cedens atque succedens iterum. Lib. de resurr. Si tamen vt creditur de sua morte renascitur. Aug. de orig. anim. l.</HI> 4. <HI>c.</HI> 20. <HI>Vide &amp; Clement. Apost. constit. l.</HI> 5. <HI>c.</HI> 7. <HI>Plin. hist. nat. l.</HI> 10. <HI>c.</HI> 2. <HI>Oppian. de ancup. Orum in hieroglyph. Claudian. &amp; Lactant. nom carm. de Phoenice &amp;c.</HI></NOTE> the <HI>Phoenix</HI> doth out of her owne ashes, or as <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Non hydra secto corpore firmior vinci dolentem creuit in Herculem succisa serpens caede se reparans sua. Sen. Med.</HI> 4.1.</NOTE> the <HI>Hydra</HI> rather re∣paireth her selfe out of her own losses with a much more plentifull increase. <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Exod.</HI> 1.12. <HI>Sic foenum graecum qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> peius tractatur, prouenit melius. Plin. hist. l.</HI> 18. <HI>c.</HI> 16.</NOTE> The more <HI>Pharao</HI> op∣pressed the <HI>Ebrewes,</HI> the more they increased, and the mightier they grew. The <HI>Children of God</HI> in the <HI>Word</HI> are compared especially to <HI>two sorts</HI> of <HI>silly creatures,</HI> to <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Cant.</HI> 2.14. <HI>&amp;</HI> 6.9. <HI>Matth.</HI> 10.16.</NOTE> <HI>Doues,</HI> and to <HI>Sheepe.</HI> <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vt fugit accipitrem penna trepidante columba, Vt solet accipiter trepidas vrgere columbas. Ouid. Met. l.</HI> 1.</NOTE> No fowle more preyed vpon by <HI>Eagles, Haukes, Vultures,</HI> and other birds of prey, than the poore <HI>Pigeon.</HI> And yet, <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Quantum vult consumat edacitas vulturum, tamen maior est numerus columbarum. Optat. contr. Parmen. l.</HI> 2.</NOTE> let those rauenous fowles (saith <HI>Optatus</HI>) con∣sume neuer so many of them, there will be a grea∣ter number of <HI>Doues</HI> still, than of any kind of them. There is more <HI>Doues</HI> than <HI>Haukes,</HI> or than <HI>Kites,</HI> for all that. Againe, for the <HI>Sheepe,</HI> it is one of the sil∣liest creatures that is, and most vnable to defend it selfe: neither is it vnknowne to vs (to spare to speak <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ier.</HI> 50.6. <HI>Esai.</HI> 56.9. 1 <HI>Sam.</HI> 17.34. <HI>Ezek.</HI> 34.5. <HI>In praedam lupis ferisque r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>liquis exp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>siti sunt cum primis ouium greges. Spin. de prouid.</HI></NOTE> how they are preyed vpon in those places where
<PB N="22" REF="18"/>
<HI>Wolues,</HI> and <HI>Beares,</HI> and <HI>Lions,</HI> &amp; other wilde beasts are rife) how many of them are <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 44.11, 22. <HI>Ier.</HI> 12.3. <HI>Ouium homini cib{us} frequentissimus, vt nullus fere alius in lauienam veniat. Spin. ibid.</HI></NOTE> slaine for mans vse; no one sort of creatures commeth so frequent to the <HI>Shambles</HI> as they; they come not by one, or two, but they are driuen by troopes thither; as also how many of them die by diseases; they are subiect to <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Saeuissima inter eos pestis gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssatur. Ibid.</HI></NOTE> rots, and murreons, that <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><HI>Illa cateruatim dat stragem. Afri∣can. in Geopon.</HI></NOTE> make hauocke of them by whole sale; nor are they naturally so fruit∣full as many other beasts are, and those of prey by name, some of them, as the <HI>Fox</HI> and others, that bring diuers at a litter, whereas <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><HI>Vnicum dunta∣xat quotannis pa∣rit. Spin.</HI></NOTE> the <HI>Ewe</HI> hath vsu∣ally but one. And yet for all this wee see what <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Nullum animal frequentius in agris accurrit. Idem.</HI></NOTE> plenty there is euery where of them. We may see <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><HI>Oues olim mite pecus, nunc tam in∣domitum &amp; edax, vt homines deuo∣rent, oppida diru∣ant. Th. Morus Vtop. l.</HI> 1.</NOTE> <HI>Sheepe</HI> eat out <HI>men</HI> in many places among vs; and whole <HI>Townes</HI> by them depopulated and tur∣ned into <HI>Sheepe-walkes.</HI> Such a <HI>prouidence of God</HI> is there in the <HI>preseruation,</HI> and <HI>increase</HI> of that <HI>Crea∣ture</HI> that so <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 23.1, 2. <HI>&amp;</HI> 74.1. <HI>&amp;</HI> 77.20. <HI>&amp;</HI> 79.13. <HI>&amp;</HI> 80.1. <HI>&amp;</HI> 95.7. <HI>&amp;</HI> 100.3. <HI>Esai.</HI> 40.11. <HI>&amp;</HI> 63.11. <HI>Ier.</HI> 23.1, 3. <HI>&amp;</HI> 31.10. <HI>&amp;</HI> 49.20. <HI>&amp;</HI> 50.6.</NOTE> oft he compareth his <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>Children vnto,</HI> whom he hath taken into his speci∣all and peculiar <HI>protection</HI>; and whom therefore their cruell <HI>Aduersaries</HI> shall no more be able to root out, than the <HI>Haukes</HI> able to destroy all the <HI>Doues</HI> that are, or the <HI>Wolues</HI> to woory, and slay all the <HI>Sheepe</HI> in the <HI>World.</HI></P>
<P><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Question.</HI></NOTE>Yea but (may some say) may we in this Land then be sure euer of such safetie,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ezek.</HI> 34.22, 23, 31. <HI>&amp;</HI> 36.37, 38. <HI>&amp;</HI> 37.24, 26.</NOTE> neuer to be ouer∣runne, or rooted out?</P>
<P>No: It is <HI>Gods Church</HI> in generall, not this or that <HI>Church</HI> in part<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ular,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Answer.</HI></NOTE> that is sure thus constantly to continue.<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Mica</HI> 2.12. <HI>&amp;</HI> 7.14. <HI>Zach.</HI> 9.16. <HI>&amp;</HI> 10.3. <HI>&amp;</HI> 11.7, 11. <HI>&amp;</HI> 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.7. <HI>Matth.</HI> 10.16. <HI>&amp;</HI> 9.36. <HI>&amp;</HI> 26.31. <HI>&amp;</HI> 25.32, 33. <HI>Iohn</HI> 10.2, 3, 4, 7, 8, 11, 12, 15, 16, 26, 27, 28.</NOTE> Now <HI>Gods Church</HI> is not confined to this,
<PB N="23" REF="18"/>
or that <HI>place</HI>; nor is <HI>Gods protection</HI> tied vnto, or en∣tailed vpon this, or that <HI>people.</HI> We haue <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 119.57, 94. <HI>Ier.</HI> 2.3.</NOTE> no <HI>pro∣mise of protection</HI> longer than wee continue <HI>Gods portion.</HI> Wee haue <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Cor.</HI> 10.1-12.</NOTE> no better <HI>euidence,</HI> nor <HI>assu∣rance</HI> than the <HI>Iewes</HI> had: <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 132.14.</NOTE> <HI>Here</HI> (saith <HI>God) shall be my rest for euer.</HI> And, <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Verse</HI> 8.</NOTE> <HI>God will establish it for euer.</HI> And, <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><HI>Psal.</HI> 89.23. <HI>Esai.</HI> 41.11, 12.</NOTE> <HI>I will destroy all that rise against it.</HI> And yet wee know <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Luk.</HI> 19.44. <HI>&amp;</HI> 21.24.</NOTE> what is become of them at this day, <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 23.38.</NOTE> <HI>Their habitation is left desolate.</HI> And <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Thess.</HI> 2.16.</NOTE> <HI>The wrath of God</HI> (saith the <HI>Apostle) is come vpon them to the vt∣most.</HI> It is true indeed, that <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Deus nisi dese∣rentem se non dese∣rit, priusquam de∣seratur neminem deserit. Aug. ad im∣poss. sibi art.</HI> 7. <HI>Re∣cessurum non dese∣rit antequam dese∣rat. Ibid.</HI> 14. <HI>Non enim nos deserit fons, si nos fontem nō deseramus. Idem in Ioan.</HI> 32.</NOTE> <HI>God neuer leaueth any, but those that leaue him.</HI> But if <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>King.</HI> 11.7, 9.</NOTE> <HI>Salomon leaue God, and build Temples</HI> for <HI>Milcom,</HI> and <HI>Chamosh; God will leaue him,</HI> and <HI>raise vp aduersaries</HI> on al sides against him. If <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">2 <HI>Chron.</HI> 32.25.</NOTE> <HI>Ezekiaes heart be lift vp;</HI> <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 39.6, 7. 2 <HI>Chron.</HI> 32.26.</NOTE> <HI>God will pull him downe</HI> againe. If <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 1.21. <HI>Ier.</HI> 3.2. <HI>&amp;</HI> 9.2.</NOTE> <HI>the holy Citie</HI> become <HI>an Harlot,</HI> or <HI>a</HI> <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Facta est vrbs to∣ta lupanar. Iuuen. sat.</HI> 1. <HI>Vnus gurges omnium gula: vnū pene lupanar est omnium vita. Sal∣uian. de prou. l.</HI> 7.</NOTE> <HI>Stewes</HI> (as he speaketh) no reason but that <HI>God</HI> should <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ier.</HI> 7.29. <HI>&amp;</HI> 12.7.</NOTE> <HI>abandon</HI> it, and giue her <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ier.</HI> 3.8.</NOTE> <HI>a Bill of diuorce,</HI> and <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ezek.</HI> 13.36, 45, 47.</NOTE> deale with <HI>Aholah,</HI> and <HI>Aholibah,</HI> as <HI>adulterous women</HI> are wont to be dealt with. If <HI>Gods Vine</HI> grow not <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><HI>Hoshea</HI> 10.1.</NOTE> barren only, but beare <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><HI>Deut.</HI> 32 32.</NOTE> <HI>bitter,</HI> <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 5.2.</NOTE> <HI>noysome,</HI> and <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><HI>Deut.</HI> 32.33.</NOTE> <HI>poysonfull grapes</HI>; it shall be a iust thing with <HI>God</HI> to <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 5.5. <HI>Psal.</HI> 80.12.</NOTE> <HI>plucke vp her hedge,</HI> and <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><HI>Esai.</HI> 5.6. <HI>Ier.</HI> 12.11.</NOTE> <HI>lay her waste,</HI> <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ier.</HI> 9.11, 12.</NOTE> <HI>as a wilde wildernesse,</HI> or <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><HI>Matth.</HI> 3.10. <HI>&amp;</HI> 7.19 <HI>Luk.</HI> 13.7.</NOTE> <HI>to cut her downe,</HI> and <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ezek.</HI> 15.4, 6.</NOTE> <HI>cast her into the fire.</HI> If <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><HI>Numb.</HI> 11.5. <HI>&amp;</HI> 14.3, 4.</NOTE> <HI>Israel</HI> begin to <HI>looke backe into Aegypt</HI>; it shall be iust with <HI>God</HI> <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><HI>Deut.</HI> 28.68.</NOTE> to <HI>bring backe his Israel</HI> that was, into their former <HI>Aegyptian bondage</HI> againe. If the <HI>Hebrewes</HI> liue in those <HI>abominable courses</HI> <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><HI>Leuit.</HI> 1.24, 25. <HI>Deut.</HI> 18.12.</NOTE> for which <HI>God cast out the
<PB N="24" REF="19"/>
Canaanites,</HI> <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><HI>Leuit.</HI> 18.28.</NOTE> the Land <HI>that spewed out the Canaanite,</HI> shall now <HI>spew them out.</HI> If <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ezek.</HI> 5.6. <HI>&amp;</HI> 16.47, 48.</NOTE> <HI>Gods</HI> owne <HI>people</HI> grow <HI>worse than the Heathen</HI> themselues; it shall be iust with <HI>God,</HI> to <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ezek.</HI> 7.24.</NOTE> <HI>bring</HI> the very <HI>worst of the Hea∣then</HI> in vpon them, and by them, whom they <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ezek.</HI> 16.51, 52.</NOTE> <HI>iusti∣fie</HI> in some sort, <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ezek.</HI> 7.21.</NOTE> to destroy them. Nor may <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><HI>Ier.</HI> 25.28, 29. <HI>Rom.</HI> 11.<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, 21.</NOTE> we looke to fare better than they did, if we be faultie as they were. <HI>Gods Church</HI> may stand firme and sta∣ble still, though wee fall. The <HI>Lampe</HI> may burne cleare else-where, though the <HI>Light</HI> be done out with vs. If we desire therefore to haue this <HI>Protecti∣on</HI> continued vnto vs, let vs continue to be <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><HI>Deut.</HI> 32.9. <HI>Exod.</HI> 19.5, 6.</NOTE> <HI>Gods,</HI> that <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><HI>Deut.</HI> 26.17, 18. <HI>Ier.</HI> 7.23. <HI>&amp;</HI> 31.33.</NOTE> <HI>God</HI> may continue to bee ours. Let vs bee carefull to keepe and maintaine <HI>a Church of God</HI> with vs, <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><HI>Semen sanctum statumen terra. Esai.</HI> 6.13.</NOTE> <HI>The holy seed vpholdeth the state.</HI> In a word, as <HI>Samuel</HI> to his people (whose words I will end all with) <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">1 <HI>Sam.</HI> 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.24, 25.</NOTE> <HI>Feare the Lord, and serue him with all your heart in sinceritie; and consider what great things he hath hitherto done for you.</HI></P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="19"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

