<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>

<HEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Abrahams decease A meditation on Genesis 25.8. Deliuered at the funerall of that worthy seruant of Christ, Mr. Richard Stock, late pastor of All-Hallowes Bread-street: together with the testimonie then giuen vnto him. By Thomas Gataker B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>Approx. 186 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBPLACE>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</PUBPLACE><PUBLISHER>Text Creation Partnership,</PUBLISHER><DATE>2004-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 1).</DATE><IDNO TYPE="DLPS">A01523</IDNO>


<IDNO TYPE="stc">STC 11647</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="stc">ESTC S102880</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="eebo citation">99838642</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="proquest">99838642</IDNO>

<IDNO TYPE="vid">3028</IDNO>
<AVAILABILITY><P>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SERIESSTMT><TITLE>Early English books online.</TITLE></SERIESSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 1, no. A01523)</NOTE><NOTE>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3028)</NOTE><NOTE>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1099:05)</NOTE></NOTESSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBLFULL><TITLESTMT><TITLE TYPE="245" I2="0">Abrahams decease A meditation on Genesis 25.8. Deliuered at the funerall of that worthy seruant of Christ, Mr. Richard Stock, late pastor of All-Hallowes Bread-street: together with the testimonie then giuen vnto him. By Thomas Gataker B. of D. and pastor of Rotherhith.</TITLE><AUTHOR>Gataker, Thomas, 1574-1654.</AUTHOR></TITLESTMT><EXTENT>[6], 62, [2] p.   </EXTENT><PUBLICATIONSTMT>
<PUBPLACE>London :</PUBPLACE>
<PUBLISHER>Printed by Iohn Haviland for Fulke Clifton, and are to be sold at his shop on New-fishstreet hill, vnder St. Margarets Church, at the signe of the holy Lambe,</PUBLISHER>
<DATE>1627.</DATE>
</PUBLICATIONSTMT><NOTESSTMT><NOTE>With a final errata leaf.</NOTE><NOTE>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</NOTE></NOTESSTMT></BIBLFULL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Header created with script mrcb2eeboutf.xsl on 2014-03-05.</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL N="4"><P>Manually keyed and coded text linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</P><P>Issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</P><P>Keying and markup guidelines available at TCP web site (http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/)</P></EDITORIALDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><LANGUSAGE ID="eng"><LANGUAGE>eng</LANGUAGE></LANGUSAGE><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS><TERM>Stock, Richard, 1569?-1626.</TERM><TERM>Sermons, English --  17th century.</TERM><TERM>Funeral sermons.</TERM></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC><REVISIONDESC><CHANGE><DATE>2004-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>TCP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Assigned for keying and markup</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-08</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Apex CoVantage</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Sampled and proofread</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-09</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Judith Siefring</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Text and markup reviewed and edited</ITEM></CHANGE><CHANGE><DATE>2004-10</DATE><RESPSTMT><RESP>pfs</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</ITEM></CHANGE></REVISIONDESC></HEADER>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A01523">
<STC T="S">11647</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99838642</BIBNO>
<VID>3028</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P><PB REF="1"/>
ABRAHAMS DECEASE. A MEDITATION ON GENESIS 25. 8. DELIVERED AT THE FV∣NERALL OF THAT WORTHY SER∣uant of Christ, M<SUP>r</SUP>. RICHARD STOCK, Late Pastor of All-Hallowes Bread-street: TOGETHER WITH THE TESTIMO∣nie then giuen vnto him.</P>
<P>By THOMAS GATAKER B. of D. and Pastor of <HI>Rotherhith.</HI></P>
<P>LONDON, Printed by <HI>Iohn Haviland</HI> for <HI>Fulke Clifton,</HI> and are to be sold at his shop on New-fishstreet hill, vnder S<SUP>t</SUP>. <HI>Margarets</HI> Church, at the signe of the holy Lambe. 1627.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR HENRY YELVERTON Knight, one of the Iustices of his Maiesties Court of <HI>Common Pleas.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL;</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">Y</SEG>OVR <HI>speciall interest</HI> in that <HI>worthy Ser∣uant</HI> of <HI>Christ,</HI> whom this <HI>weak work</HI> con∣cerneth, by your <HI>sin∣gular fauours</HI> to him and his deseruedly procured, cānot but giue you <HI>interest</HI> in the <HI>worke</HI> it selfe before any. Vnto your <HI>Worship</HI> therefore I addresse
<PB REF="3"/>
and direct it, as to one that may iustly lay <HI>best claime</HI> to it: Not doubting but that, as you did in more than ordinary manner <HI>re∣spect</HI> his <HI>person</HI> while he <HI>liued,</HI> so you do no lesse <HI>honour</HI> the <HI>memory</HI> of him now <HI>deceased.</HI> The <HI>worke</HI> I wish were <HI>worthy</HI> either <HI>you</HI> or <HI>him.</HI> But, how little time I had for the <HI>compo∣sing</HI> and <HI>peecing vp</HI> of these <HI>broken Meditati∣ons,</HI> cannot be vnknowne to those, &amp; from them may be made knowne to others, that either <HI>sent</HI> or <HI>brought</HI> me the <HI>first word</HI> of his <HI>decease,</HI> being newly allighted from a <HI>wearisome iourney,</HI> not aboue <HI>two daies</HI> before the <HI>Funerall</HI> was to be performed. Besides that so <HI>sudden</HI> and vnexpected <HI>tidings</HI> of the <HI>losse</HI> of so deare a <HI>Friend,</HI> causing much <HI>griefe</HI> and <HI>distractiō,</HI> could not but produce with∣all as great an <HI>indisposition</HI> to the minding of that that this <HI>office</HI> imposed on me did ne∣cessarily require of me; and defeat conse∣quently that <HI>second</HI> <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Diligentia sub∣dium. Cicero pro Quinct.</NOTE> <HI>helpe</HI> of <HI>redoubled di∣ligence,</HI> </P>
<P> which others are wont to vse (as the <HI>sea-man</HI> his <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>oares,</HI> when the <HI>wind</HI> slacketh or scanteth) to redeeme the want of <HI>time</HI> with. That which made me (as conscious of the <HI>rawnesse</HI> of it) the more backward at
<PB REF="3"/>
first to yeeld to the importunitie of those, (not a few) who both by <HI>letters</HI> and by <HI>word</HI> of mouth were very instant and vr∣gent for the publishing of it. Nor haue I had much <HI>loisure</HI> since to <HI>reuise</HI> and <HI>digest</HI> my <HI>confused notes;</HI> nor yet <HI>desire</HI> to <HI>adde</HI> or <HI>alter</HI> much, lest (to those that then heard it) it might seeme not the same. One short <HI>pas∣sage</HI> or two onely I haue inserted, that my <HI>memory</HI> then failed me in. Else the <HI>substance</HI> of all here was then deliuered. Which if, espe∣cially in the <HI>Testimony</HI> then giuē vnto him, whom this <HI>office</HI> was performed vnto, it seeme <HI>slight</HI> and <HI>slender,</HI> to that it ought or might haue beene: Besides the former <HI>consi∣derations,</HI> which might well sufficiently ex∣cuse, let it be remembred; what a great <HI>Ora∣tour</HI> sometime said, that <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Pictores pulchrā absolutam{que} faciem rarò nisi in peius ef∣fingunt. Plin. Sec. lib. 5. epist. 10.</NOTE> <HI>An exact face is ve∣ry seldome drawn but with much disaduantage:</HI> how much more when <HI>a bungler</HI> but hath it in hand? I may well say of him, as he some∣time of <HI>Basile,</HI> <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Greg. Naz. in Basil.</NOTE> <HI>There wanted but his owne tongue to commend him with.</HI> A <HI>better</HI> I wish there had been employed therin than mine owne; or that mine owne (if but for his sake) had (at least then) been <HI>better.</HI> But the
<PB REF="4"/>
best is, <HI>The Sea needs not the Riuers, that</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Ibid.</NOTE> <HI>yet runne into it;</HI> nor he either mine, or any other mans <HI>praise;</HI> that due <HI>honour</HI> and re∣uerent <HI>estimation</HI> of him remaining in the <HI>mindes</HI> of so <HI>many,</HI> that neither mine, nor a∣ny other mans, <HI>commendation</HI> of him, either need to adde ought, or can adde much ther∣unto. Howbeit this may bide, when they are gone. Which whatsoeuer it is, presuming that <HI>your Worship</HI> will <HI>accept</HI> of, if not for it owne sake, yet for his, who <HI>liueth</HI> yet with you, and you desire (I know) should doe so also with others, I <HI>recommend</HI> it to your <HI>pa∣tronage,</HI> and <HI>your selfe</HI> with <HI>all yours</HI> to the <HI>protection</HI> of him who hath promised to be <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Sol &amp; Seutum. Psal. 84. 12.</NOTE> <HI>Sunne</HI> and <HI>Shield</HI> to all those that sincere∣ly <HI>rely</HI> on him; and rest.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your Worships to be commanded in the Lord Iesus, THO. GATAKER.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<PB N="1" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>THE TESTIMONIE GIVEN TO THAT worthy Seruant of CHRIST, Master RICHARD STOCK, at his Funerall.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">A</SEG>LL <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Christianor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> cor∣pora Christi mem∣bra, Dei templa. Tertul. de resurr. carn.</NOTE> <HI>Christian mens bo∣dies</HI> are <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 6. 15.</NOTE> <HI>Members</HI> of <HI>Christs Body,</HI> <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 6. 19.</NOTE> and <HI>Tem∣ples</HI> of <HI>Gods Spirit;</HI> and are therefore in <HI>decent</HI> and <HI>comely</HI> manner to be laid vp in their <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, Dor∣mitoria. Vide Du∣rant. de ritib. lib. 1. cap. 23.</NOTE> <HI>slee∣ping chambers</HI> or their <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Cubilia. Esai. 57. 2.</NOTE> <HI>resting places,</HI> as the Prophet <HI>Esay</HI> termeth them. A <HI>decent</HI> and <HI>comely Sepulture</HI> then is due to all <HI>Christian corps.</HI> But more then so, with some <HI>solemnitie</HI> may this <HI>office</HI> well bee performed to those, in whom the <HI>Holy Ghost</HI> manifested a more speciall <HI>residence</HI> by <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 12. 4, 6, 11.</NOTE> a more plentifull measure of spirituall <HI>endowments,</HI> and more powerfull <HI>opera∣tions</HI>
<PB REF="5"/>
flowing from the same, while they liued; and whom, hauing obtained <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">2 Cor. 12, 27. 30.</NOTE> a more eminent <HI>place</HI> in <HI>Christs body, God</HI> hath made <HI>instruments</HI> of more than ordinary <HI>good</HI> to his <HI>portion</HI> and <HI>people</HI> here. <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 25. 1.</NOTE> <HI>Samuel dyed</HI> (saith the Storie) <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Sam. 3. 20.</NOTE> a <HI>Prophet of God,</HI> <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 7. 15, 16.</NOTE> and <HI>Ruler of Gods people, and all Israel assembled to his buriall,</HI> and <HI>mourned for him.</HI></P>
<P>This being apparant, good ground there is for this <HI>solemne Assemblie,</HI> which the decease of our right worthy, and deseruedly beloued, and much respected <HI>Christian Brother,</HI> M. RICHARD STOCK, a graue and reuerend <HI>Father</HI> in this our <HI>Church,</HI> a faithfull <HI>Minister</HI> and seruant of <HI>Iesus Christ,</HI> and the vigilant <HI>Pastor</HI> of a neighbouring <HI>Congregati∣on,</HI> for the performance of this last <HI>Christian office</HI> to the <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Resi∣quiae. Hinc I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l. Scaligeri epit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ph. Scaligeri quod reli∣quum esi.</NOTE> <HI>remainders</HI> of him with vs, hath occasio∣ned at this present.</P>
<P>Concerning whom &amp; his deportments, howsoe∣uer very much might iustly be spoken, and be spo∣ken iustly by my selfe, not frō others <HI>reports,</HI> but of mine own <HI>knowledge,</HI> hauing bin <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Test<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s oculatus: qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> auritis d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>m praefer Plaut. Tru∣cul. 2. 6. quos sccun∣dae notae testes ap∣pellat. Sen. quaest. n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t. l. 4. c. 3. Nam &amp; serur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> &amp; sia∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us visa solent, quam audita nar∣rari, &amp; in tertium nas transf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sa faci∣lius coaces<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unt. Gof∣f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>id. vit Be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n. l. 1. prae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t. contra quam Apuleius: cui Flo∣rid. 1. Pluris est. au∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>us t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is uni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, quam ocula<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</NOTE> an <HI>eye witnesse</HI> of them, as hauing beene familiarly and inwardly ac∣quainted with him ever since the <HI>fourth yeere</HI> of <HI>his abode</HI> in the <HI>Schooles</HI> of the <HI>Prophets,</HI> and shortly af∣ter the time of <HI>my first accesse</HI> thither; (for there was no more distance betweene our two <HI>stand∣ings)</HI> yet neither will the <HI>streights</HI> of <HI>time</HI> permit it, nor will it be very needfull so to doe; his <HI>life,</HI> and <HI>courses,</HI> and <HI>constant labour</HI> in the <HI>worke</HI> of the <HI>Word,</HI> being so well knowne, not in this, or the neighbour <HI>places</HI> onely, but thorow-out the whole <HI>City,</HI> wherein he constantly continued the <HI>worke</HI>
<PB N="3" REF="5"/>
of his <HI>Ministery</HI> by the space of well neere thirty yeeres. I will endeuour therefore to contract (what I well may) that which I shall speake of him, and hasten to those things that more neerely concerne our selues.</P>
<P>And to beginne with the <HI>times</HI> of my <HI>first notice</HI> of him. As in his first <HI>beginnings</HI> he was of <HI>eminent note</HI> in the <HI>Colledge</HI> he liued in, both for his <HI>vnwea∣riable industry,</HI> and his <HI>singular proficiency</HI> in those <HI>studies</HI> of <HI>humanitie,</HI> that are as <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Theologiae anc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l∣lari.</NOTE> <HI>handmaids</HI> to <HI>Di∣uinity,</HI> and helpe to lay a good <HI>ground</HI> for any fu∣ture <HI>profession;</HI> So his care was so <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Pietatem huma∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ita<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i intercalarem facere.</NOTE> to <HI>entertwine pletie</HI> and <HI>humanitie</HI> the one with the other, that <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Tanquam subte∣men &amp; stamen.</NOTE> as <HI>web</HI> and <HI>woofe</HI> they ranne on euer along toge∣ther through the whole <HI>course</HI> of his <HI>studies.</HI> Nor was he carefull onely of this <HI>practise</HI> himselfe, but (according to that of the Apostle, <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Hebr. 10. 24.</NOTE> <HI>Obserue one another,</HI> <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Quod ex Prou. 27. 17. tractum vi∣d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tur.</NOTE> <HI>to whe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> on to godlinesse and well-doing;)</HI> hee was no lesse forward to <HI>incite</HI> others thereunto; and not to <HI>incite</HI> them onely thereunto, but to <HI>as∣sist</HI> them therein, and to afford what <HI>helps</HI> he could (which well also he could doe) unto any that were either <HI>desirous,</HI> yea, or <HI>willing,</HI> but to imbrace them. In which kinde I cannot without iust note of <HI>in∣gratitude</HI> but acknowledge my selfe much indeb∣ted vnto him; and haue cause (with many others, beside my selfe, much my betters) to <HI>blesse God</HI> that euer we came acquainted there with him. In a word, while he staied in the <HI>Colledge</HI> (which his desire was to haue done longer then he did, if op∣portunity had serued) <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Greg. Naz. in B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣sil.</NOTE> he gaue before hand, ere he came to it, <HI>euident signes</HI> of one likely to proue
<PB REF="6" MS="y"/>
<NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</NOTE> a <HI>skilfull Master-builder</HI> in <HI>Gods worke,</HI> and <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uk <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> 16</NOTE> a <HI>win∣ner</HI> of many <HI>soules</HI> to God.</P>
<P>Nor was he one of those <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>rathe-ripe wits,</HI> that promise <HI>faire</HI> in the <HI>blossome,</HI> but <HI>faile</HI> in the <HI>fruit;</HI> that like <HI>Comets,</HI> blaze brighter than the fixed <HI>starres</HI> for a time, but after a while <HI>vanish</HI> and come to nought, the <HI>matter</HI> of them being wholly either <HI>spent</HI> or <HI>disperst.</HI> But his <HI>proceedings</HI> in <HI>pub∣like</HI> were correspondent to his <HI>beginnings</HI> in <HI>priuate.</HI> When it pleased <HI>God</HI> <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</NOTE> to <HI>call</HI> him <HI>out</HI> and <HI>set</HI> him <HI>apart</HI> to that imploiment that he had <HI>ordained</HI> him to <HI>before,</HI> he proued <HI>a painfull, a faithfull Minister of Christ, a skilfull, a powerfull dispenser of Gods Word.</HI> If any demand <HI>proofe</HI> hereof: not to insist vpon his <HI>constant</HI> and <HI>incessant imploiments,</HI> with generall <HI>approbation</HI> and <HI>applause</HI> both of religious and <HI>iu∣dicious,</HI> continued for so many <HI>yeeres</HI> (as was be∣fore said) together, not <HI>a Sabbath</HI> intermitted, wherein (if <HI>health</HI> serued) he <HI>preached</HI> not <HI>twise,</HI> either in his owne <HI>charge</HI> (where he was frequen∣test) or elsewhere <HI>abroad;</HI> besides his <HI>catechisings</HI> of the younger sort at certaine times in the <HI>weeke dayes,</HI> and other such <HI>offices</HI> as to the <HI>pastor all functi∣on</HI> are necessarily annexed, and are <HI>priuately</HI> to bee performed; wherein also he was no lesse diligent than in the execution of his <HI>publike Ministery.</HI> Not to insist (I say) upon this; (which yet were suffici∣ent <HI>proofe</HI> of it:) As the Apostle saith to the <HI>Corin∣thians,</HI> <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Cor. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 1, 2.</NOTE> <HI>You are</HI> <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>the seale of my Apostleship, and</HI> <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 9. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</NOTE><HI>my</HI> <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></NOTE> <HI>letters testimoniall.</HI> So may I well say of this our reuerend Brother: So many <HI>Christian soules</HI> pro∣fessing themselues to haue had their <HI>first</HI> effectuall
<PB REF="6"/>
<HI>calling</HI> and <HI>conuersion</HI> from him, (in which kinde, I suppose, not many in this City may compare with him) besides the <HI>multitudes</HI> of those that acknow∣ledge themselues to haue been <HI>edified, built up,</HI> and <HI>bettred</HI> by him, are the <HI>seale</HI> of his <HI>calling,</HI> and of <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">2 Cor. 13. 3.</NOTE> <HI>Christ speaking in him,</HI> and not <HI>verball</HI> or <HI>vocall,</HI> but <HI>reall letters testimoniall</HI> of the <HI>efficacy</HI> of his <HI>ministe∣ry,</HI> through <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 3. 6, 7.</NOTE> <HI>Gods blessing</HI> thereupon.</P>
<P>An <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Iacob. de Vorag. in A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dr. s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rm 4.</NOTE> obscure <HI>Author</HI> saith, that the <HI>Apostles</HI> were like <HI>Fishermen,</HI> the succeeding <HI>Ministers</HI> like <HI>Huntsmen:</HI> <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Pis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>atores praedicatores primitiu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Matth. 4. 19. qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vno <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> multitud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> capi∣unt, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uc. 5. 6. Ioan. 21. 6. Act. 2. 41. &amp; 4. 4.</NOTE> the <HI>Apostles</HI> like <HI>fishermen</HI> that catch <HI>many</HI> at <HI>one draught;</HI> <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Praedicatores mo∣derni vt venatores, Ier 9. 16. qui cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> clamo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ibus &amp; labo∣ribus multis vix v∣nam feram capi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></NOTE> the succeeding. <HI>Ministers</HI> like <HI>Huntsmen,</HI> that with much <HI>toile</HI> and <HI>clamour,</HI> running up and downe <HI>all day,</HI> scarce take <HI>one Deere</HI> or <HI>Hare</HI> ere <HI>night.</HI> And such indeed is the hard condition of many of <HI>Gods seruants,</HI> that not∣withstanding their <HI>faithfull</HI> and <HI>painfull discharge</HI> of their duty, they are enforced to complaine with the Prophet, <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Es<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>. 53. 1.</NOTE> <HI>who beleeueth our report?</HI> and, <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Es<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i. 49 4</NOTE> <HI>I haue laboured in vaine;</HI> scarce able to produce or instance in any <HI>one,</HI> of whom they can with some good ground of assurance presume, that they haue <HI>gained</HI> him at least <HI>to God.</HI> But well might this our Brother, through <HI>Gods blessing</HI> vp∣on his <HI>labours,</HI> stand out and say, not of <HI>one</HI> or <HI>two,</HI> but of <HI>troupes,</HI> in the words of the same <HI>Pro∣phet,</HI> <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Esai. 8. 18.</NOTE> <HI>Behold I and the Children, that God hath giuen me;</HI> and with the Apostle, <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Cor. 4. 15.</NOTE> <HI>These haue I begotten to God by the Gospell of Christ Iesus.</HI></P>
<P>Yea more than that; well assured I am, that di∣uers now famous <HI>lights</HI> in <HI>Gods Church,</HI> and <HI>faith∣full Ministers</HI> of his <HI>Word,</HI> doe professe to haue ligh∣ted
<PB REF="7"/>
their <HI>candles</HI> at his <HI>lampe,</HI> yea some of them to haue receiued their <HI>first beginnings</HI> not of <HI>light</HI> on∣ly, but of spirituall <HI>life</HI> and grace, (without which all light be it neuer so great, is <HI>no light,</HI> but meere <HI>darknes)</HI> from his <HI>Ministery.</HI> It is no small <HI>honour</HI> for a man <HI>to winne,</HI> and it were but, <HI>any one soule:</HI> (<NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Iam. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>0.</NOTE> <HI>He hath saued a soule,</HI> saith S<SUP>t</SUP>. <HI>Iames;</HI> as a matter worthy the glorying in.) For <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Matth. 16. 26.</NOTE> to win <HI>a soule</HI> is to win more than the <HI>whole world</HI> againe is worth. But what an <HI>honour</HI> is it then to be, not the <HI>winner</HI> of a soule, but the winner of such as proue <HI>winners</HI> of <HI>soules,</HI> and so <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Plut. de <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>ct. cum princip.</NOTE> by <HI>winning</HI> of some <HI>one</HI> immediatly, to be a mediate meanes of <HI>winning many</HI> others by him? <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Dan 12. 3.</NOTE> <HI>They shall shine</HI> (saith he) <HI>as the Heauens,</HI> <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Iun.</NOTE> <HI>that in∣struct; and they</HI> <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> iustifi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. Ian. ad <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> cōuer∣tentes. Geneu. &amp; Reg. Bibl. Angl.</NOTE> <HI>that conuert others, as the stars.</HI> And how gloriously then (suppose we) doth this our <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>blessed</HI> Brother <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg">Matth. 13. 43.</NOTE> <HI>shine</HI> now <HI>in the Kingdome of God,</HI> that was an <HI>instructer</HI> of those that were <HI>in∣structers</HI> of others; that was a <HI>conuerter</HI> of those that were <HI>conuerters</HI> of others themselues?</P>
<P><HI>Many</HI> then (as <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 1. 16.</NOTE> the Holy Ghost saith of <HI>Iohn</HI> the <HI>Baptist)</HI> did this our Brother <HI>winne to the Lord. Many</HI> (I say) he <HI>wonne;</HI> though <HI>all</HI> he could not: that was more then <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> 18. 6. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 19.</NOTE> the <HI>Apostle</HI> himselfe was able to doe. But <HI>many</HI> yet he <HI>wonne,</HI> and his <HI>desire</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Thess. 3. 2.</NOTE> and <HI>endeuour</HI> (with <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Rom 10. 1. 1 Cor. 9. 19. 22. &amp; 10. 33.</NOTE> the same <HI>Apostle)</HI> was to <HI>win all;</HI> his <HI>own</HI> especially, of whom he vsed to protest, that <HI>it was more comfort to him to winne one of them, than to winne twenty other.</HI> But some <HI>refractary spi∣rits</HI> (as <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Psal. 58. 3, 4, 5. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. Ier. 6. 16, 17, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>8. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>9. 30.</NOTE> who almost doth not?) he met withall, that would not be <HI>reclaimed;</HI> that by their <HI>crosse carriage</HI> were as <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Quod de Cana∣naeis, Iosh. 23 13.</NOTE> <HI>thornes</HI> in his <HI>eyes,</HI> and as <HI>goad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI>
<PB N="7" REF="7"/>
in his <HI>sides,</HI> and <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Quod de Sodo∣mitis, 2 Pet. 2. 7, 8. De Hebraeis, Psal 106. 33.</NOTE> a <HI>vexation</HI> of <HI>heart</HI> to this faith∣full <HI>seruant</HI> of <HI>Christ:</HI> Whom, if any of them bee yet liuing, the <HI>Lord</HI> vouchsafe <HI>mercy,</HI> and <HI>better mindes</HI> to, and <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Act. 7. 60. 2 Tim. 4. 16.</NOTE> <HI>lay not this sinne of theirs to their charge.</HI> And if there be any of those that liued any long time under so <HI>painfull</HI> and <HI>powerfull</HI> a <HI>Mini∣stery</HI> as his was, that remaine still <HI>vnconuerted, vn∣reclaimed, vnreformed,</HI> let them feare and beware of that dreadfull <HI>censure</HI> of the Apostle, <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">2 Cor. 4. 4.</NOTE> <HI>If our Gospell be yet hid, &amp;c.</HI> And let such know, that not <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Mat. 10. 14 Luk. 9. 5. &amp; 10. 11. Act. 13. 51.</NOTE> the <HI>dust</HI> of his <HI>feet,</HI> but the <HI>sweat</HI> of his <HI>browes,</HI> and the <HI>teares</HI> of his <HI>eyes,</HI> and his <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Esai. 49. 4.</NOTE> <HI>strength wasted</HI> with them, and his <HI>spirits spent</HI> vpon them, shall one day <HI>rise vp in iudgement</HI> against <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hem to make their <HI>doome</HI> <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Matth. 10 15.</NOTE> the <HI>heauier,</HI> if by <HI>timely repentance</HI> it be not preuented.</P>
<P>But because a man may <HI>winne others,</HI> and yet <HI>lose himselfe;</HI> <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Non salutis esse dispensatorem, hoc est salutis etiam esse participem, Aug. epist. 140.</NOTE> he may <HI>saue others,</HI> and yet not <HI>saue himselfe:</HI> (<NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Animam faci∣unt, etiam qui non habant. Contra quē Sen. Non faciunt animum, quia nec habent.</NOTE> they may <HI>beget life</HI> in others, that <HI>haue none</HI> in themselues.) The <HI>Word</HI> may <HI>worke by</HI> a man, and yet not <HI>worke on</HI> him: He may be <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Per lapideum canalem transit a∣qua ad arcolas, in canali lapideo nihil generans, sed tamē hortis plurimii fru∣ctum affert. Aug. in Ioan. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r. 5.</NOTE> like a <HI>treene</HI> or a <HI>stonegutter</HI> (saith <HI>Augustine)</HI> that <HI>con∣ueigheth water into a garden,</HI> but <HI>receiueth no benefit</HI> thereby it selfe; or like <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Hermae, siue Sta∣tuae Mercuriales. Ier. 31. 21.</NOTE> the <HI>hand</HI> on the <HI>high way</HI> that <HI>pointeth others the way,</HI> which yet it <HI>neuer wal∣keth</HI> it selfe; or <NOTE N="†" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Diogenis dictum. Stob. c. 23. Quod &amp; de Peripateticis Cleanthes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>auit. Laert.</NOTE> like <HI>an Harpe</HI> (saith the Heathen man) that <HI>maketh others melody,</HI> or <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Antisthenem Diogenes <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> dixit, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Din Prus. orat. 8.</NOTE> a <HI>Trumpet,</HI> that <HI>soundeth loud,</HI> but <HI>heareth nothing</HI> it selfe; or <NOTE N="“" PLACE="marg">Aqua baptismatis baptizatos ad regnum caeleste mitt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, &amp; ipsapostea in clea∣cam descendit. Gregor. in Euang hom. 17.</NOTE> like
<PB N="8" REF="8"/>
to the <HI>baptisme water</HI> (saith <HI>Gregory)</HI> that <HI>helpes men</HI> to <HI>Heauen ward,</HI> and <HI>goeth</HI> after <HI>downe to the sincke</HI> it selfe: He may<SUP>q</SUP> <HI>preach to others,</HI> and <HI>not preach to himselfe;</HI> he may <HI>conuert others,</HI> and yet <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></NOTE> prooue <HI>a</HI> <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></NOTE> <HI>castaway himselfe.</HI> (And yet it is <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></NOTE> seldome seene, that much good is done, where a due <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Method. apud Epishan. haeres. 64.</NOTE> <HI>concent</HI> is not betweene <HI>tongue</HI> and <HI>hand,</HI> betweene <HI>lip</HI> and <HI>life.)</HI> This our Brother therefore was none of those <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Qui dicunt &amp; non faciunt. M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tih. 23. 3.</NOTE> that <HI>say and doe not:</HI> but <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Basil. in Psalm. 63. Quod iussit &amp; gassit. Bern. epist. 42. &amp; in Cant. 20. Non verbis solum praeduans, sed exemplis. Idem de temp. 51. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> de Origen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Euseb. hist. lib. 6. cap. 3. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></NOTE> as <HI>he taught, he</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Isider. Pelus. lib. 2. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>st. 251. &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>st. 271. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Itaque Menander. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Suadet loquentis vita, non oratio. Plutare. de leg. poet. &amp; praecept. pol t. Et Gregor. Nazian. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Qui docent tan∣tum <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> faciunt, ipsi praeceptis suis detrahunt pondus. Bonum quidem est recta &amp; ho∣nesta praecip<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re: sed nisi &amp; facias, mendacium est. Lactant. instit. lib. 3. cap. 16. Nisi &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> que praecipit, soluta praecepta sunt. Qui praecipiunt, nec saciunt, abest ab cis si∣des. Praeceptus <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> suis fidem de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>abit, qui quod verbis astr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re conatur, r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>psa resoluit. Ibid. lib. 4. cap. 23.</NOTE> <HI>wrought:</HI> His <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. I∣sid. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>b. 2. epist. 275.</NOTE> <HI>doctrine</HI> and his <HI>practise concurred,</HI> and went hand in hand together: His <HI>actions</HI> were, though <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Gregor. Nazian. in Easil.</NOTE> <HI>silent,</HI> yet <HI>reall</HI> and <HI>effectuall Sermons</HI> of that he <HI>preached</HI> in the <HI>Pulpit:</HI> The <HI>course</HI> of his <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Pluta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e. de Stoic. repugn. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Si∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>cat. epist. 37. Concordet sermo cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vita. S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nec. epist. 75. Ad legem suam quisque vi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> vita d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ss<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntiat. Idem epist. 20.</NOTE> <HI>life</HI> was <HI>consonant</HI> to the <HI>tenour</HI> of his <HI>teaching.</HI> And <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Isid. Pel. lib. 3. ep. 3<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</NOTE> both ioyning and conspiring in one, were a
<PB N="9" REF="8"/>
meanes to draw on many, who <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Ibid. Qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> e∣rimobten p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ret, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. 235. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Aristot. Ethic. lib. 10. cap. 1. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> by the one alone paraduenture had not easily beene wonne. In a word; for his <HI>teaching,</HI> I doubt not but that they will giue him the <HI>best testimony</HI> that <HI>heard</HI> him <HI>oftest;</HI> and for his <HI>life</HI> they that <HI>knew</HI> him <HI>best.</HI> For he was not <HI>a flash;</HI> one of those that <HI>shew all</HI> in <HI>a Ser∣mon,</HI> or that <HI>spend all</HI> vpon some <HI>one curious good worke,</HI> that they minde to make their <HI>Master-piece.</HI> But both in his <HI>life</HI> and <HI>teaching</HI> he held on such a <HI>tenor,</HI> that the more men, <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Vt enim de pictore, scalptore, fictore nisi artifex iudicare; ita nisi sapiens non potst perspicere sapientem. Plin. l. 1. epist. 10.</NOTE> <HI>wise</HI> and <HI>iudicious</HI> at least, were <HI>acquainted</HI> with either, <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Miror magis, quô magis intelligo. Idem de Euphrate ibid.</NOTE> the more they <HI>reuerenced</HI> and <HI>admired</HI> him for either.</P>
<P>There are <HI>two</HI> things (saith one) that make <HI>a compleat man.</HI> <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Isid. l. 2. ep. 131. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Ibid. ep. 175. ex. Mat. 10. 16.</NOTE> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntegritie</HI> and <HI>Iudgement:</HI> the one whereof <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> but <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Idē ibid. Nō est vera simplic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>as, nisi animiocul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, et plus sit, qui fallere nolit, et cantus sit, quo falli non possit. Bern. de praecept. &amp; dispens.</NOTE> <HI>lame</HI> and <HI>maimed</HI> without the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; and in many oft they doe not meet. But an happy <HI>coniunction</HI> of them both was there in this our Brother. For the <HI>proofe</HI> whereof I may well referre my selfe to the <HI>iudgement,</HI> both of those that so frequently desired to make vse of him, for the <HI>ouersight</HI> of their <HI>last wils,</HI> and for his <HI>assistance</HI> by way of <HI>direction,</HI> in the <HI>disposing</HI> of their <HI>estates:</HI> (and we know all, how <HI>cautious</HI> men are wont to be in that kinde:) As also of those <HI>reuerend Bre∣thren,</HI> of the <HI>Ministerie</HI> as well as other, who, ei∣ther
<PB N="10" REF="9"/>
by <HI>letters</HI> or otherwise, out of <HI>all parts</HI> of this <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Vt animi scasa ele∣qut, &amp; apte possi, &amp; li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> err a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>deat. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. 3. 2. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> 2 Tim. 2. 2. Tit 1. 6 <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eg. N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k. in Ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>il. &amp; I∣s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>. Peld. 2. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. 302. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Mat. 5. 19. Isid. ib<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. cp. 235. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Greg. Naz. ib d.</NOTE> <HI>Realme</HI> (I speake what I know) did vsually seeke to him, as to one more then ordinarily able to giue them satisfaction, for the <HI>resolution</HI> of their <HI>doubts.</HI></P>
<P>These <HI>two</HI> then (as he saith) make <HI>a compleat man</HI> indeed. But there is somewhat more required to make <HI>a compleat Minister,</HI> to wit, <SUP>i</SUP> that he <HI>can</HI> <SUP>k</SUP> <HI>speak his mind fitly,</HI> (for what vse of <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Schol. A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>siaph. Plut. Muti siquidem <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> est? Esai. 56. 10. Innocens &amp; abs{que} sermine conuersatio, quantū exemplo prodest, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Hier<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ad Ocean.</NOTE> <HI>a mute Messenger?)</HI> and that he <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Ier. 1. 17. Act. 4. 29. Ephes. 6. 19. Tit. 2. 15.</NOTE> <HI>dare doe it freely.</HI> (For <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Quis tibi <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Dei non audebit? Ambr. ep. 29. Ita{que} Greg. Naz. ad Eunō 5. Oij <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>si sid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>liter dixcrim, vobis erit <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> sum, mibip<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>o, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. Tuneo ita{que} damnum vestrum, timeo damnationem m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>am, fi tacuero. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. 99.</NOTE> of whom is <HI>courage</HI> and <HI>freedome</HI> of speech required more then of <HI>Gods Messengers?)</HI> Nor was this our worthy Brother defect<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>e in either.</P>
<P>For, as for the former, how well able he was, not to <HI>expresse</HI> only, but to <HI>v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>sse</HI> to, nor to <HI>confirme</HI> alone, but to <HI>commend</HI> also, that that he deliuered, with <HI>cleere method, sound proopes, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>je words, fit phrase, pregnant similitudes, plentifull illu∣strations, pithy perswasions, sweet insinuations, power∣full enforcements, allegations of antiquitie,</HI> and <HI>variety of good literature;</HI> that both the <HI>learnedst</HI> might <HI>re∣ceiue satisfaction</HI> from him, and the very <HI>meanest</HI> and <HI>dullest</HI> also might <HI>reape benefit</HI> by him: and so as might well <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plin. See. l. 1. cp. 20. &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> relinqu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bat. Val. Max l. 8. c 9.</NOTE> leaue an <HI>impression</HI> in the <HI>hearts</HI> and <HI>mindes</HI> of his <HI>hearers;</HI> they cannot bee ignorant,
<PB N="11" REF="9"/>
that for any space of time heard him. In a word, in this kinde he was such an one <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Quem imitari plurimi concupis∣cant, poucissimi pus∣sint. Plin. de <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>n∣ton. l. 5. cp. 10.</NOTE> as <HI>many</HI> stroue to <HI>imitate, not</HI> many of them <HI>matched.</HI></P>
<P>Againe, because it is in vaine to be <HI>able</HI> to <HI>speake</HI> to good purpose, if a man <HI>dare not</HI> vse his <HI>tongue;</HI> if, as he said sometime of the <HI>Eretrians,</HI> he be <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Themislod<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> apud Plut. in Them. &amp; in a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ophth.</NOTE> like the <HI>Sword-fish,</HI> that <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Nam &amp; gladio lingua consern so∣let. Diogenes de spur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne à pulchro pros<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cta, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rt. Et A∣pul. florid. 3. vt gla∣dius vsu splendes∣cit, situ rubiginat. ita vox in vagina silentij condita diu∣tino torpore hebtta∣tur. Sed &amp; s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o diuinus glad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us di∣citur, Esai 49. 2, Ephes. 6. 17.</NOTE> <HI>hath a sword,</HI> but hath <HI>no heart;</HI> or like some <HI>cowardly companion,</HI> that <HI>carri∣eth a weapon</HI> about him for a shew, but <HI>dare not draw it,</HI> or make <HI>vse</HI> of it, though iust occasion thereof bee offered: For his <HI>freedome</HI> of <HI>speech</HI> therefore in <HI>reprouing</HI> of <HI>sinne,</HI> and that euen to the <HI>faces</HI> of the <HI>gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>est,</HI> both in <HI>publike</HI> and <HI>priuate,</HI> when occ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>on required it, I doubt not but there are many here that are well able to testifie, and some accidents made it to bee more publikely knowne, then his desire was that it should haue beene.</P>
<P>Much hath beene spoken, and much more then I entended; and more time taken vp then I made account of. And yet much more might be added, then hath beene spoken, if <HI>time</HI> and <HI>strength</HI> would permit. Many things I haue <HI>touched,</HI> and rather <HI>pointed at</HI> then <HI>insisted on.</HI> And yet many things (I know) many among you will misse, that might as iustly haue beene spoken of, and that (it may bee) some of you will deeme should not haue beene omitted. One, his <HI>Zealous</HI> and <HI>earnest pursuit</HI> of <HI>re∣formation</HI> of some <HI>prophanations</HI> of the <HI>Sabbath;</HI> wherein he preuailed also for <HI>alteration</HI> of some things in that kinde <HI>offensiue,</HI> as well <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">For their mee∣tings on S<SUP>t</SUP>. <HI>The∣mas</HI> day.</NOTE> with the <HI>maine body</HI> of the <HI>City,</HI> as <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">For their Moon∣day feasts.</NOTE> with some particular <HI>so∣cieties:</HI>
<PB N="12" REF="10"/>
An other his <HI>discreet carriage</HI> in the <HI>catechi∣zing</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. dep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u∣p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t. Id<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>{que} in A∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>al. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Quibus gemina sunt Philostrati illa cp. 2. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> &amp;c. Itaque quod Plin. l. 6 cp 27. Facilis <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; nonfacilis electio. est enim ex <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>s eius l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rga materia.</NOTE> of the <HI>younger</HI> sort; the <HI>males</HI> apart one day, and the <HI>females</HI> another; the <HI>riper</HI> and <HI>forwarder</HI> first in the <HI>presence</HI> of the <HI>ruder</HI> and <HI>rawer,</HI> and the <HI>ruder</HI> and <HI>rawer apart</HI> by themselues after the <HI>de∣parture</HI> of the former, that they might both <HI>reape</HI> what <HI>fruit</HI> might bee by <HI>hearing</HI> them, and yet <HI>re∣ceiue no discouragement</HI> by <HI>being heard</HI> of them: A third his <HI>pious care</HI> and <HI>diligence</HI> in the <HI>religious in∣struction</HI> and <HI>education</HI> of those that were vnder his <HI>priuate charge, children</HI> and others: Some one thing, some another. And I co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>sse, with <HI>Nazi∣anzene</HI> in somewhat the like case, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>at it is herein with me, <SUP>t</SUP> as with one in a <HI>field</HI> or a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, reple∣nisht with <HI>faire flowers</HI> of <HI>all sorts,</HI> who w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> casteth his eye on one, another offereth it selfe to him, and while he is catching at that, another commeth in his way, and while that pleaseth his eye, another withdraweth it to it selfe: And <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Greg. Naz. in Patrem.</NOTE> as the <HI>rings</HI> or <HI>circles</HI> that rise on the surface of the <HI>water,</HI> when a <HI>stone</HI> is cast into a standing <HI>poole,</HI> they come so thick one vpon the neck of another, that, as if they stroue for place, they iustle out ei∣ther other: so such variety of passages presenteth it selfe to me, that while I looke after one, I lose and let slip another, and when I would fetch that
<PB N="13" REF="10"/>
vp againe, another choppeth in, as contending for roome with it: And if I should <HI>pursue</HI> and <HI>insist vpon</HI> euery <HI>particular,</HI> that either others might ex∣pect, or that might iustly challenge a <HI>place</HI> here <HI>time</HI> and <HI>speech</HI> would faile mee before <HI>matter</HI> to speake of.</P>
<P>To draw toward an end therefore together with his <HI>end;</HI> the <HI>end</HI> of his <HI>labours,</HI> but the <HI>begin∣ning</HI> of his <HI>resi,</HI> the <HI>end</HI> of his <HI>worke,</HI> but the <HI>receipt</HI> of his <HI>reward:</HI> In these and the like <HI>imploiments</HI> publike and priuate, hee <HI>spent</HI> his <HI>time,</HI> he <HI>spent</HI> his <HI>strength,</HI> <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Sicut l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>erna se consumit in seru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>∣um al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orum. Iac. de Vorag. de Ioan Bapt. 6.</NOTE> like a <HI>torch</HI> or <HI>taper, wasting</HI> and <HI>consu∣ming himself,</HI> for the <HI>behoofe</HI> and <HI>benefit</HI> of <HI>others,</HI> <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">Esai. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>9<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>g his <HI>worke with God</HI> then, and his <HI>reward</HI> for it <HI>from God</HI> now. And for these <HI>emploiments</HI> principally it was that he desired <HI>recouery</HI> of <HI>health</HI> and <HI>strength;</HI> vnto the <HI>performance</HI> whereof also (though therein iniurious to himselfe, and con∣trary to his owne desires) he oft <HI>strained</HI> himselfe, and that in the middest of his <HI>infirmitie</HI> and <HI>weak∣nesse,</HI> not to the vncertaine <HI>hazard</HI> onely, but to the euident <HI>impeachment</HI> and impairing of either. <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg">Esai. 38. 2<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> <HI>What is the Signe,</HI> said <HI>Ezekias,</HI> when he was pro∣mised recouery, <HI>that I shall goe vp to the house of the Lord?</HI> as desiring <HI>continuance</HI> of <HI>life</HI> and <HI>recouery</HI> of <HI>health</HI> for no one end more then that. And therfore also was this our Brother so desirous of <HI>recouery,</HI> that he might <HI>repaire</HI> to <HI>Gods house</HI> againe, that he might <HI>returne</HI> to <HI>Gods worke</HI> againe. To which purpose the very last <HI>Lords day</HI> before his <HI>decease,</HI> hauing after many <HI>relapses</HI> recouered a little <HI>strength,</HI> he made shift to get out to a neighbour
<PB N="14" REF="11"/>
<HI>Congregation,</HI> there to ioine with <HI>Gods people</HI> in <HI>pub∣like performance</HI> of such <HI>solemne seruice of God</HI> as that <HI>day</HI> is vsually spent and emploied in. And ha∣uing held out to the end with them in <HI>both parts</HI> of the <HI>day,</HI> he reioiced much therein, that he was <HI>able</HI> so to doe; the rather because thereby he concei∣ued some good <HI>hope,</HI> that hee should be <HI>strong</HI> e∣nough ere long, to returne to his wonted <HI>worke</HI> and <HI>employment</HI> againe. But the <HI>Lord</HI> saw it better (for <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Psal. 135. 6. Ephes. 1. 11.</NOTE> his <HI>will</HI> appeareth by his <HI>worke)</HI> to put an end to his <HI>incessant labours</HI> here, and to translate him to the place of his <HI>endlesse rest</HI> else where. The <HI>gaine</HI> is his; the <HI>losse</HI> ours, min<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wne (among others) not the least. The <HI>Lord sanctifie</HI> it vnto vs, and to those whom any way it concernet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>; and vouchsafe in mercy to <HI>repaire</HI> it, by raising vp ma∣ny alike qualified and endowed in his roome. With whom now leaue we him, and returning home to our selues, afford we a <HI>reuerent</HI> and <HI>religi∣ous care</HI> to those <HI>instructions,</HI> that for the fitting and preparing of vs vnto the <HI>way</HI> that he is gone before vs, shall out of <HI>Gods Word</HI> be deliuered vn∣to vs.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<PB REF="11"/>
<HEAD>ABRAHAMS DECEASE.</HEAD>
<EPIGRAPH>
<BIBL>GEN. 25. 8.</BIBL>
<Q>And Abraham gaue vp the ghost, and died, in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>good old age, an old man, and full of yeeres; and he was gathered to his people.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">B</SEG>Efore was a long <HI>dis∣course</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Abrahams Death.</NOTE> of <HI>Abrahams life:</HI> here is a <HI>report</HI> in few words of his <HI>death.</HI></P>
<P>Wherein (to come to <NOTE PLACE="marg">Of it foure Particulars.</NOTE> them directly without further <HI>preface,</HI> because much time is already spent) wee may consi∣der these <HI>particulars:</HI></P>
<P><NOTE N="1" PLACE="marg">Quis, <HI>Who.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Who</HI> died;</P>
<P><NOTE N="2" PLACE="marg">Quando, <HI>When.</HI></NOTE> <HI>How</HI> he died;</P>
<P><NOTE N="3" PLACE="marg">Q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>omodo, <HI>How.</HI></NOTE> <HI>When</HI> he died; and</P>
<P><NOTE N="4" PLACE="marg"><HI>Quô,</HI> Whither.</NOTE> <HI>Whither</HI> he went when he died.</P>
<P><PB REF="12"/>
<HI>First, who died;</HI> Abraham. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Particular <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. Quis Person, <HI>Who.</HI> Point 1.</NOTE></P>
<P><HI>Whence we may obserue, that</HI></P>
<P>No state or condition here freeth men from death.</P>
<P>For who might sooner or better haue expected to haue beene freed from it then <HI>Abraham? Abra∣ham</HI> (I say) <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Gen. 20. 7.</NOTE> <HI>a Prophet of God;</HI> <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Gen. 23. 6.</NOTE> <HI>a Prince of God;</HI> <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m 2. 23. 2 Chron. 20. 7. Esai. 41. 8.</NOTE> <HI>a</HI> speciall <HI>friend of God;</HI> <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Rom. 4. 16.</NOTE> <HI>the Father of the faith∣full, &amp;c.</HI> And yet of this <HI>Abraham, a Prince, a Pro∣phet, Gods friend, his fauourite, the father of the faith∣full,</HI> is it here said, that <HI>he died;</HI> and by the <HI>Iewes</HI> to our Sauiour, <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Iohn 8. 54.</NOTE> <HI>Abraham is dead.</HI> So <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Iohn 11. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, 36.</NOTE> <HI>Lazarus Christs friend;</HI> and yet, <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Iohn 11. 11.</NOTE> <HI>This our Friend</HI> (saith <HI>Christ) slee∣peth;</HI> that is (as afterward he there e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>eth himselfe) <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">fohn 11. 14.</NOTE> <HI>hee is dead.</HI> The <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Luke 12. 4. Iohn 12. 14, 15.</NOTE> <HI>Apostles</HI> likew<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>Christs friends;</HI> and yet they are <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Matth. 20. 23. Luke 21. 16. Iohn 2<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 19. Act. 12. 2, &amp; 20. 29.</NOTE> <HI>all dead:</HI> (For it was no true <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Iohn 21. 23.</NOTE> <HI>Word</HI> that <HI>went among the Disciples</HI> concerning <HI>Iohn,</HI> from the <HI>words</HI> of our <HI>Sauiour</HI> either <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Sic eum volo ma∣nere, &amp;c. Vulg. per∣peram. Quod se∣qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tur tamen Am∣bros. in Psal. 45. &amp;. 118. Aug. in Ioan. 124. &amp; de temp. 149. B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>da, Lyra, Rupert. &amp;c. Pro∣pugnat Georg. Tra∣pez. oppugnat Card. Bessarion. Graeci co∣dices resellunt.</NOTE> <HI>mistaken</HI> or <HI>misinterpreted,</HI> that <HI>that Disci∣ple should not die.) Dauid</HI> <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">1 Sam 13. 13.</NOTE> <HI>a man after Gods owne</HI> <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"> Iohn 21. 22.</NOTE> <HI>heart:</HI> and yet <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">1 King. 2. 1.</NOTE> <HI>he goeth the way of: all flesh.</HI> <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Zech. 1. 5.</NOTE> <HI>Your Fathers</HI> (saith the Prophet <HI>Zachary) where are they? or doe the Prophets liue for euer?</HI> And the <HI>Iewes</HI> an∣swer him in the negatiue, <HI>No;</HI> <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Iohn 8. 52.</NOTE> <HI>the Prophets are dead.</HI> In a word; as the Psalmist saith, that <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Psal. 49. 10.</NOTE> <HI>wise men die as well as fooles:</HI> so <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Ezek. 21. 4.</NOTE> <HI>good</HI> men <HI>die</HI> as well as <HI>bad:</HI> yea, the <HI>good</HI> goe oft before the <HI>bad.</HI> <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Esai. 57. 1.</NOTE> <HI>The righteous</HI> (saith he) <HI>are taken away from the euill to come.</HI> And of <HI>Ieroboams</HI> young <HI>Sonne</HI> it is said; <NOTE PLACE="marg">u <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Menand. Plut. ad Apollon. <HI>God taketh the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> soonest, whom hee loueth best.</HI> Mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ce t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> epitaph. sui.</NOTE>
<PB N="17" REF="12"/>
<NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">1 King. 14. 12, 13. Reason.</NOTE> <HI>He shall die, because there is some goodnesse in him.</HI></P>
<P>Now the <HI>reason</HI> why the <HI>godly die</HI> as well as the <HI>wicked,</HI> is,</P>
<P>First, if we regard <HI>naturall causes,</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Natural. 1.</NOTE></P>
<P N="1">1. Because they are made of the same <HI>mould</HI> and <HI>mettall</HI> that others are: <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">2 Cor. 4. 7.</NOTE> <HI>We haue this treasure</HI> (saith the Apostle) <HI>in</HI> <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Testacea vasa. Hier. de virgin. fictilia. Greg. Mor. l. 3. c. 6. Natural. 2.</NOTE> <HI>earthen vessels:</HI> they are but <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Esai 64. 8.</NOTE> <HI>ear∣then p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts</HI> as well as <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Ier. 18 6. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Prov. Graec.—Vul∣gus fictilis, Qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> si∣mul offendit ad for∣tunam, frangitur. Phaedr. fab. 72. Spirituall 1.</NOTE> others.</P>
<P N="2">2. Because they are subiect to the same <HI>casualties</HI> that others are. For, <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Eccles. 9. 2. Cui∣uis potest accidere, quod cuiquam po∣test. P. Syr. Spirituall 2.</NOTE> <HI>All things come alike to all: The same</HI> <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> casus.</NOTE> <HI>chance betideth the good and the bad; the cleane and the vncleane;</HI> <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Malac. 3. 18.</NOTE> <HI>the sacrificer and him that sacrificeth not;</HI> <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Zech. 5. 3, 4. Spirituall 3.</NOTE> <HI>the swearer, and him that</HI> <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Iuramentum re∣uerenti. Iun. timen∣ti. Pisc. Spirituall 4.</NOTE> <HI>feareth to sweare, that maketh conscience of an oath.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, if we regard <HI>spirituall respects.</HI></P>
<P N="1">1. The <HI>godly die</HI> also that they may <HI>rest</HI> from their <HI>labours:</HI> For, <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Apoc. 14. 13.</NOTE> <HI>They rest from their labours that are deceased in Christ.</HI></P>
<P N="2">2. They <HI>die</HI> that they may <HI>receiue</HI> their <HI>reward;</HI> to wit, <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">2 Tim. 4. 7, 8.</NOTE> <HI>the Crowne of righteousnesse;</HI> which they must <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">2 Tim. 2. 5. Iam. 1. 12.</NOTE> not expect, till they haue <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plutarc. contr. Epic.</NOTE> <HI>finished their race.</HI></P>
<P N="3">3. They <HI>die,</HI> that they may be <HI>rid</HI> of <HI>sinne:</HI> <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Rom. 8. 10.</NOTE> <HI>they die for sinne,</HI> saith the Apostle: yet not to <HI>pay</HI> for it, as the wicked doe, but to be <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Rom. 7. 24.</NOTE> <HI>freed from</HI> it: For, <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Rom. 6. 7.</NOTE> <HI>He that is dead, is freed from sinne.</HI></P>
<P N="4">4. They <HI>die,</HI> that they may be <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Antiphan. Moriar? desinam alligari posse, desinam aegrotareposse, desinam posse mori. Sen. epist. 24.</NOTE> <HI>freed</HI> from <HI>death</HI> it selfe: <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">2 Cor. 5. 4.</NOTE> <HI>that mortalitie</HI> (saith the same Apostle) <HI>may be swallowed vp of life.</HI></P>
<P N="5"><PB REF="13"/>
5. They <HI>die,</HI> that they may <SUP>t</SUP> <HI>goe to God:</HI> For, <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">2 C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r. 5. 6.</NOTE> <HI>While we bide here in the body, wee are absent from</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Spirituall. 5. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Gre Naz. in Basil, Spirituall 6.</NOTE> <HI>the Lord:</HI> and <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">2<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> 58. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g. Naz. in Patr.</NOTE> <HI>We desire therefore to remoue hence, that we may goe home to him.</HI></P>
<P N="6">6. They <HI>die,</HI> that they may <HI>be with Christ:</HI> <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">Philip. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> 23. Obiect. I.</NOTE> <HI>I desire</HI> (saith he) <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> vti Ho∣mer. Ody<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Solu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re, v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣ram soluere: vt Fab. instit. l. 1. P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rm t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a∣mus vela ventis, et oram soluentibus bene pre, emu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Et l. 4 Solu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mus oram, prosecti sumi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s. Vtà nau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gatur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s tract<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sit Uid. P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sc. in Luc. 12. 36. Hinc <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. 2 Tim. 4. 6.</NOTE> <HI>to loose,</HI> or <HI>to be loosed, and to bee with Christ.</HI></P>
<P>But against the <HI>truth</HI> of this <HI>point,</HI> may some <HI>ob∣iection</HI> be made.</P>
<P>For first, if <HI>no state</HI> or <HI>condition free</HI> men <HI>from death,</HI> how (may some say) it is said of <HI>Enoch,</HI> that <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Hebr. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 5.</NOTE> <HI>he neuer saw death;</HI> and of <HI>Elias,</HI> that <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">2 King. 2. 11.</NOTE> <HI>he was ta∣ken</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Answ.</NOTE> <HI>vp aliue into heauen?</HI></P>
<P>To this I answer, that <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>a siagu∣laria regulam non fa iunt, regulam nō i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ingunt. Priuil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣gis sing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>orum le∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>me mmunem <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>t. H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>on. in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> 1 Bed. n Act.</NOTE> <HI>singular and extraordinary priuiledges neither make a rule, nor marre a rule.</HI> It followeth not, because some one or two of this or that <HI>estate</HI> or <HI>condition</HI> haue by <HI>speciall fauour</HI> beene some time <HI>exempted</HI> from this <HI>generall sentence,</HI> that therefore the <HI>estate</HI> or <HI>condition</HI> it selfe <HI>exempteth</HI> any, or that all of the same <HI>estate</HI> are <HI>exempt</HI> and freed therefore therefrom. <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Esai. 38. 3.</NOTE> <HI>Ezekias walketh with God</HI> as well as <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Gen. 5. 24.</NOTE> <HI>Enoch,</HI> and yet <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">2 King. 20. 21.</NOTE> he <HI>died,</HI> when his <HI>lease</HI> of <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">2 King. 20. 6.</NOTE> <HI>fifteene yeeres</HI> expired. <HI>Eliseus</HI> was <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">2 King. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 7.</NOTE> <HI>a Pro∣phet of God</HI> as well as <HI>Elias;</HI> and <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">2 King. 2. 15.</NOTE> <HI>the Spirit of E∣lias</HI> (it is said) <HI>rested vpon Eliseus:</HI> and yet <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">2 King. 13. 20.</NOTE> he <HI>died,</HI> and was <HI>buried;</HI> as appeareth by the <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">2 King 13. 21.</NOTE> <HI>miracle,</HI> that <HI>God</HI> wrought by his <HI>corps</HI> sometime after his <HI>de∣cease.</HI> These were <HI>personall priuiledges:</HI> and <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Pers<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nasi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctio moritur cum I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>uris sunt pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>legia. N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n sunt amplianda priuil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gia. Ibid.</NOTE> <HI>per∣sonall prerogatiues</HI> passe no further than the <HI>persons</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">d Heb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 9 26.</NOTE>
<PB N="19" REF="13"/>
of those, whom they are conferred on.</P>
<P>But secondly, if euen <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Apo. 2. 10. 13.</NOTE> the <HI>faithfull die</HI> also, (for <NOTE PLACE="marg">Obiection 2.</NOTE> how should the <HI>faithfull</HI> looke to escape <HI>death,</HI> when <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Rom 4 16.</NOTE> <HI>the Father of the faithfull,</HI> as wee see here, himselfe <HI>dieth?)</HI> how (may some say) are the words of our Sauiour made good where he saith; <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bn 8. 51.</NOTE> <HI>If any man keepe my sayings, he shall neuer</HI> <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Mortem videre. i mori. Psal. 49. 9. &amp; 98. 48. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 11. 6. Sicut vid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re vi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>am <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i. viuere, I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bn 3. 36. Ineptum est e∣nim quod C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rysost. nom. nescio quis in Marc 10. distinguit inter mortem gu∣stare &amp; videre. Answ.</NOTE> <HI>see death;</HI> And, <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Iubn 11. 26.</NOTE> <HI>He that liueth and beleeueth in me, shall</HI> <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>neuer die?</HI></P>
<P>To this I answer, that there is as <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">1 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or. 15 45.</NOTE> <HI>a twofold life,</HI> so <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Luke 9 60.</NOTE> <HI>a twofold death:</HI> A twofold <HI>life;</HI> to wit, <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n. 2. 7.</NOTE> <HI>a na∣turall life</HI> issuing from the <HI>coniunction</HI> of the <HI>soule</HI> to the <HI>body;</HI> and <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Rom 8. 10.</NOTE> <HI>a spirituall life</HI> arising from the <HI>con∣iunction</HI> of <HI>God</HI> to the <HI>soule.</HI> And a twofold <HI>death;</HI> to wit, <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Ia<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 2 26.</NOTE> <HI>a naturall death</HI> arising from the <HI>disiuncti∣on</HI> of the <HI>soule</HI> from the <HI>body;</HI> and <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Ep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>s 2. 1, 12 &amp; 4 18.</NOTE> <HI>a spirituall death</HI> arising from the <HI>disiunction</HI> of <HI>God</HI> from the <HI>soule.</HI> For looke <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eg. N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>z. a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>g. Q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>od an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oc Deus est an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mae. Bern. s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rm. Par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 3.</NOTE> what the <HI>soule</HI> is to the <HI>body,</HI> the same is <HI>God</HI> to the <HI>soule.</HI> <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>a 73 26. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Isia. P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> 3. ep. 252. Sicut anim<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>a est co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>poris <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>ita Deus vita est an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mae. Ber. ser part 3 V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>nis an ma est, vita animae Deus est Aug. deci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it. l. 19. c. 6. &amp; de v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rb. Apost. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>8. &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Sanci. 16 A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esse debet, vt viuat corpus, anima, vt viuat anima, D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us. Ibid.</NOTE> As the <HI>soule</HI> is the <HI>life</HI> of the <HI>body,</HI> so is <HI>God</HI> the <HI>life</HI> of the <HI>soule.</HI> And <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Psal. 73 27. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Isid. ibid. Moritur corpus cum re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>edit anima: mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tur anima, si re∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>da Deus. Aug. de verb. Apost. 28. Corpus mortu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m est sine anima; anima m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> sine Deo. I∣dem de Sanct. 13. Mors co poris a spiritu deser<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; mors spirit' à Deo. Idem de C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ui. l. 19. c. 26.</NOTE> as the <HI>na∣turall death</HI> ensueth, when the <HI>soule departeth</HI> from the <HI>body;</HI> so the <HI>spirituall death</HI> followeth, when <HI>God with-draweth</HI> himselfe from the <HI>soule.</HI> The <HI>faithfull</HI> then may <HI>dye</HI> the <HI>naturall death:</HI> but they neuer <HI>dye</HI> the <HI>spirituall death.</HI> <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">Eccle 12. 7.</NOTE> <HI>Death</HI> may <HI>seuer</HI> their <HI>soules</HI> from their <HI>bodies:</HI> but <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Rom. 8. 38, 39.</NOTE> <HI>death</HI>
<PB N="20" REF="14"/>
cannot <HI>cut</HI> off either <HI>soule</HI> or <HI>body</HI> with them from <HI>Christ.</HI> The <HI>Faithfull</HI> may <HI>die;</HI> and yet our Saui∣ours words true. For <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Callimach epigr. 14. Qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> virtutem <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s interit. Plaut. Capt. 3. 5.</NOTE> they <HI>die not,</HI> euen when they <HI>die.</HI> <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Chrysost. in Phi∣lip. hom. 3. Quod a Iudaeo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>um doctori∣bus tractum docet 10. Capnio in Cabal. lib. 1. pag 755.</NOTE> <HI>Wicked</HI> men (saith <HI>Chrysostome)</HI> are <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. 1 Tim. 5. 6.</NOTE> <HI>dead</HI> euen while they <HI>liue: good</HI> and <HI>godly</HI> men <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Viuunt. omnes Deo, Luke 10. 38.</NOTE> <HI>liue</HI> euen when they be <HI>dead.</HI> The <HI>life</HI> of the one is nothing but <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Per vitam ad mortē <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> est.</NOTE> <HI>a passage to death:</HI> the <HI>death</HI> of the other is nothing but <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Per mortem ad vitam reditus est. Ambr. de bon. mort.</NOTE> <HI>an entrance into life.</HI> For it is <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Non est vita sed mors dicenda, quae viuentem à Christo separat.</NOTE> <HI>no life</HI> but <HI>death,</HI> that <HI>seuereth a man from Christ</HI> while he liueth: It is <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Non est m. sed v. dic. quae morientem Christo sociat. Idem de Abel. l. 2. c. 9.</NOTE> <HI>no death</HI> but <HI>life,</HI> that <HI>bring∣eth a man home to Christ</HI> when he <HI>dieth.</HI></P>
<P>And thus much briefly for <HI>answer</HI> to these two <HI>Obiections.</HI></P>
<P>Now for the <HI>vse</HI> of the <HI>Point.</HI></P>
<P>First, it may serue to <HI>hearten</HI> and <HI>encourage</HI> vs a∣gainst the <HI>feare</HI> and <HI>dread</HI> of <HI>death.</HI> For doe all, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Vse 1.</NOTE> euen the <HI>godly</HI> and <HI>faithfull die?</HI> Why should wee be loath to come to that, that so many <HI>Saints</HI> of <HI>God</HI> haue come to before? As <HI>Phocion</HI> said to one that was to die with him; <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>; Plut. in apophth. &amp; de laud. sui. Isid. Pel. l. 3<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. 154.</NOTE> <HI>Art thou not glad to fare as Phocion doth?</HI> So, why should any be loath to doe as <HI>Abraham</HI> doth? Or why should we be afraid to goe that <HI>way,</HI> that all the <HI>holy</HI> men of God haue gone before vs? It is true indeed, there might be some colourable cause of <HI>feare,</HI> if wee were to goe some <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Oppian. venat. lib 1. Auia—peragro loca, nullius ante Trita solo. Lucret. lib. 1. &amp; 4.</NOTE> <HI>vncouth</HI> and <HI>vntrod way,</HI> such as none euer went before vs; as <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Qui cum Horat. lib. 1. ep. 19. dicere poterat; Libera per vacuum posui vestigia princeps: Non <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> meo press<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pede.</NOTE> <HI>Abel</HI> did when he <HI>died.</HI> Or if none but the <HI>wicked</HI> had gone this way before vs,
<PB REF="14"/>
we might iustly feare, that it were indeed the <HI>high way</HI> to <HI>hell.</HI> But now when the <HI>blessed Saints</HI> and the <HI>best beloued</HI> of <HI>God</HI> haue, either <HI>all</HI> or the <HI>most</HI> of them at least, <HI>gone</HI> this way before vs; yea when he was no <HI>wicked</HI> but <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Matth. 23. 35. Iustitiae princeps: cui Christus iustitiae primatum tribuit. Aug. nom. de mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ab. SSae. l. 1. c. 3.</NOTE> a <HI>iust</HI> man, that <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Chrysost in Gen. 21.</NOTE> <HI>went</HI> first of all this <HI>way:</HI> we may well and boldly <HI>follow</HI> him and them in it without <HI>feare,</HI> as being <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Hac iter ad su∣peros, magnique ad tecta Tonantis. O∣uid. Met. l. 1 Ianua vitae, portagloriae. Bern. de temp. 48.</NOTE> the <HI>high way</HI> to <HI>Heauen</HI> too; nor neede we <HI>dread</HI> or <HI>suspect</HI> any <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Si quid incom∣modi aut motus in hoc negotio est, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>o∣rientis vitium est. Bassus apud Senec. epist. 30.</NOTE> <HI>e∣uill</HI> in that, that <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Quomodo malū, quod a Deo pro bo∣no maximo datum est? Cic. Tuscul l. 1.</NOTE> <HI>God,</HI> who <HI>loued</HI> them so deerely, would neuer haue <HI>suffered</HI> to befall them, if it should haue beene any way <HI>preiudiciall</HI> vnto them.</P>
<P>Secondly, doe euen such also <HI>die.</HI> This should teach vs <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">1 Thess. 4. 14. Non est lugendus qui antecedit, sed de∣siderandus, &amp;c. Cur enim immoderate feras abisse, quem mox consequeris? Tertul. de patient. Quod latius Cypr. de mortal. Non sunt lugendi fratres nostri accersione don inica de seculo liberati, cum sciamus eos non ami<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>i sed praemitti, recedentes praecedere; ut pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>es &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> de∣siderari eos debere, non plangi.</NOTE> not to <HI>mourne</HI> or bee grieued for the <HI>faithfull deceased,</HI> as if any <HI>euill</HI> had befallen them. For if they <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Apoc. 14. 13.</NOTE> <HI>died in the Lord,</HI> if they <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Hebr. 11. 13.</NOTE> <HI>deceased in the faith;</HI> they are but <HI>gone</HI> the same <HI>way</HI> that <HI>Gods best</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Vse 2.</NOTE> <HI>beloued</HI> went before them that liued in former times. They are rather <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">Ab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erunt non ob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>runt. Ambr. in Theodos.</NOTE> <HI>departed,</HI> than <HI>deceased;</HI> <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Praecesserunt, non decess<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>runt. Aug. de diuers. 43. Pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ecti, non omissi. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ron. ad Saluin.</NOTE> <HI>sent before</HI> vs, whither <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">2 Sam. 12. 23.</NOTE> we must follow, <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg">Dimissi, praem ssi, non amissi. Cypr. sup. Aug. cp. 6. &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>20. Sen. ep. 63. &amp; 99. &amp; ad Marc. c. 19</NOTE> <HI>leaft</HI> onely, not <HI>lost.</HI> Their <HI>death</HI> is rather <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Abitus, Luke 2. 29. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plato apolog <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Simocat. ep. 25. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Chrysost. tom. 6. ser. 43. Profectio est, quam mortem putamus. Tertul. de patient.</NOTE> a <HI>departing,</HI> or <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Exitus. Luke 9. 31. 2 Pet. 1. 15. Excessus de corpore. Tertul de resur. de mundo digredi. Ammian. l. 29. Mors migratio est. Cic. Tuscul. l. 1. migrare magis quam mori. Vell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iusl 1. non emori, sed emigrare. Hieron. in Nepot.</NOTE> a <HI>going out of this world,</HI> or <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Transitus, Iohn 13. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Chrysost. &amp; Theophil. Morstransitus est. Sen. ep. 65. Non est <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> sed transitus. Cypr. de mortal.</NOTE> <HI>a passage to heauen,</HI>
<PB N="22" REF="15"/>
or <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Reditus. Eccles. 12 7. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>triasse erit b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c. Bern de consid. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 5 <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Epcharm <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. E∣pict <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uer∣ti, vnde vene<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>s, quid graue est? S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> tranq. c. 11. Itaque Pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>us ex∣p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sans, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>s. epist. 139.</NOTE> <HI>a returne to God,</HI> then a <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Obitus. Non obi∣it. Ambr. de Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>od.</NOTE> <HI>deceasing,</HI> or <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Int<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ritus. I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>teri∣tus non est. Ambr. de bon. mort. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 8. &amp; Cic. Tus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. l. 1. Mors non interimit. Lu∣cret. l. 2. H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ud is in∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rit. Plaut. sup.</NOTE> <HI>surcea∣sing,</HI> or <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Intermissio. Mors intermi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>it vi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>am, non erip<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t. Sen. ep. 36. nee illud qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>e.</NOTE> <HI>intermission,</HI> or <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Intercisio.</NOTE> <HI>intercision,</HI> yea, or <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Diminutio.</NOTE> <HI>di∣minution,</HI> either of <HI>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fe,</HI> or of their good or happy estate. There is no cause therefore to <HI>mourne</HI> for those that <HI>die in Christ;</HI> there is cause rather to <HI>mourne</HI> for those that <HI>liue out of Christ.</HI> For the one <HI>liueth</HI> still though he <HI>die:</HI> the other is <HI>dead,</HI> though he yet <HI>liue,</HI> and shall one day <HI>die eternally,</HI> if he con∣tinue as he now is. <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Luges corpus, i quo recessit anima? luge animā, à qua recessit D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us. Aug. de Sanct. 13.</NOTE> Doest thou <HI>mourne</HI> (saith <HI>Au∣gustine)</HI> ouer the <HI>body</HI> that the <HI>soule</HI> hath <HI>leaft: mourne</HI> rather ouer the <HI>soule</HI> that <HI>God</HI> hath <HI>forsa∣ken;</HI> as <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 15 35.</NOTE> <HI>Samuel</HI> did for <HI>Saul;</HI> and as <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">2 Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 12 21.</NOTE> the <HI>Apostle</HI> saith, he should doe for such as had <HI>liued in lewd and loose courses,</HI> and <HI>not repented</HI> yet of them. <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Chryso<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>. in Philip. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>om. 3. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Isid. Pel. l. 1. cp. 334.</NOTE> Such there is cause therefore indeede to <HI>mourne</HI> for: But no cause in the world to <HI>mourne</HI> for those that are in no worse case, than <HI>Abraham</HI> and <HI>Isaak,</HI> and <HI>all</HI> the <HI>faithfull</HI> are, that liued in former times, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Vse 3.</NOTE> or than others of the same ranke shall be hereafter to the worlds ends.</P>
<P>Thirdly, are <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">2 Sam. 14 14. Rom. 4 12. Heb. 9. 26. Mors per o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nes it. Sen. epist. 95. Mors omnes aequè vocat. Ir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tis d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>js propi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>jisque mori<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dum est. Idem quaest. nat. l. 2. c. 59.</NOTE> <HI>all</HI> of <HI>all sorts subiect to death,</HI> as well <HI>good</HI> as <HI>bad,</HI> Prophets as priuate men, &amp;c? This then should admonish vs to make the best <HI>vse</HI> we can of our <HI>religious friends, neighbours, ac∣quaintance, husbands,</HI> parents, <HI>pastors</HI> especially, while they are with vs, (<NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Io<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> 12 35.</NOTE> <HI>Walke,</HI> yea and <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Iohn 9. 4.</NOTE> <HI>worke</HI> too, <HI>by the light, while you haue it with you,</HI> saith our
<PB N="23" REF="15"/>
Sauiour) since that <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Nostros omnes sic habeamus, tan∣quam nihil nobis de p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rpetuitate, imò nihil de diuturnita∣te eorum promissum sit. Tanquam v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>es∣suris, imò iam re∣cedē ibus fruamur. Tanquam extem∣plò abituros posside∣am{us}. Sen. ad Marc. cap. 10.</NOTE> we know not how soone they may be taken away from vs. It is that wherein most men are generally faulty, that as he saith of <HI>rarities</HI> and <HI>strange sights,</HI> <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Ad quae noscenda iter ingredi, trans∣mittere maria sole∣mus, ea sub oculis posita negligimus: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> quia ita compa∣ratum est, ut proxi∣morū incuriosi lon∣ginqua sectemur, sed quod omnium rerum cupido lan∣guescit, cum facilis occasio est; seu quod differimus, tanquā saepe v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>suri, quod datur videre, quo∣ties v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lis cernere. Plin. sec. l. 8. ep. 20.</NOTE> when they are <HI>neere</HI> at hand with vs, we <HI>regard not</HI> so much to see them, as we would, if they were <HI>further</HI> off, and wee should come occasionally where they were, or as <HI>strangers</HI> are wont to be, that come out of other parts, whi∣ther they are after a while to returne againe; be∣cause hauing them <HI>at hand,</HI> we thinke we may see them when wee will, whereas the <HI>strangers,</HI> vnlesse hee see them now, while hee is here, thinketh hee shall neuer haue the like <HI>opportunity</HI> againe: So we <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nter eos quos nunquam vidimus, floruisset, non solum libros eius, verum euam imagines cō∣quireremus, ciusdē nunc honor praesen∣tis &amp; gratia, quasi sati<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tate. langue∣scit. Idem lib. 1. epist. 16.</NOTE> neglect oft to make that good <HI>vse</HI> that wee might, of the <HI>meanes</HI> and the <HI>ministery</HI> that <HI>God</HI> hath setled among vs, and of our <HI>religious friends</HI> that he hath setled vs with, in <HI>hope</HI> that wee may long enioy them, and hauing them <HI>at hand</HI> with vs, we may make <HI>vse</HI> of them when wee <HI>will.</HI> By meanes whereof it commeth many times to passe, that meere <HI>strangers,</HI> that <HI>visit</HI> them but <HI>by starts,</HI> profit more by them, than the most of those doe, that <HI>constantly</HI> liue and <HI>abide</HI> with them, and that <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Sophocl. A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ac.</NOTE> when it is too late now, we come to see and consi∣der to our griefe, what <HI>opportunitie</HI> we haue ouer∣slipped of our owne good. It is with vs in these c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ses as it is with vs for our <HI>bookes.</HI> A <HI>booke</HI> of good vse <HI>borrowed,</HI> which we know not how soone the <HI>owner</HI> of it may call for, wee are carefull to make <HI>present vse</HI> of, whereas it might chance to haue <HI>li∣en long</HI> by vs, ere we looked on it, if it had beene
<PB N="24" REF="16"/>
<HI>our owne.</HI> Well it were therefore for vs, if wee could seriously consider, that <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">Rerum natura ti∣bi illum non man∣cipi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> dedit, sed com∣modavit Sen. ad Polyb. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 19. Homo commodatus vitae, non donatus est. P. Syr.</NOTE> our <HI>religious friends</HI> and <HI>Pastors,</HI> (as <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Non tam data, quàm commodata. Pri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>as. in 1 Cor. Fortuna vsu dat multa, mancipio ni∣hil. P. Syr. Nihil horum dono d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tur: collat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>ijs &amp; ad do∣minos redituris in∣strumetis scena ad∣ornatur: mutuò ac∣cipimus in incertum diem; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sus fructus tantiem noster est. Sen. ad Marc. c. 10. Exposition 2. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Eurip. Phoeniss.</NOTE> <HI>all</HI> other <HI>things of this life,</HI> yea, and <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">Vita data est vtenda; data est sine foenore nobis Mutua, nec c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rto persolüenda die. Pedo ad Liu. vsuram vitae natura dedit, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nquam pecuniae, nulla pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣stituta die. Cic. Tusc. l. 1. Vita{que} mancipio nulli datur, omnibus vsu. Lucret. l. 3. Vsu &amp; fructu no∣bis est vita, non mancipio tradita. Arnob. l. 2.</NOTE> <HI>life</HI> too it selfe) are not so much <HI>giuen</HI> vs of <HI>God,</HI> as <HI>lent</HI> vs to <HI>vse,</HI> and that <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg">Cuius tempus ille ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>er muneris tui temperat. Sen. ad Marc. c. 10.</NOTE> for no longer than he shall see good; and therefore labour to make the <HI>best vse</HI> we can of them, while we haue them; as we would doe of some <HI>toole</HI> or <HI>vtensile,</HI> that be∣ing <HI>lent</HI> vs, we know not how long wee shall haue the <HI>vse</HI> of. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Particular 2. Quomodò. Manner How. Exposition 1.</NOTE></P>
<P>And thus much for the first <HI>particular,</HI> the <HI>Person</HI> that died, <HI>Abraham.</HI></P>
<P>The second followeth, and that is the <HI>manner how</HI> he died, noted in that it is said, <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> expirauit.</NOTE> <HI>He breathed out,</HI> or, <HI>He gaue vp the Ghost.</HI></P>
<P>That which some expound of <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Aequo ani<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o. Caluin.</NOTE> <HI>a willing end,</HI> of a willingnesse to depart: as it is said of our Saui∣our, that <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Iohn 19. 30.</NOTE> <HI>hee bowed his head downe,</HI> when <HI>all was finished,</HI> and <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>gaue vp his Spirit.</HI> And true it is, that as the Heathen man saith, <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Sapientis est <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>xire, non &amp; e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ci. Sen. ep. 70.</NOTE> it is <HI>the part of a wise man,</HI> rather <HI>willingly to goe out,</HI> than to bee <HI>thrust out against his will,</HI> so it is the <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Luke 2. 29. Act. 7. 59. 2 Sam. 15. 26. 1 Pet. 4. 19.</NOTE> vsuall practise of <HI>Gods children</HI> willingly to <HI>resigne and giue their soules vp to God,</HI> when he pleaseth to <HI>call</HI> for them.</P>
<P>Others vnderstand it <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">De l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ui &amp; leni morte, D. Kimchi &amp; Aben-ezra.</NOTE> of <HI>a quiet end,</HI> or an <HI>easie end,</HI> of dying without difficultie: as it is said of
<PB REF="16"/>
<HI>Iacob,</HI> that <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Gen. 49. 33.</NOTE> when he had done <HI>blessing his sonnes, he plucked vp his feet, and so gaue vp the ghost.</HI> And it is true also that <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Ti. Exception. maeo. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣pbocl. Hinc Themist. Exposition 3. de anima. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Point 2. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Senectu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> leniter emittit, non repente auulsum vi∣tae, sed minutatim subduct<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m. Sen. ep. 30. Animam seni∣lem mollis exoluit Sopor. Sen. O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dip. 4. 2. Proofe 1.</NOTE> <HI>old</HI> men vsually die with much <HI>ease;</HI> <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Adolescent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣ri sic mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> vi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, vt cum aquae mul∣titudine vis flam∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> opprimitur: se∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es autem, sicun cum sua sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nte nulla adhibita vi consumptus ignis extinguitur. Et quasi poma ex arboribus, si crudasunt, vi auelluntur, si matura &amp; cocta, decidunt; sic vitam adolescentibus vis aufert, senibu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> matu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>itas. Cic. de se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ect.</NOTE> like <HI>an apple</HI> that being come to full <HI>maturi∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y,</HI> doeth without <HI>force</HI> or <HI>stresse</HI> vsed to it, <HI>drop downe</HI> of it selfe; or like <HI>a lampe,</HI> that <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Ignis qui alimentis deficitur, sua sponte subfidit. Sen. epist. 30.</NOTE> of it selfe <HI>goeth out,</HI> when the <HI>matter</HI> that fed it <HI>faileth.</HI></P>
<P>But because I finde the word vsed <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Gen. 6. 17. &amp; 7. 21. Numb. 17. 12, 13. &amp; 20. 3.</NOTE> <HI>generally</HI> and <HI>indefinitely,</HI> as well of <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Iob 3. 11. &amp; 10. 18.</NOTE> <HI>young</HI> as of <HI>old,</HI> as well of such as die <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Iosh. 22. 20. Psal. 88. 15. Z<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch. 13. 8.</NOTE> <HI>strong</HI> and <HI>violent,</HI> as that die <HI>vo∣luntary</HI> or <HI>easie deaths:</HI> I take it rather, that there is in this <HI>phrase</HI> of speech an intimation of <HI>mans frail∣tie,</HI> and of the <HI>frailtie</HI> of <HI>mans life.</HI> <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Expiraui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> <HI>Hee puffed out,</HI> or, <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Spiritum efflauit.</NOTE> <HI>Hee breathed out;</HI> that is, <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Spiritus defe∣cit.</NOTE> <HI>His breath failed,</HI> or, <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Spiritus ab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>js.</NOTE> <HI>His breath went away,</HI> and <HI>he died.</HI></P>
<P>So that the <HI>Point</HI> that hence I would obserue then is this, that</P>
<P><HI>The life of Man is but a breath, but a blast:</HI></P>
<P>And so consequently the <HI>frailty</HI> and the <HI>vanitie</HI> of <HI>mans life.</HI> That which may the better appeare vn∣to vs, if we shall consider,</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 What it is <HI>compared</HI> vnto; and</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 What it may be <HI>taken away</HI> with.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>First (I say) what it is <HI>compared</HI> vnto. <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Pindar. Pyth. 8. Plutarc. ad Apollon.</NOTE> <HI>What is man?</HI> saith the Heathen man. Why? hee is euen <HI>the dreame of a shadow.</HI> What hath lesse <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>truth</HI> in it than a dreame? What lesse <HI>substance</HI> than a <HI>sha∣dow?</HI>
<PB N="26" REF="17"/>
What either vanisheth away more sudden∣ly, than the one; or is dispelled sooner than the other? Nor came another of them much short of him, who compared <HI>mans state,</HI> as the former did his <HI>life,</HI> not to <HI>the dreame of a shadow,</HI> but to <HI>the</HI> <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Aes∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hyl Stob. cap. 96.</NOTE> <HI>shadow of a smoake.</HI> They seemed (it seemeth) to them to haue said little or nothing to speake of, that compared it, either to <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Greg. Naz. ad Iu∣lian.</NOTE> <HI>a dreame,</HI> or to <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Vt calidus fu∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> abignibus Va∣nescit per spatium brcue sord dus: Sic bic quo <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>egimur, spiritus <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uit. Sen. Troad. 2.</NOTE> <HI>a smoake,</HI> or to <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. So∣ph<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>l. Aiac.</NOTE> <HI>a shadow</HI> alone, when yet to minish the weight and adde to the vanitie of it, ioyning two of them together, they make it, not <HI>a smoake</HI> onely, but <HI>the shadow of a smoake,</HI> that is farre lesse; nor <HI>a dreame</HI> barely, but <NOTE N="†" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plut. ad Apollon.</NOTE> <HI>the dreame,</HI> not of some <HI>substance,</HI> which yet were a thing of nothing, but of <HI>a shadow.</HI> And, <HI>What is man</HI> saith one of the ancient Fathers. Why? he is <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Greg. Naz. ex Gen. 2. 7.</NOTE> <HI>Soule</HI> and <HI>Soile;</HI> or <HI>Breath</HI> and <HI>Body:</HI> <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Psal. 78. 39. Esai. 2. 22. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> &amp; venti flatum &amp; spiritū hominis designat. Eccles. 1. 6. &amp; 12. 7. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> item vtrum{que} denotat. Ioan. 3. 8. &amp; 4. 24. sed &amp; ani∣ma &amp; animus quasi <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> dictus, Cassiod Canin. alij. &amp; pro vento etiam vsurpatur. Seru. in Aen. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>1.</NOTE> <HI>apuffe of wind</HI> the one, and <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Gen. 3. 19. &amp; 18. 21. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, dust and ashes.</NOTE> <HI>a pile of dust</HI> the other: no soliditie in either, if you consider them apart; and most vnlikely to impart any such thing either to other, if you con∣sider them in themselues. I might adde what they say, that compare men to the <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Sirac. 14. 18. &amp; Aug. in Psal. 101. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Musaeus. Clem. strom. l. 6. Et ab ills Homer. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> &amp;c. Et <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, &amp;c. Quod laudat Zeno. Laert. citant Clem. strom. l. 6. Plut. ad Apoll<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n. &amp; Lucian Episcop. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plut. de tard. vindict. &amp; de vit. Epicur. Sed &amp; M mueru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ss, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. &amp;c. Stob. c. 96. Et Ari∣stoph. auib. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Clem. airom. l. 5.</NOTE> <HI>leaues</HI> of <HI>trees</HI> that
<PB N="27" REF="17"/>
soone <HI>shed;</HI> to <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. &amp;c. Luc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. Episc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p. H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mo bulla. Varr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. rust. l. 1. c. 1.</NOTE> <HI>bubbles</HI> on the <HI>water,</HI> that <HI>fall</HI> as fast as they rise; to <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Epi∣charm. Clem. strom. lib. 5.</NOTE> <HI>bladders</HI> puffed vp of <HI>wind,</HI> that may be let out with the <HI>pricke</HI> of a <HI>pinne,</HI> and the like.</P>
<P>But because these may peraduenture seeme vn∣to some to haue spoken somewhat <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plutar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. sup.</NOTE> <HI>hyperbolically</HI> or excessiuely in the <HI>point:</HI> let vs heare the <HI>Spirit of God,</HI> that speaketh no otherwise of things than as they are indeede, speake. If we demand then of the <HI>mouth</HI> of <HI>God</HI> himselfe, <HI>What Man is;</HI> he ma∣keth vs answer euen in effect as they did: to wit, that <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Adam Abei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> com∣par est. Ps. 144. 3, 4.</NOTE> <HI>Adam is as Abel,</HI> or <HI>Abels Mate:</HI> (for to the <HI>Names</HI> of those two <HI>Patriarches</HI> there is an allusion in the <HI>Originall:)</HI> that is, <HI>Man</HI> (as it is translated) <HI>is as</HI> <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Geneu. &amp; Reg. Bibl.</NOTE> <HI>vanitie,</HI> or, <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Vet. Bibl. Angl.</NOTE> <HI>a thing of nought: his daies passe away like</HI> <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Iob 8. 9. Psalm. 102. 11. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Aristoph. a∣uib. Clem. strom. l. 5.</NOTE> <HI>a shadow.</HI> He is <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Psal. 73. 20. &amp; 90. 5. Iob 20. 8.</NOTE> <HI>as a dreame that vani∣sheth when one awaketh: as</HI> <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Iob 7. 7.</NOTE> <HI>a wind,</HI> <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Psal. 78. 39. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Soph<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cl. Aia<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> <HI>that goeth away and commeth not againe.</HI> <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Esai. 2. 22. Quod de senibus Sen. ep. 30. Anim<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> senilu cum in primis fit labijs, haud magna vià corpore distrahitur.</NOTE> <HI>His breath is in his nostrils;</HI> ready euer and anon to puffe out: And <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">Psal. 146. 4.</NOTE> <HI>when that breath</HI> of his is <HI>once gone,</HI> <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Eccles. 12. 7.</NOTE> <HI>hee returneth instantly to his dust;</HI> to that <HI>dust,</HI> <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">Gen. 2. 7. &amp; 3. 19.</NOTE> of which he was formed at first. His <HI>life is</HI> <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Iob 7. 9. Vt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ubes, grauidas quas m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>do vidimus, Arctoi Borgae dissipat impetus. So<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Tr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ad. 2.</NOTE> <HI>as a cloud,</HI> that is soone disperst with the <HI>wind;</HI> or <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Iam. 4. 14.</NOTE> <HI>as a vapour, that appea∣reth for a while, and then vanisheth away.</HI> In a word: <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Omnis Adam totus Abel. Psal. 39. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, 12.</NOTE> <HI>All Man is all Abel;</HI> and that euen then, when he is at the very <HI>best;</HI> that is, <HI>euery Man,</HI> <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> fundatus, constitutus.</NOTE> be he neuer so well <HI>vnderlaid,</HI> neuer so surely and soundly <HI>set∣led,</HI> he <HI>is nothing but vanitie,</HI> that hath <HI>no soliditie</HI> at
<PB N="28" REF="18"/>
all in it; or (as he saith elsewhere) but <SUP>e</SUP> <HI>alye,</HI> that hath <HI>no truth</HI> at all in it; or <SUP>f</SUP> <HI>as nothing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> yea, <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Psal. 62. 9.</NOTE> <HI>ligh∣ter</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Psal. 62. 9. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Esai 40. 17. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Sophocl. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Iambl. hortat. c 8. Proofe 2.</NOTE> (if ought may so be) <HI>than vanitie</HI> it selfe; and (if more than so may be yet) euen <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Esai. 40. 17.</NOTE> <HI>lesse than nothing.</HI> Which <HI>speeches</HI> (I suppose) come not an ace short of those other.</P>
<P>Againe, the <HI>frailtie</HI> and <HI>vanitie</HI> of <HI>mans life</HI> may appeare, if we shall consider what it may be <HI>taken away</HI> with. And it is strange to think, <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Ti <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Greg. Naz. de baptism.</NOTE> how <HI>small</HI> a matter may put an end to <HI>mans life.</HI> When a <HI>great man</HI> sometime threatned <HI>a Philosopher</HI> with <HI>death,</HI> <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Dio∣genes Perdiccae. La∣ert. Et Theodorus Lysimacho; Enim∣uerò magnifi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a res tibi contigit, quia <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>antharidis vim as∣secutus es. Cic. Tusc. l. 1. &amp; Val. Max. l. 6. c. 2.</NOTE> <HI>What is that more</HI> (quoth he) <HI>than à Spanish Flie may doe?</HI> and he might well haue added, <HI>not to me onely, but to thy selfe.</HI> Yea, to passe by that of <HI>Cleopatra,</HI> who when to preuent publike disgrace, she had made her selfe away with the helpe of <HI>an Aspe,</HI> yet had nothing to be seene on her, saue <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plut. Anton.</NOTE> <HI>two small pricks,</HI> that could hardly be seene, made with the <HI>wormes tooth</HI> on the one of her <HI>armes;</HI> which yet were enough (it seemeth) to make an <HI>end</HI> of her, and <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Tu qui te Deum credis, successu ali∣quo elatus, quantu∣lo serpētis dente pe∣rire potes? Plin. l. 7. c. 7.</NOTE> might as well haue done of any other. To let that passe, I say, not a <HI>Spanish,</HI> but <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Conrad. Visperg. Na<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cler. ex Ioan. Cremon. &amp; Io. Bal. in Adrian. Pp 4 qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Papatum <HI>Nicholas Breake-speare</HI> dicebatur.</NOTE> <HI>an ordi∣nary Flie</HI> or <HI>a grat,</HI> flying casually into his mouth, is said to haue <HI>stifled</HI> that proud <HI>Pope,</HI> that made the <HI>highest State</HI> then in the <HI>Christian world stoope</HI> euen to the <HI>holding</HI> of his <HI>stirrop.</HI> And indeed, <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Nihil tam exiguum est, quod non in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>iem generis humani satis val at. Sen. nat. quaest. l. 6. c. 2.</NOTE> what is there so <HI>small,</HI> that may not bee <HI>a mans bane?</HI> The <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uli nos, &amp; ne to∣ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s quidem dolor, sed aliqua <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> latere eius s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>issura conficit. Ibid.</NOTE> <HI>paring</HI> of a <HI>toe,</HI> the <HI>cutting</HI> of <HI>a corne,</HI> the <HI>scratch</HI> of <HI>a naile,</HI> the <HI>pricke</HI> of <HI>a pin,</HI> haue beene
<PB N="29" REF="18"/>
sometime, and <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Quicquid enim fieri potuit vnquā, &amp; potest. Idem.</NOTE> may againe be, the meanes of <HI>a mans end.</HI> A <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Tarquinius Pris∣cus piscis spina in∣ter coenandum sus∣focatus es<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Guide Bitur.</NOTE> <HI>fish-bone,</HI> a <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Anacr contem V∣uae passae succo exi∣les virium reliquias fouentē vnicus gra∣nipertinacior in a∣ridis faucibus hu∣mor absumpsit. Val. Max. l. 9 c. 12 &amp; Plin. l 7. c. 7. Quod de Sophocle etiam Sotades. Stob. c. 96.</NOTE> <HI>grape-kernel,</HI> some <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Fabius Senator poto in lactis haustis vno pilo strangula∣tus est. Plin. ibid.</NOTE> <HI>one haire,</HI> a <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">Est quos potio strangulauerit malè lapsa per fouces: stil∣licidio perire potes. Sen. q. nat. l. 6. c. 2. Vse 1.</NOTE> <HI>drop</HI> of <HI>water,</HI> <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Saliua crassior suff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cat. Ibid.</NOTE> his owne <HI>spittle,</HI> let down vnwarily, may <HI>choake</HI> him. <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Abortus causa sit odor a lucer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rum extinctu. Plin. l. 7. c. 7. Nunquid vt homo concidatres magni molimenti est? odor illisoporque, &amp;c. mortisera sunt. Sen. ad Marc. c. 11. Animal aquarum nouitatibus, flatu{que} non familiaris aquae, &amp; tenuissimis causis atque off<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nsionibus morbidum, putre, cassum. Ibid. Iouinianus Imp. foetore prunarum &amp; nidore parietum recens cal∣ceillitorum extinctus est. Hieron. in Nepot. Ammian. l. 25. &amp; Aur. Victor. Fato gemino &amp; Q. Ca∣tulus ob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>jt. Vell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>us l. 2.</NOTE> <HI>bad</HI> or <HI>vnwonted aire,</HI> an <HI>euill smell,</HI> a little <HI>smoake</HI> may soone <HI>stifle</HI> him. <HI>Man</HI> is <HI>as the grasse,</HI> or <HI>as a flower</HI> (saith the <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Psal. 40. 6, 7.</NOTE> <HI>Pro∣phet</HI> and the <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Psal 103. 15, 16.</NOTE> <HI>Psalmist)</HI> which <HI>if the wind blow but on it, it is by and by gone:</HI> and his <HI>life</HI> is as <HI>a candle,</HI> or <HI>a taper, a weake light,</HI> that euery <HI>light,</HI> not <HI>gust,</HI> but <HI>puffe</HI> of <HI>winde</HI> is ready to <HI>blow out.</HI> Yea not some <HI>malignant blast,</HI> or some <HI>euill breath</HI> onely, but euen the <HI>want</HI> of <HI>breath;</HI> nor the <HI>aire,</HI> if it bee <HI>infected,</HI> onely, but the very <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Suppresso tantum spiritu esse desierunt Licinius Macer, Zeno Cittieus, Metrocles Cynicus, Com<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>latro. Val. Max. l. 9 c. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>2 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>l. Suid. Hinc &amp; Plin. l 31. c. 1. Nubes obtentu vital<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m spiritum strangulant.</NOTE> <HI>want</HI> of it to <HI>breathe</HI> with, will soone make man cease to be, and put a <HI>period</HI> to his <HI>life.</HI> <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Psal. 104 29.</NOTE> <HI>If thou withdrawest</HI> (saith hee) <HI>from them their breath, they die, and returne againe to their dust.</HI></P>
<P>And what may this <HI>frailtie</HI> and <HI>vanitie</HI> of <HI>mans life</HI> then teach vs?</P>
<P>Surely; <HI>first,</HI> not to <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Ier. 17. 5.</NOTE> make <HI>flesh</HI> our <HI>arme;</HI> not to <HI>relie</HI> vpon so <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Vti Laco de Athenis, quas <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Pindarus dixit, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>feeble,</HI> so <HI>fraile,</HI> so <HI>fickle</HI> a <HI>stay,</HI> as the <HI>life</HI> euen of the <HI>greatest,</HI> or what euer he be, <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Esai. 2. 22.</NOTE> <HI>Cease from man</HI> (saith the <HI>Prophet) whose breath is in his nostrils: for what excellency is there in him?</HI> And, <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Psal. 146. 3.</NOTE> <HI>Trust not in Princes</HI> (saith the <HI>Psalmist) nor in any
<PB N="30" REF="19"/>
Sonne of Man: for there is</HI> <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Psal. 60. 11.</NOTE> <HI>no</HI> certainty of <HI>helpe by them.</HI> For their <HI>life</HI> is but <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Psal. 78. 39.</NOTE> <HI>ablast,</HI> and <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Psal. 146. 4.</NOTE> <HI>whe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> their breath goeth they die, and returne to their dust,</HI> euen <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Psal. 82. 7. Ve∣rum nos homunculi Sali<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> animae, qui cum extempso ami∣simus, Aequo men∣dicus a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>{que} ille opu∣lentissimus Censetur censu ad Acheron∣tem mortuus. Plaut. Trinum. 2. 4. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Lu∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ian. Impares nas∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>r, pares mori∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur: aequat omn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> cinis. Sen. epist. 91. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>rs exaequat <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ia. Idem ad Marc. c. 10. Quis discer∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at species mortuo∣rum? redoperiter∣ram, &amp; diuites, si potes, depre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>e. Ambr. de Nabuth. c. 1. Hinc illud an∣tholog. lib. 3. cap. 13. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> as others doe; <HI>and then all their proiects pe∣rish with them.</HI> Men thinke themselues <HI>safe</HI> com∣monly, if they can get into <HI>fauour</HI> with some <HI>great man,</HI> or if they can by any meanes procure but the <HI>protection</HI> of such an one. But, not to presse that which some yet well obserue, that these proue oft but <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Sunt infirma (in∣fida) quaedamrefu∣gia; ad quae cum quis fugerit, magis infirmatur, quam confirmatur. Aug. in Psal. 45.</NOTE> <HI>vntoward shelters,</HI> but <HI>v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>safe sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>egards;</HI> like the <HI>tree</HI> to the <HI>passenger,</HI> that flieth to it for <HI>succour</HI> in a <HI>storme,</HI> <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Multi c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣dentibus eis ad qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s confugerant, &amp; ipsi quae siti sunt, quos nemoquaereret, si non ad eos confugis∣sint. Aug. ibid. Quid ego de Regum familiaribus dicam, quos quidem regia saepe incolumis, saepe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ē lapsa prosternit. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>eth. consol. l. 3. c. 5.</NOTE> that either <HI>braineth</HI> or <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eth</HI> him with the <HI>fall</HI> of a <HI>bough,</HI> who might haue beene <HI>safe</HI> enough, had he not <HI>shrouded</HI> himselfe vnder it: Yea that <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Esai. 30. 3. &amp; 31. 1, 3. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plut. de amic.</NOTE> many are <HI>ruined</HI> together with them by their <HI>fall,</HI> as the <HI>vnder-woods</HI> by the <HI>Oke</HI> or the <HI>Ce∣dar</HI> when it is <HI>felled,</HI> who neuer <HI>got</HI> by them while they stood. What <HI>surety</HI> of helpe or <HI>safety</HI> canst thou haue from those, who haue no <HI>suretie,</HI> <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Ad omnia patienda pares sumus: nemo alter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>agilior est: nemo in crastinū sui certior. Sen. ep. 91. Vt caetorū hominū, ita principū illorum omniū, qui Dij sibi videntur, aeuum omne &amp; br<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue &amp; fragile est. P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>n. Paneg. Psal. 82. 6, 7.</NOTE> no more than thou hast, of themselues? Or what <HI>sure∣tie</HI> or certainty can they haue of themselues, whose <HI>life</HI> dependeth vpon so <HI>fickle</HI> a <HI>stay,</HI> as is a <HI>puffe</HI> of <HI>wind,</HI> or a <HI>blast</HI> of <HI>breath</HI> onely? <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Psal. 62. 8. &amp; 84. 12, 13. &amp; 146. 5. Ier. 17. 7, 8.</NOTE> Make <HI>God thy stay,</HI> therefore, who is <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Esai. 26. 4. &amp; 54. 10.</NOTE> <HI>a rocke of eternitie,</HI> or an <HI>euerlasting rocke:</HI> not <HI>man,</HI> who is <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">Quid est <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>? Vas fragile, quas∣sum, ia<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>atu, non tempestate magna, vt d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssipetur, est opus: vbicun{que} arietauerit, soluitur. S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m. ad Mar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 11.</NOTE> so <HI>fraile,</HI>
<PB N="31" REF="19"/>
so <HI>feeble a fabricke,</HI> as being <HI>supported</HI> and <HI>held toge∣ther</HI> but with <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Salillum animae. Plau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. sup.</NOTE> a <HI>little breath,</HI> may with <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">Anxiae, solicitae{que} tutelae, precarij spi∣ritus, &amp; malè in∣horentis, quem pa∣uor repentinus, aut ex improuiso sonus auribus grauis ex-Vse 2. cutit. Sen. ibid. Cu∣ius caduca possessio tam leu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>afflatu c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣cussadilabitur. Val. Max. l. 9. c. 12.</NOTE> as small a matter againe bee <HI>throwne downe</HI> and <HI>dissolued.</HI> And <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg">Esa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 8. 12, 13, 14. &amp; 51. 6, 7, 8, 12, 14. Matth. 10. 28. &amp; 16. 25.</NOTE> take heed how for the procuring of the <HI>fa∣uour</HI> of the one, thou either <HI>watue</HI> the <HI>fauour,</HI> or <HI>in∣curre</HI> the <HI>dispeasure</HI> of the other.</P>
<P>Secondly, the consideration hereof should ad∣monish vs with <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Iob 14. 14.</NOTE> <HI>Iob,</HI> to liue in <HI>continuall expectati∣on</HI> of our <HI>end,</HI> in <HI>continuall preparation</HI> for the time of our <HI>decease;</HI> since that <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Gen. 27. 2. Eccles 9. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> we <HI>know not how soone</HI> or <HI>how sodainly,</HI> we may be <HI>smitten;</HI> and wee <HI>know</HI> withall, <HI>how small a matter</HI> is enough to <HI>make an end</HI> of vs. It was no euill <HI>counsell</HI> therefore, that besides <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Sic quotidiè vi∣namus, quasi die il∣la iudi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>andi simus. H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eron. in Matth. 23. Dies omnis pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>im<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> habeatur. Martin. Du<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iens. de morib. Respect 1.</NOTE> <HI>Christian Diuines,</HI> euen some <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Omnem creded<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ē tibi diluxisse supre∣mum. Horat. l. 1. ep. 4. Sic ordinand{us} est dies omnis, tanquā cogat agmen, &amp; cō∣summet atque ex∣pleat vitam. Sen ep. 11. Qui omnes dies tanquam vltimum ordinat, nec optat crastinum, nec time<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Id<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> de breu. vit. c. 7. Sic diem omnem aspi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, tanquam esse vel vltimus possit. Paratus exire sum. Idem <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> 61.</NOTE> <HI>Heathen</HI> haue giuen, that a man should doe well to</P>
<P><HI>Make euery day his dying day.</HI></P>
<P>Which yet is not so simply to be vnderstood, that a man should <HI>euery day</HI> doe the same <HI>duties,</HI> or be imployed in the same <HI>workes,</HI> that hee either would or should, if he knew it to be the <HI>last day</HI> of his <HI>life:</HI> But that in some other speciall <HI>respects</HI> he should make <HI>each day</HI> to be so (to wit, as his <HI>dying day)</HI> to him.</P>
<P N="1">1. In the <HI>dispeeding</HI> of his <HI>repentance</HI> and <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Sirac. 5. 8.</NOTE> <HI>not de∣laying</HI> it <HI>a day</HI> longer. Be as carefull to <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. 4. 27.</NOTE> <HI>breake off thy sins</HI> this day and <HI>euery day,</HI> as if it were to be thy <HI>dying day.</HI> Make <HI>euery day</HI> thy <HI>dying day,</HI> by <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Rom. 6. 2, 11.</NOTE> <HI>dying vnto sinne euery day.</HI> It is an <HI>Heathen</HI> mans <HI>counsell;</HI> and it is <HI>good</HI> and wholsome <HI>counsell;</HI> <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Hoc citra diem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mortis praesta: morian<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>r ante te vitia tu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Sen. ep. 27.</NOTE> <HI>Let thy
<PB N="32" REF="20"/>
sinnes die in thee before thou diest.</HI> Let them <HI>dye be∣fore thee;</HI> for <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Ier. 6. 29. 30. Vl∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>sne est criminum modus? &amp; non pri∣us est vt de vitâ hamines quam de iniquitate d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>scedāt? Quis enim non cū suis iniquitatibus moritur? &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ipsis ad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>odum a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>{que} in ipsis sceterib{us} <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>∣pelitur? Sal. de prou. l. 5. c. 8. Non cessant vitia ciuiū vs{que} ad excidia ciuitatum. Pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> est interire qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gi: Prius ipsos, quam in ipsis vitia, non esse. ib. l. 6. c. 12.</NOTE> if they <HI>stay till death</HI> with thee, if <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Iohn 8. 22, 24.</NOTE> <HI>thou diest before they die,</HI> thou art sure to <HI>die eter∣nally.</HI> And how knowest thou but that <HI>thou</HI> maist <HI>die</HI> before <HI>they die,</HI> if <HI>they die</HI> not in thee <HI>this day;</HI> when <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, Eurip. Al∣cest. Qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s enimest tam adolesc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ns, cui fit exploratum se ad vesperū esse victu∣rum? Cic. de sen. Quis s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it an adijci∣ant hodiern<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tem∣pora vitae Crastina Dijsuperi? Horat. carm. 4. 7. Nemo tā Respect 2. diuos habuit fauen∣tes, Crastinum vt possit sibi polliceri. Sen. Thyest. 3. Nihil dehodierna die promittitur, ni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>il de hac <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Sen. ad Mar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. c. 10.</NOTE> thou hast <HI>no certainty</HI> of <HI>thy liues continuance</HI> till the <HI>next day?</HI> And it is the <HI>aduice</HI> of a <HI>Iewish Rabbine,</HI> and might well haue come from any <HI>Chri∣stian;</HI> <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> die ante mortem agas poenitentiam. R. Eleazar. Drus. apopht<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. l. 1.</NOTE> <HI>Repent thee a day before thou diest.</HI> Not meaning thereby, that a man should <HI>deferre</HI> and put off his <HI>repentance,</HI> till he <HI>lay,</HI> as hee thought, now a <HI>dying,</HI> or not like to <HI>liue</HI> aboue <HI>a day</HI> longer: But that <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Hodiè resipiscendum, ne forte cras moriamur. Ibid.</NOTE> he should <HI>this</HI> present <HI>day repent,</HI> and <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Quomodo enim de die in diem dis∣ferendo peccas, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>um extremum diem tuum nescids? Aug. ep. 145.</NOTE> not <HI>put</HI> it <HI>off</HI> till the <HI>next day;</HI> because before the <HI>next day,</HI> for ought he knoweth, he may <HI>die;</HI> <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Prou. 27. 1. Iam. 4. 13. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>; Anacrcon. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Pindar. Isth 8.—aetas quid <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rastinavoluat scire nefas homini. Stat Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>b. l. 3. Ney<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is quid serus vesper vehat. Varro. Liu. l. 45. Gell. l. 1. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 22.</NOTE> hee <HI>knoweth not what</HI> or <HI>where</HI> he shall be <HI>to morrow.</HI> As <HI>Solomon</HI> therefore aduiseth him, that hath <HI>in∣tangled</HI> himselfe by <HI>suretiship,</HI> so doe thou much more; (for the matter more concerneth thee) <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Prou. 6. 4, 5.</NOTE> <HI>Giue no sleepe to thine eyes, nor flumber to thine eye∣lids,</HI> before thou hast <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">2 Tim. 2. 25, 26.</NOTE> by <HI>sincere</HI> and <HI>serious repen∣tance wound</HI> thy selfe and thy <HI>soule</HI> againe out of those <HI>snares of Satan,</HI> <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Prou. 5. 22. &amp; 29. 6.</NOTE> which by the practise of <HI>sinne</HI> thou hast <HI>entangled thy selfe</HI> in.</P>
<P N="2">2 In the <HI>shunning</HI> and <HI>auoiding</HI> of all <HI>euill.</HI> Be as carefull to <HI>shunne sinne e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ery day,</HI> as thou wouldest
<PB N="33" REF="20"/>
be, if it were to be thy <HI>dying day,</HI> <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Vt quotidiè pri∣diè caueat, ne faci∣at, quod se pigent postridiè. Plaut. Sti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h. 1. 2.</NOTE> <HI>Doe not that</HI> (saith he) <HI>to day, that thou maist repent thee of to morrow.</HI> Yea, <HI>doe not that,</HI> (say I) <HI>to day, that it may be too late to repent of tomorrow.</HI> There is hardly any man to be found so <HI>desperate,</HI> if he beleeue at least that he hath a <HI>soule</HI> to <HI>saue,</HI> that <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Zaleuc. legum prooem. Nu∣per me amicicuius∣dam langu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r admo∣nuit, optimos esse nos, dum infirmi sumus. Quem enim infirmum auaritia aut libido solicitat? non am<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ribus ser∣uit, non adpetit ho∣nores, opes negligit, nemini inuidet, ne∣minem desp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cit; a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ne sermoni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us qui∣dem malignis aut attendit aut alitur. Innoxiam in posterum, si contingat euadere, vitam destin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t. Plin. Sec. l. 7. ep. 25. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Tyr. Max. dissert. 41.</NOTE> would wilfully abandon himselfe to any <HI>euill</HI> act, if he thought but that he should or might <HI>die</HI> instantly vpon the <HI>deed</HI> done. When thou shalt therefore be incited to the doing of ought, that thy conscience enformeth thee to bee <HI>euill,</HI> doe but thinke thus seriously with thy selfe; <HI>Would I doe this, if I were to die to day, or if I were to die as soone as it is done?</HI> And yet how knowest thou, but that thou maist <HI>die</HI> in the <HI>doing</HI> of it, but that this <HI>puffe</HI> of thy <HI>life</HI> may <HI>puffe out,</HI> ere it be <HI>done?</HI> Thou maist be taken with <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Dan. 5 6.</NOTE> <HI>Bal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a∣sar,</HI> <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">2 Sam. 13. 26, 29.</NOTE> <HI>Ammo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> and <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">1 King. 16. 9, 10.</NOTE> <HI>Ela,</HI> besides <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Ita Archias cae∣tèr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tyranui Thebanioppressi sunt, cum is vino plenus, literas coniurationis indices puluino sub∣i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cisset. Plut. de Socrat. gen. &amp; sympos. l. 1. c. 3. &amp; in Pelopid.</NOTE> others, amids thy <HI>cups,</HI> or vpon thine <HI>ale-bench:</HI> Thou maist with <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Numb. 25. 8.</NOTE> <HI>Zimri</HI> and <HI>Cozbi</HI> (and the like hath befallen o∣thers too) be smitten <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Ita periere Spousippus Philos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>phus. Tertul. apolog. Rodaldus Long<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bard. Rex. Paul. Diac. lib. 4. cap. 17. Ioan. 12. Pp. Luitprand. lib. 6. cap. 11.</NOTE> in thine <HI>vncleane bed,</HI> yea in the <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Quosdam concubitus extinxit. Sen. epist. 66. Inter vsum Veneris absumptisunt. Corn. Gallus Praetorius, &amp; T. Haterius Eques Rom. Plin. lib. 7. cap. 53. &amp; Val. Max. lib. 9. cap. 12. Bellrandus Ferrerius Hispan. Pontan. de obed. lib. 1. cap. 10. Et Gia∣chet. Salucianus vna cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>scortosu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Fulg. lib 9. cap. 12. sed &amp; <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Philetaer. in Venatr. Athen. lib. 13.</NOTE> <HI>act</HI> of thine <HI>vncleannesse:</HI> Thou maist with <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Num. 16. 32, 35.</NOTE> <HI>Core</HI> and his complices, be swept away, in thy <HI>re∣bellious courses</HI> against <HI>Minister</HI> or <HI>Magistrate;</HI> or amids thy <HI>friuolous suites,</HI> and <HI>malicious pursuits</HI> of
<PB N="34" REF="21"/>
thy brethren. Thy <HI>lie,</HI> or thy vaine <HI>oath</HI> may bee thy <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Dan. 434.</NOTE> <HI>last word;</HI> thy <HI>drunken health</HI> thy <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Accadion <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Sed &amp; Erasi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>us sari fato <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. Ath<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd. 10. A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gi∣nascil. vi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, vt F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stus, q ā <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Erasm. Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. 4. ce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>. 8. adag. 2. L. Valla m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, dumm <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sip <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>em haurit; Ap. S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>∣seius, c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> hausisset. P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. 7. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 53.</NOTE> <HI>last draught;</HI> thy <HI>fraud,</HI> or thine <HI>oppression</HI> thy <HI>last deed.</HI> In <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Dum resp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>s, quod aiunt, v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sa▪ Respect 3. musque nos, iam murtal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> aderit. Sen. de <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ra. lib. 3. cap. 43.</NOTE> the <HI>twinckling</HI> of an <HI>eye,</HI> in the <HI>turning</HI> of an <HI>hand,</HI> while thou art but <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Psal. 66. 18.</NOTE> <HI>looking after</HI> some <HI>sinne,</HI> as <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Gen. 19. 26. Ius. 17. 32.</NOTE> <HI>Lots wife looking to Sodome</HI> ward, (<NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Dr. Wilkinson Sermon.</NOTE> <HI>She turned her but, and she was turned)</HI> maist thou sodainly be <HI>snatched</HI> away, with thy <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Eurip. O∣rest. Impura m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, pura manu. Apul. ap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>log.</NOTE> <HI>minde defiled,</HI> though thy <HI>hand</HI> yet <HI>vnsoiled.</HI> And certainly <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Nulla res magis proderit, quam c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gitatio mort<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>litatis. S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n. de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ra. l. 3. c. 42. Nih<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>què profuerit ad temperantiam <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erum, quam srequens cog<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o breais au<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, &amp; huius inc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rti. Idem ep. 114.</NOTE> no meanes would be more effectuall to keepe vs continually within compasse, than the serious consideration of the <HI>frailtie</HI> and the <HI>vncertaintie</HI> of our <HI>life,</HI> how <HI>soone</HI> and how <HI>sodainly</HI> it may <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Excisa sestine auolat. Psal. 90. 12. Anima a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orpore segre∣gata, vento si niles auolamus. Hieron. ep. de Psal 90.</NOTE> <HI>flit</HI> away from vs.</P>
<P N="3">3. In <HI>embracing</HI> of all <HI>good occasions.</HI> Be <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Lucian. in Nigrin. Sed propera, nec te venturas differ in horas. Qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> non est ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iè, cras minus ap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us erit. Ouid. remed. l. 1.</NOTE> as carefull <HI>euery day</HI> to <HI>entertaine</HI> any <HI>occasion</HI> of <HI>wel-doing,</HI> as thou wouldest be, if it were to bee thy <HI>dying day.</HI> <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Gal. 6. 10.</NOTE> <HI>Let vs doe good</HI> (saith the Apostle) <HI>while wee haue</HI> <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Tempus vt noris, iubet. Sed <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> iste tempestiuum tempus est. Auson. ex P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>i sent.</NOTE> <HI>time, and opportunitie</HI> so to doe: considering that if we neglect it now, when it is offered, wee know not whether it will euer be offered vs againe. <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Prou. 3. 28. Praeceptum de <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>icordiae operibus non differendis. Aug. de verb. Dom. 59. Cum potes henefa∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>re, noli differre. Polyc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rpi nom, ep. ad Philip.</NOTE> <HI>Say not</HI> (saith Solomon) <HI>to thy neighbour, Goe and come againe to morrow, if thou hast that by thee wherewith</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Psal. 50 22.</NOTE> <HI>thou maist helpe him.</HI> And, <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Eccles. 9. 10. Quicquid agis, agas pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> virlbus <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. des<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</NOTE> <HI>whatsoeuer thou doest</HI> (saith he) <HI>doe it,</HI> as <HI>with all diligence; for there is no
<PB N="35" REF="21"/>
worke, nor wisdome in the graue that thou goest to:</HI> so <HI>without delay;</HI> because <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Eccles. 11. 2.</NOTE> <HI>thou knowest not what euill may come,</HI> that may cut off all <HI>future opportunitie</HI> of <HI>wel-doing,</HI> either by taking <HI>thee</HI> from the <HI>meanes,</HI> or the <HI>meanes</HI> from <HI>thee.</HI> And <HI>as</HI> <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Eccles. 11. 4. In∣cipe: virendi rect<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> qui prorogat ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, Rusticus expectat dum defluat anmis: at ille Labitur, &amp; labetur in omne vo∣lubilis aeuum. Ho∣rat. l. 1. cp. 2.</NOTE> <HI>he that obserueth the wind shall neuer sow;</HI> so <HI>hee that regardeth the clouds shall neuer reape.</HI> But especially <SUP>d</SUP> neglect not the <HI>meanes</HI> of that <HI>maine worke,</HI> (<NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Psal. 95. 7, 8. Hebr. 3. 7, 8, 11. &amp; 4. 7.</NOTE> <HI>To day,</HI> saith he, <HI>if you heare his voice, harden not your hearts,</HI> but <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Psal. 81. 8, 13.</NOTE> <HI>hearken:</HI> And, <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">2 Cor. 6. 1, 2.</NOTE> <HI>Now while the acceptable time is, while it is the day of saluation, we beseech you, receiue not the grace of God</HI> offered you <HI>in vaine.)</HI> of <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">1 Tim 6. 19.</NOTE> <HI>laying a good foundation for the obtaining of life eternall;</HI> and the <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. 1 Tim. 6. 12.</NOTE> <HI>laying hold</HI> of all opportunities that may tend thereunto. For this, if it bee <HI>not</HI> first <HI>done, dismall</HI> and <HI>desperate</HI> will thine estate be, if <HI>death so∣dainly</HI> surprise thee. Whereas if it be <HI>once well</HI> and substantially <HI>done,</HI> <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Rom. 8. 38, 39.</NOTE> <HI>death</HI> shall neuer be able to <HI>raze</HI> or to <HI>rip vp</HI> thy <HI>worke,</HI> come it neuer so <HI>soone</HI> after, or so <HI>suddenly</HI> vpon thee. It is with vs in this case, as it is for our <HI>wills.</HI> A man that hath not his <HI>Will made</HI> before hand, if hee bee sodainly taken with <HI>dead Palsie</HI> or <HI>lethargie,</HI> is <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Quia in eo qui testatur, cius tem∣poris quo testamen∣tum facit, integri∣tas mentis exigitur. Digest. l. 28. tit. 1. l. 2 Et Cod. Iust. l. 6. tit. 22. l. 9. Sancimus tale testamen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ū ho∣minis, qui in ipso actu testandi ad∣uersa vasetudine t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>us est, pro nihi∣lo esse.</NOTE> thereby vtterly <HI>disabled</HI> to doe ought therein, or to settle his estate. Whereas if a man haue before time <HI>made</HI> and fini∣shed his <HI>will,</HI> though he haue no <HI>time</HI> or <HI>abilitie,</HI> being so taken, now to <HI>recognize</HI> it, yet <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Surdus &amp; mu∣tus testamentū fa∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere non potest: sed si qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s post testamē∣tum factum, vale∣tudine aut quolibet alio casu talu esse ceperit, ratum nihilominus permanet testamentum Digest. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, 28. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t. 1. l 6. Q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>od ment<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sana factum est, stat testamentum, etiam si furor mox sec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tus fu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rit. Cod. Iust. l. 6. tit. 22. l. 9.</NOTE> his <HI>will</HI> standeth <HI>firme</HI> and good still for all that, and shall as well take <HI>effect</HI> as if he had seriously now againe <HI>considered</HI> of it, and <HI>signed</HI> and <HI>sealed</HI> it the second
<PB N="36" REF="22"/>
time. In like manner, those that neglect now the <HI>meanes</HI> of their <HI>saluation,</HI> in hope of hauing them, and making vse of them time enough hereafter, if either <HI>death,</HI> or some <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rhus <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>a∣bilis, qui <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of∣ficiat, mentem con∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>utiat. Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. cp. 58.</NOTE> such <HI>disease, soduinly smite</HI> them, as is wont to <HI>depriue</HI> of, or <HI>disturbe</HI> the vse of <HI>vnderstanding</HI> and <HI>reason,</HI> they are thereby vt∣terly <HI>disabled</HI> to do ought therein. Whereas those that are now carefull to make a good <HI>vse</HI> of them, and neglect not the <HI>grace</HI> and <HI>mercy</HI> of <HI>God</HI> therein now vouchsafed them, hauing <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Rom. 5. 1, 2.</NOTE> <HI>reconciled</HI> them∣selues <HI>to God</HI> once, and made their <HI>peace with him;</HI> though <HI>death</HI> should take them so <HI>suddenly,</HI> that they haue not <HI>time</HI> so much as to thinke on it, yet their <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Esai, 54. 10.</NOTE> <HI>peace with God</HI> shall stand <HI>firme</HI> and <HI>sure;</HI> nor shall the <HI>want</HI> of <HI>opportunitie</HI> or <HI>abilitie</HI> to doe ought then, any whit <HI>impeach</HI> or <HI>impaire</HI> their euer∣lasting <HI>wel-doing.</HI></P>
<P N="4">4. In the <HI>manner</HI> of <HI>doing</HI> all that we doe. Bee carefull to <HI>doe,</HI> whatsoeuer it is that thou doest, <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Respect 4. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Zaleuc. leg. prooem. St<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>b. tom. 2. c. 42. Ita Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ep 61. Hoc <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nimo tibi hanc epi∣stolam scribe, tan∣quam cum maximè scribentem m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs e∣u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>atura fit.</NOTE> as <HI>sincerely,</HI> as <HI>vprightly,</HI> as thou wouldest doe it, if thou wert to doe it, when thou art <HI>a dying;</HI> or as thou wouldest doe it, if thou thoughtest thou shouldest <HI>die</HI> as soone as it were <HI>done,</HI> that <HI>present∣ly after</HI> the <HI>doing</HI> of it, thou shouldest <HI>depart this world,</HI> and goe to giue an <HI>account</HI> of the <HI>doing</HI> of it to God. So <HI>doe,</HI> I say: for <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Dic tibi dormitu∣r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; Potes non ex∣pergis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i. Dic exper∣recto; Potes non dormire amplius. D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c exeunti; Petes non reuerti. Dic re∣uertenti; Pates non exire. Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. cp. 49.</NOTE> so (for ought thou knowest) thou maist <HI>doe.</HI> And therefore, not on∣ly, when thou <HI>hearest</HI> now, so <HI>heare,</HI> as if this were the <HI>last Sermon</HI> thou should <HI>heare,</HI> as with <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Act. 20. 9.</NOTE> <HI>Eutychus</HI> it had like to haue beene; so <HI>pray,</HI> when thou <HI>prai∣est,</HI> as if that might proue the <HI>last prayer</HI> thou shouldest make; (for the <HI>manner</HI> of preferring and
<PB N="37" REF="22"/>
<HI>commencing</HI> of it, I meane, though not for the <HI>matter</HI> of the <HI>suit commenced)</HI> but so <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">1 Cor. 10 31.</NOTE> <HI>eat</HI> and <HI>drinke</HI> too, as if that might bee thy <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Ob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>jt repente <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. Manlius Torqua∣tus, cum in coena plac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntam appete∣ret; P. Quint us Scapula, cum apud Aqu lium Gallum coenare<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>s Sauf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ius cum domi s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ae pranderet P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>n. lib. 7. cap. 53. Ier<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m. 41. 1, 2.</NOTE> last <HI>meale;</HI> so <HI>buy</HI> and <HI>sell</HI> too, as if euery <HI>bargaine</HI> thou makest, might be the last that euer thou shouldest make: yea, so follow not thy <HI>serious affaires</HI> onely, but thy <HI>lawfull disports</HI> and <HI>delights</HI> too, as one that maist <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Nullis evidenti∣bus causis ob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, dū calceantur matuti∣no, duo Caesares; &amp;c. omnes vsque ndeò sani at{que} tem∣pestiui, vt de pro∣gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>endo cogita∣rent. Pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. ibid. Particular 3. Quando. Time When. Branch 1. Exposition 1.</NOTE> <HI>in an instant</HI> as well be taken away, (thy <HI>life</HI> lying in thy <HI>breath,</HI> and thy <HI>breath</HI> being but a <HI>blast)</HI> as others not a few before thee haue beene, either <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">Cn. Bcbius, cum à puero hor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e quae∣sisset; C. Serui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>us, cum in soro ad tabernam flaret in fratrem innixus; Bcbi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s Iud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>x dum vnd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>monium differri iub<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, M. Terentius dum in soro tabellas s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rihi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; C. Iulius Medicus, dum inungit, specillum per oculos <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rabens. Pliu. ibid.</NOTE> in the one, or <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg">Risu exanimatus est Philemon Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ius. Val. Max. lib. 9. cap 12. Terpander ficu per lusum in esingesta. Trypho. antholog. lib. 1. cap. 37. Drus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us Claud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>j Imp. sil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us pyro. Sueton. Claud. cap. 27. M<SUP>r</SUP>. H. Mor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s <HI>in the Tennis-court with the racket in his hand.</HI></NOTE> in the other.</P>
<P>And thus much also for the <HI>second Particular</HI> here considerable, the <HI>manner how</HI> hee died, and the <HI>frailtie</HI> of <HI>mans life</HI> in the <HI>phrase</HI> here im∣plyed.</P>
<P>The <HI>third Particular</HI> followeth; and that is the <HI>time when</HI> he dyed.</P>
<P><HI>He dyed,</HI> (saith my <HI>Text).</HI></P>
<P N="1">1. <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">In bona canitie. Gen. 15. 15.</NOTE> <HI>in a good old age,</HI> or <HI>with a good hoary head;</HI> for that the <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> quod à <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> distinguitur Iob 15. 10. 1 Sam 12. 2.</NOTE> <HI>Word</HI> properly and primarily sound∣eth; and it is accounted <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> plus est quam <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> &amp; <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> quam <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. D. Ki<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>hi. Vide D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us. obs<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> l. 6. c. 13. Sencctus l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssae aetatis, non f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>actae nomen est. Sen. ep. 26.</NOTE> a further degree than the former.</P>
<P><HI>Good</HI> (I say) not (as some) <HI>morally;</HI> as <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Dis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>dens in grat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in Gen. 15. quo etiam abire vid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tur C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rysest. b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m. 37. &amp; Philo, Sed &amp; Hugo. Boni in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p ent <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> bonis o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eribus; &amp; implentur m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ritis operum suorum.</NOTE> <HI>well spent, well employed,</HI> replenisht with <HI>deeds</HI> and <HI>em∣ploiments
<PB N="38" REF="23"/>
spiritually good:</HI> (albeit, no doubt, <HI>Abra∣hams old age</HI> also, as well as his <HI>younger time</HI> so was:)</P>
<P>But <HI>good</HI> rather <HI>naturally;</HI> that is,</P>
<P>Either <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Multa, prouecta. Pet. Martyr. Lon∣g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, diuturna. O <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. Iun. Exposition 2.</NOTE> <HI>great:</HI> for in <HI>length</HI> and <HI>greatnesse</HI> in part consisteth the <HI>goodnesse</HI> of <HI>age;</HI> and <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Sicus dicimus, Bona pars homini<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>magnap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s Mart. Quinqua sci e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Zeno, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Laert. Sed &amp; Demosthe∣nes. Stob tom. 2. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 4.</NOTE> <HI>goodnesse</HI> in that sense goeth sometime for <HI>greatnesse:</HI></P>
<P>Or <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Placida, tranquil∣la. Par. Prospera ac <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. Mus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ul.</NOTE> <HI>quiet, happy,</HI> and <HI>prosperous;</HI> as it is said elsewhere, <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Gen. 15. 15.</NOTE> in <HI>peace</HI> and <HI>prosperitie:</HI></P>
<P>Or <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Integra. Oleast. commoda. Pisc, fa∣cili, bona valetudi∣ne. Mart. Branch <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Exposition 1. Exposition 2.</NOTE> <HI>haile</HI> and <HI>healthy,</HI> as wee say; <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Morlis, dolorib{us}, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uris vacua. Par. Point. Generall 3.</NOTE> <HI>free</HI> for the most part from such <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Vide Obseru. 3 rat. 2. &amp; Spec. 2. rat. 1.</NOTE> <HI>annoiances</HI> and troublesome infirmities, as that <HI>age</HI> is wont to be infested with∣all: though not, it may be, so <HI>fresh</HI> and <HI>vigorous</HI> as <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Deut. 34 7.</NOTE> <HI>Moses,</HI> or so able and actiue as <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sh. 14 11. Ta∣lis &amp; Cyrus. Xe∣noph. P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d. l. 8. &amp; Metellus. Cic. de sen.</NOTE> <HI>Caleb,</HI> are neere their ends said to haue beene:</P>
<P>Or <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Ol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ast. Par. &amp;c.</NOTE> all these; for the word may well include them all.</P>
<P N="2">2. <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Senex, satur.</NOTE> <HI>Old and full;</HI> not <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Plenus plenitudine eius de quo Ioan. 1. 16. Procop. vide Hugon. sup.</NOTE> of <HI>grace</HI> and <HI>goodnesse,</HI> as some: (that is most true indeed also of <HI>Abra∣ham,</HI> but seemeth not here intended:)</P>
<P>But of <HI>daies,</HI> or of <HI>yeeres;</HI> as it is expressed <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Gen. 35. 29. 1 Chron. 23. 1.</NOTE> else∣where: hauing <HI>liued</HI> euen as long as <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Vt non appeteret vitae pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rogationem. Oleast. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>lu. M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rt. &amp;c.</NOTE> himselfe <HI>desired,</HI> or <HI>so long</HI> (as we say) <HI>as heart could wish.</HI></P>
<P>Whence the <HI>Point,</HI> that in the <HI>Generall</HI> wee may obserue, is this, that euen</P>
<P><HI>The longest liuers die at last.</HI> <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Psal. 90. 10.</NOTE> <HI>The daies of mans life are seuenty yeeres;</HI> saith the Psalmist. But <HI>A∣braham</HI> had liued a whole <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">175. Vers. 7.</NOTE> <HI>hundred</HI> to that, and yet at length, you see, <HI>he dieth.</HI> Yea that is the <HI>con∣clusion</HI>
<PB N="39" REF="23"/>
still (<NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Enoch. Gen. 5. 24.</NOTE> <HI>one</HI> onely excepted) with <HI>all</HI> those <HI>Ancients</HI> that liued so long before the <HI>floud,</HI> (not <HI>three</HI> or <HI>foure</HI> times, as they say of <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Ho∣mer. Odyss. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>Nestor</HI> and some <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Vide pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n. h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st. n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t. lib. 7. c. 48. &amp; L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cian. de M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rob.</NOTE> other, but <HI>nine</HI> or <HI>ten</HI> times as long as the <HI>longest</HI> ordinary <HI>liuers</HI> liue now adaies) <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Et mortuus est. Gen. 5. 5, 8, 27, &amp;c. Reason 1.</NOTE> <HI>And hee died.</HI></P>
<P>Nor is it any maruell, that they so doe.</P>
<P>For first, we are of <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Vitrei sumus. August. de verb. Dom. 1.</NOTE> a <HI>glassie matter,</HI> of a very <HI>brittle mettall:</HI> <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Qui si∣mul ossndit ad for∣tunam frangitur. Pbaedr. fab. 72. vbi∣cun pue a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ietaueri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, solu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tur. Sen. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. ad Marc. cap. 11.</NOTE> ready with euery <HI>light dash</HI> to <HI>cracke</HI> asunder, to <HI>fl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</HI> in <HI>pieces.</HI> And * <HI>wee walke a∣mids many casualties;</HI> ready euer anon to seize on vs; and any <HI>one</HI> alone enough to make an <HI>end</HI> of vs. And <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Hydria tandé ad font<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m srangitur. Eccles. 12. 6.</NOTE> <HI>the pot</HI> (as the Prouerbe is) <HI>goeth so of<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to the well, that at length it commeth home broken;</HI> or rather, that it neuer commeth home againe. <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Mors obique <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e exp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, si sapis, eam vbique expectabis. August. nom. despir. &amp; anim. c. 51. Bern. m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t. c 3. &amp; O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. mor. c. 7. Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ibus in i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>is, ad descent bus in msidij<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> est. Bern. de <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 14.</NOTE> <HI>Death lieth euery where,</HI> in euery corner, <HI>in waite</HI> for vs; euen <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>a qui∣b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s hic <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> administratur, a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ua, terra, spiri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, omnia tam causae viuend<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sunt qua<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or∣tis. Sen. ep. 117. Non <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ibus nobis, non hamor, non vigilia, non somnus sine mensura quadam <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> sunt. Idem quaest, nat. l. 6. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 2. O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or, sapor, humor, c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bus, &amp; sine quibus viu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re non po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, sunt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>∣mini morlifera. Idem ad Marc. c. 11.</NOTE> in those things themselues that are <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"> Inter v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rios ca∣sus am<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>{us}. Au∣g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st. ibid. &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 28. Sub <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> casibus quotid <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ambulamus.</NOTE> the <HI>meanes</HI> to <HI>maintaine life.</HI> Not <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Greg. Naz. d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> bapt.</NOTE> a <HI>crum</HI> of that <HI>bread</HI> we <HI>eat,</HI> nor <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Potio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is stilla ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e lapsa strangulat. Sen. quaest nat. l. 6 c. 2.</NOTE> a <HI>drop</HI> of that we <HI>drinke,</HI> but, if it goe but <HI>an haires bredth</HI> awry, it may be our <HI>bane.</HI> There is not <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Passus inter me &amp; m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtem. 1 Sam. 20. 3.</NOTE> a bare <HI>step,</HI> or a <HI>pace</HI> only <HI>betweene death and vs,</HI> as <HI>David</HI> speaketh; or an <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Anath<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> morteremotus Quatuo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, &amp;c. Iuuen 14 <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Arat. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o Prus. orat. 74. E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> prope tam letum quam prape cernu aquam. O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d. Pont. l. 2. Inter v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>ae mortisquevias N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> gracililim<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e ducto. Sen. Med 2.</NOTE> <HI>hand∣bredth,</HI> some few <HI>inches,</HI> as it is said of those that be
<PB N="40" REF="24"/>
at <HI>sea:</HI> but euen scarce a <HI>nailes bredth,</HI> yea or an <HI>haires bredth</HI> betweene <HI>vs</HI> and <HI>it,</HI> if not <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ras si in n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ui∣gat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>one tantum ex∣istimas minimum esse quo mortevita diducit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r. In <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mni loco aeque tenue in∣teruallum est. Non v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>que se mors tam prope ost<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ndit, nbique tam prope est. S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nec. epist. 50. A morte semp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a∣tundem absumus. Quod enim tempus morti exemp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> est? a quo prope non est, parata omnibus lo∣cis, omnibus mo∣m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntis? Id<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m epist. 30.</NOTE> <HI>at all times,</HI> yet at <HI>many times</HI> more at least, than wee are vsually aware of. And it is no maruell there∣fore if <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Quem saepe ca∣sus transit, aliqua∣do inuenit. P. Syr. Circuit fatum; &amp; si quem diu praete∣rijt, rep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rit. Sen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c. quaest. nat. l. 6. c. 1. Mors propter in∣certos casus quoti∣diè imminet; prop∣ter breuitatem vi∣tae nunquam pot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st longè abesse. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>c. Tuscul. l. 1. Nemo p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>riculo proximus, iutus diu. Cyp. nom. de singul. cler.</NOTE> <HI>death meet with</HI> vs, or <HI>light vpon</HI> vs at length: it is maruell rather that it <HI>misseth of</HI> vs so long.</P>
<P>Besides that, <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Stygias vltrò quaerimus vndas. Senec. Herc. fur. 1. Plures dentibus suis, quam alient ensibus perierunt. Vide Iun. P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ov. 23. 2.</NOTE> wee our selues also helpe oft to <HI>hasten</HI> our <HI>owne end,</HI> while wee <HI>betray</HI> our selues to him, who <HI>lieth</HI> thus <HI>in wait</HI> for vs, by wilfull <HI>distemper,</HI> by <HI>disorder,</HI> by <HI>misdiet.</HI> As not <HI>one apple</HI> therefore of an <HI>hundred hangeth on</HI> the <HI>tree</HI> to full <HI>maturitie,</HI> or so long, till it <HI>drop downe</HI> with <HI>ripenesse</HI> alone and its owne <HI>weight,</HI> but either it is <HI>pluckt off</HI> with the <HI>hand,</HI> or <HI>blowne downe</HI> with the <HI>wind,</HI> or <HI>preuented</HI> of its <HI>maturitie</HI> by some one meanes or other: not one <HI>glasse,</HI> or earthen <HI>pot</HI> of an <HI>hundred,</HI> that lasteth so long as it might, but by some <HI>mischance</HI> or other it commeth to its <HI>bane:</HI> So <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Pauci ad Senectutem p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s∣unt. Cic. de sen. Quota pars moritur tempore fati? Senec. Her<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t. 2. 2.</NOTE> not <HI>one man</HI> among an <HI>hundred</HI> (what and I should say a <HI>thousand?)</HI> that <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">Implet dies suos. Esni. 65. 20.</NOTE> <HI>fulfilleth</HI> his <HI>naturall course,</HI> that <HI>liueth</HI> so long as in <HI>course</HI> of <HI>na∣ture</HI> he well might, but hath his <HI>life shortned,</HI> and his <HI>end bastned</HI> <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Multas natura mortis vias aperuit: multis itineribus fata decurrunt. Uno modo nascimur: multis morimur. Cestius. Senec. controu. 16. Vnum natura nobis introi∣tum ad vitam dedit, exitus mul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>os. Senec. epist. 70. Mille modis leti miseros mors vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> fa∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>igat. Sil. Theb. lib. 9.</NOTE> by <HI>sword,</HI> by <HI>stresse,</HI> by <HI>sorrow,</HI> by <HI>sadnesse,</HI> by <HI>surfet,</HI> by <HI>sicknesse,</HI> by some one such <HI>casualty</HI> or other.</P>
<P N="2"><PB N="41" REF="24"/>
2. <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Casus nostros. no∣biscum in hac carne por<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>amus. Aug. hem. 28. Innumerabilia pericula in ipso sunt. sinu. Sen. quaest, uat. l. 6. c. 2.</NOTE> We carry euery one of vs our owne <HI>bane</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Reason 2.</NOTE> about vs. Euery one (say some <HI>Chymicks)</HI> hath his owne <HI>balsome</HI> within him: but <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Me∣trodor. Stob. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 16.</NOTE> euery one of vs (sure I am) hath within him his own <HI>bane;</HI> and that that will be sure at length to make an <HI>end</HI> of him, though no such <HI>casualtie,</HI> as before wee spake of, should befall him. <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Vitrei sum<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Aug. sup.</NOTE> <HI>We are of a glassie matter;</HI> (saith he) nay, <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Si vitrei esse∣mus, casus <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> timere<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>s. Fragi∣liores sumus quam si vitrei essemus. I∣demibid.</NOTE> were it so onely, <HI>we were better</HI> and <HI>safer</HI> th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n now we are. For <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Quid fragilius vase vitre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>? &amp; ta∣men seruatur &amp; durat per secula; &amp; inuenis calices ab auis &amp; proauis re∣liotos, in quibus bi∣bunt nepot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s &amp; pronepotes. Etsi e∣nim casus vitreo vafi timentur, se∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ectus ei &amp; feb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is non timotur. Ibid.</NOTE> a <HI>Venice glasse,</HI> as <HI>brit∣tle</HI> as it is, yet if it be charily <HI>kept,</HI> if it be carefully <HI>set vp,</HI> if it stand <HI>shut vp</HI> vnder locke and key, out of vse, out of harmes way, it may <HI>hold out</HI> many <HI>ages,</HI> it might <HI>last</HI> peraduenture euen as long as the <HI>world</HI> it selfe is like to <HI>last.</HI> But <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Demost. Clem Strom. l. 6. Ipse situ &amp; otio in tabem iturus est. Sen. ad Marc. c. 11.</NOTE> <HI>shut</HI> you <HI>vp man</HI> neuer so charily, <HI>keepe</HI> him neuer so carefully, hee may, nay he will <HI>drop away</HI> for all that, he hath <HI>poi∣son</HI> within him, that will at length make an <HI>end</HI> of him. He was <HI>bred</HI> and <HI>borne</HI> with a <HI>dangerous,</HI> with a <HI>desperate disease</HI> on him, and such as by no <HI>care</HI> or <HI>art</HI> of <HI>man</HI> he can be <HI>cured</HI> of or <HI>recouered.</HI> <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Apollodor. Donat. ad illud Ter. Phorm. 4. 1. Senectus ipsa morbus est.</NOTE> <HI>Old age</HI> (said he sometime) <HI>is it selfe a disease;</HI> and <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Senectus insanabilis morbus est. Sen. ep. 10<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Senectus m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rbus m∣gens. Nullis arcerive potest, pellive medelis. Erasm. desen.</NOTE> <HI>a disease that cannot he cured.</HI> But <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Ista vita morbus est.</NOTE> <HI>this life it selfe</HI> (saith an ancient Father) <HI>is a disease;</HI> and such <HI>a disease</HI> as we <HI>must all</HI> of vs needes one day <HI>dye of.</HI> <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Morieris, non quia aegrotas, sed quia viuis. Sen. ep. 78.</NOTE> <HI>Thou art sure to die</HI> (saith he) <HI>not because thou art sicke, but because thou liuest.</HI> For <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Medici, cum aegrotos inuisunt, phthisicus est, inquiunt, aut bydrop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cus, moriatur necesse est: deinde moritur tamen. Aug. ibid.</NOTE> <HI>sicke</HI> a man may <NOTE PLACE="marg">k Morbus hic necesse est vt ad m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtem perducat. Aug. de temp. 74.</NOTE>
<PB N="40" REF="25"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="41" REF="25"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="42" REF="26"/>
be, and yet <HI>not die</HI> of it: (not to adde, that <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Mu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> mor∣te<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>bus d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>∣lit. S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>. ib: l.</NOTE> <HI>a dis∣ease</HI> hath sometime <HI>delaid death.)</HI> But <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Psal 89. 48.</NOTE> <HI>what man liueth, and shall</HI> <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Vt Psal. 49. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>not see death?</HI> that is, <HI>who liueth, and shall not die?</HI> <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Totus ist us vitae <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>rsus n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>l aliud quam ad mortem de <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ursus est. Aug. Ciuit. l. 13 c 10. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o∣la vita ad mor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>m iter est. Sen. ad Po∣lyb. c. 30.</NOTE> The <HI>whole course of our life</HI> is nothing else but <HI>a passage to death:</HI> the seuerall <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plut. de EI Delph. Agunt opus suum sata: nobis sensum nostrae necis auferunt. Quoque facilius obrepat mors, subipso vi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ae nomine lat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t. Infantiam ins<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pue∣ritia conuertit, pu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ritia<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> pub<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtas, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>ntututem senectus abstulit. S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n. M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> c. c. 10.</NOTE> <HI>ages of our life</HI> so many seuerall <HI>degrees of death:</HI> <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Quotid è morimur: qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t commutamur. Hieron. Nepot. Quot. mor. quotidit d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>qua pars vitae. Seu. ep. 24.</NOTE> we are <HI>dying daily</HI> <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Ad mortem dies e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ruenit, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ced<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t omnis, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arpit nos ii, non corripit. Non repen∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> nos in mortem incid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, sed minutatim procedi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us minutatim subducimur. Sen. ep. 24. &amp; 30. &amp; 120.</NOTE> <HI>by degrees.</HI> No sooner are we (I say not, <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">Nasce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tes mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>w; finis{que} borigine peudet. Manil. l. 4 exquo primu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lucem vidit, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>r mortis ingressus est. Sen. M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rc. cap. 20.</NOTE> <HI>borne,</HI> but euen) <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, &amp;c. Plut. de EI.</NOTE> <HI>bred,</HI> but wee are <HI>dying</HI> and <HI>decaying.</HI> Euery <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Momentis singulis moximur. August. nom. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>dit. cap. 24. Qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> aliud singulis momentis agitur, donec ea cons<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>mata mors quae agebatur im∣pleatur, &amp;c. August. Ci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it. lib. 13. cap. 10.</NOTE> <HI>minute</HI> and <HI>moment</HI> that seemeth <HI>added to</HI> our <HI>life,</HI> <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> ipsa, si bene comsutes, damna sunt. Et illi ipsi qui addebantur adol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>entiae anni, vitae detrahcbantur. Sen. Marc. cap. 20. Cum cres∣sunt puers, quasi accedunt illis dies, cum reuerá decedant. Quicquid enim vixit, de summa minu∣it. Qua<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>do prodi. citur <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> non aug<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tur, nec addendo crescit, quia veniendo recedit. August. de verb. Dom. 1. &amp; 17. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. 1. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> de temp. 113. Ipsa suis augmentis vita ad detrimenta impellitur; &amp; inde deficit, vnde proficere creditur. Greg. Mor. l. 13. c. 27. Illa eadem vitam quae inchoat, bora <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>apit. Camil. epitaph. Et <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>psit bora vitam prima quae dedit. Sen. Her<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. fur. 3. 3.</NOTE> <HI>taketh from</HI> it. For our <HI>life</HI> it is as a <HI>taper,</HI> that being <HI>once lighted,</HI> neuer linneth spending, till it be <HI>wasted all</HI> at last: as <HI>the houre-glasse,</HI> that being <HI>once turned</HI> and set a running, <HI>neuer staieth,</HI> till the <HI>sand</HI> be <HI>all out.</HI></P>
<P>So that considering as well the <HI>varietie</HI> of <HI>casu∣alties,</HI> that we are all subiect vnto, as our owne <HI>frailty</HI> and <HI>mortalitie,</HI> that we are <HI>brod</HI> and <HI>bor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</HI> <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"> Quemad∣modum Clepsydram non extremum stillicidium exbaur. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, sed quicquid ante destuxit: sic vllima h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣ra, qua esse des<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>nus, non sola mortem facit, sed sola confummat. Sen. ep. 2<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE>
<PB N="43" REF="26"/>
with, it is no maruell if the <HI>longest liuers</HI> of vs <HI>die at last,</HI> it is maruell rather that <HI>any</HI> of vs <HI>liue so long.</HI></P>
<P>Now this may first teach vs, not to please our <NOTE PLACE="marg">Vse 1.</NOTE> selues with a conceit of <HI>long life, Why may not wee liue as long as such and such?</HI> To omit, that it is a thing altogether <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Isocr. ad De∣mon. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plut. in Epicur.</NOTE> <HI>vncertaine.</HI> For <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Eccles 3. 22.</NOTE> <HI>who can tell a man what shall be? Certaine</HI> it is, that <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Ar∣chin. Clem. Strom. l. 6. Omnes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>odem cogimur: omni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m Versatur vrná se∣rius <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cyus Sors exi∣tura, &amp;c. Horat. carm. 2. 3. Vse 2.</NOTE> <HI>first or last,</HI> <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">2 Sam. 14. 14. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Antho∣log. Debemur m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rti nos nostra{que}: Ho∣rat. art. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣rip. Alcest. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Ibid.</NOTE> <HI>die we must, liue</HI> wee neuer so <HI>long.</HI> As no∣thing more <HI>vncertaine</HI> than <HI>how long</HI> we shall <HI>liue:</HI> so <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Morte nihil <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ertius. Be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n. epist. 10. &amp; medit. c 3.</NOTE> nothing more <HI>certaine</HI> than that <HI>once</HI> <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Hebr. 9. 27.</NOTE> wee <HI>shall die.</HI> <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Incerta omnia: sola mors certa est. August. in Psalm. 38. &amp; de verb. Dom. 21.</NOTE> <HI>As sure as death:</HI> we say. And <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Quid diu est, vbi finis est? Aug. d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> verb. Dem 42. Quicquid finitur parum est. Greg. Moral. lib. 7. c. 20. Nulla longa mora est eius, quod aliquando e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>ict. T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>tull. Mihi ne <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>turnuni quidem qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c∣quam videtur, in quo est aliquid extremum. Cic. de s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n. &amp; Aug. ciui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. l. 12. c. 11.</NOTE> <HI>it ne∣uer stayeth long, that commeth at last. Stay death</HI> ne∣uer so <HI>long,</HI> before it come, it will seeme to <HI>come ouer-soone</HI> when it commeth, to those that desire it not, and at last <HI>come it will.</HI> And <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Si nongentos vitae excede<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> annos, vt ante dil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ium viu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r, &amp; Math<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m nobis tempora donarentur, tamen nihil esset praeterita longitudo, quae esse desisset. Et<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> inter eu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> qui de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>em vixit annos &amp; eum qui mille, post quamid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m vitae sinis aduenerit, &amp;c. tra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sactum omne tantundem est. Hier. in Nepot.</NOTE> <HI>last life</HI> neuer s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>ng,</HI> it will seeme but <HI>short,</HI> when it is once ouer. <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Psal. 90. 4.</NOTE> <HI>When it is gone,</HI> (saith the Psalmist) <HI>it is but as</HI> <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Quarta pars nectis.</NOTE> <HI>a watch in the night.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, it should admonish vs to take heed how we grow too farre in <HI>loue,</HI> either with this <HI>life</HI> it selfe, or with the <HI>things</HI> of <HI>this life.</HI> Since that, though we <HI>enioy</HI> them neuer so <HI>long,</HI> yet wee must <HI>leaue</HI> them at <HI>last.</HI> For <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">1 Tim. 6. 7. Iob. 1. 21. E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s. 5. 14. Nihil intulis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i, ni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>il hinc auferes. Aug. de verb. Dom. 5. &amp; 41. E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> red<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>untem natura, sicut intrantem. Non licet plus inferre quam intuleris. Sen. ep. 102.</NOTE> <HI>we brought them not with</HI>
<PB N="42" REF="27"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="43" REF="27"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="44" REF="28"/>
<HI>vs into this world; and it is certaine that</HI> <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Psal. 49. 17. Ce∣des co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mptis salt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣bus, &amp; do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, Vil∣lique; &amp; extruct∣in al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>um D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> poti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. Lin∣quenda <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>llus, &amp; d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mus, &amp; placeus vxor: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eq harum, qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>s, a borum te pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> cup <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ss<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s vlla bre∣uem d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> se∣q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>tur. Horat. car. 23 &amp; 14</NOTE> <HI>we cannot carry them out of the world</HI> with vs. If <HI>they leaue not vs</HI> while we <HI>liue here,</HI> <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou. 23. 6 <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yso<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 5. ser. 18. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Ibid. 19.</NOTE> which oft also they doe; yet <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Lucian. anthol. lib. 1. c. p. 13. Finem sunt habitura, aut tuum, aut suum. Bern. de bon. de∣ser. Et Sen. quaest. nat. l. 3. Aut p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m des<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, aut à possidente d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>seruntur. Al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uin. in Ec∣cles. praef.</NOTE> <HI>we</HI> cannot but <HI>leaue them</HI> when we <HI>goe hence.</HI> For all the <HI>things</HI> of this <HI>life</HI> must needs <HI>leaue</HI> vs, when our <HI>life</HI> it selfe <HI>leaueth</HI> vs, whereupon they depend. Let vs so <HI>hold,</HI> and <HI>vse</HI> these things there∣fore, that we <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Ps<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l. 62. 10. Sap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ns d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uitias non in animum, sed in domum recipiet. Sen. de b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at. c. 21.</NOTE> <HI>set not our hearts on them;</HI> that we suffer not our <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Coloss. 3 2.</NOTE> <HI>affections</HI> to be <HI>glewed</HI> to them. Let them <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Omniaista nobis acceda<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, non adhaereant; vt si abducantur, sine vlla nostra <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>acerationed d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>edant. Sen ep. 74.</NOTE> <HI>hang loose</HI> about vs, that when wee shall come to be <HI>stript</HI> of them, they may, as our <HI>gar∣ments,</HI> goe off with ease. Otherwise if they <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>cleaue</HI> and <HI>sticke fast</HI> to our <HI>soules,</HI> as <HI>cloathes</HI> are wont to doe to an <HI>vlcerous body,</HI> the <HI>parting</HI> one day, with them, which we can by no meanes auoid, will be <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Basil. Caes. hom. 7.</NOTE> as <HI>painfull</HI> vnto vs, as if our <HI>skin</HI> were <HI>pulled</HI> from our <HI>flesh,</HI> or <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Antipho. S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>b. c. 10. Quibu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> sua obhaesit, sine sensu au<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lli non potest. Sen. de tranq. cap. 8.</NOTE> our <HI>flesh <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orne</HI> from our <HI>bones,</HI> or ra∣ther <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Hesiod. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> as if some peece of our <HI>soule</HI> were <HI>reaft</HI> a∣way together with them.</P>
<P>Yea for <HI>life</HI> it selfe, if we <HI>loue</HI> it, (as <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Aesop. fab. Quis vitam non vult? Aug. hom. 4.</NOTE> <HI>who loueth not life?)</HI> let vs <HI>loue</HI> that <HI>life,</HI> that is <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">1 Tim. 6. 19. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Aeterna vita, veravita. Aug. de pec. mer. l. 1. c. 11. vera vita quae animam de morte eruit. Idem ep. 121. c. 2. Uita si diligitur, ibi acquiratur, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> nulla morte f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>r. Idem ep. 45.</NOTE> <HI>life indeed,</HI> and deserueth well that name. For this <HI>life</HI> that we
<PB N="45" REF="28"/>
liue here, is in a manner <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>; Eu∣rip. Hanc esse mor∣sem quā <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>s vita<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> du<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>imus, vitam il-Vse 3. lam quam pro mor∣te nos f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rmidamus. Lactant. instit. l. 3. 6. 18. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Eu∣rip. Ista v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>que quae tantum amatur vi∣ta, quamlibet iucū∣da as{que} prodicta sit, nec vita d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cēda est. Aug. ep. 121. Vita falsa est. Idem de verb. Dom. 5. hom. 13. et de temp 212.</NOTE> <HI>no life;</HI> it is <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Quod de arc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Herac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Eustath. ad I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ad. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plut. ad Apollen.</NOTE> <HI>life in name,</HI> but <HI>in deed</HI> and truth <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Mors est potius d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cenda quam <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>a, vel mortis quaedam pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>xitas. Gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g. in Euang. 36. Hae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vi∣ta qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>{us}, ma∣gis mors est, &amp;c. Bern. in Psal. 90. ser. 17.</NOTE> <HI>death.</HI> It is no <HI>true life</HI> that cannot <HI>ouercome death;</HI> that <HI>yeeldeth to,</HI> that <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>endeth to,</HI> that <HI>endeth in death.</HI></P>
<P>Thirdly, the consideration hereof should cause vs to <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Luk. 12. 15, 22.</NOTE> <HI>surcease</HI> and cast off this our <HI>immoderate care</HI> for the <HI>things of this life.</HI> As it hath beene said by way of reproofe of some people, that they vsed to <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">De Acragan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>is Empedo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>s; <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Lac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t. l. 8. De Rhodijs Stratonicus, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plut. de auar. Ide{que} ferè de Megarensib{us} Diogenes. Tertul apolog.</NOTE> <HI>build</HI> as if they looked to <HI>liue for euer:</HI> so it may well be said of many among vs, that they <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Esai. 5. 8.</NOTE> <HI>pur∣chase,</HI> and <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Jer. 22. 14, 15.</NOTE> <HI>build,</HI> and <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Ec∣cles. 4. 8.</NOTE> <HI>gather goods</HI> together, as if they made full account to <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Psal. 49. 11.</NOTE> <HI>liue euer</HI> to enioy them. Whereas neither are these things able to <HI>lengthen</HI> their <HI>liues:</HI> for <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Luk. 12. 15.</NOTE> <HI>haue a man neuer so much of them, his life dependeth not thereupon:</HI> nor to <HI>keepe</HI> them <HI>from death:</HI> for <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Psal. 49 7, 8, 9.</NOTE> <HI>no price can procure</HI> any <HI>im∣munitie from it:</HI> nor to <HI>saue</HI> them <HI>in death;</HI> for <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Prou. 11. 4. Ezck 7. 19.</NOTE> <HI>ri∣ches auaile not in the day of wrath:</HI> nor to <HI>auaile</HI> them <HI>after death;</HI> for there will then be <HI>no vse</HI> of them. And for men therefore <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Eccles. 5. 17.</NOTE> to <HI>beat</HI> their <HI>braines</HI> so much with <HI>thought</HI> and <HI>care</HI> for these things, and <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Eccles. 4. 8.</NOTE> to take such <HI>paines,</HI> as so many doe, for the com∣passing of them, is but <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Psal. 39. 6.</NOTE> to <HI>t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ile</HI> and <HI>moile</HI> about that, that they must <HI>leaue</HI> to others at length, and to <HI>inherite</HI> <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Psal. 49. 17. Eccles. 5. 15.</NOTE> nothing but <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Ier. 17. 11. Luk. 12. 20.</NOTE> <HI>folly</HI> and <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>s. 5. 16. &amp; 6. 2, 4.</NOTE> <HI>vanitie</HI> themselues, when others, <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Psal. 39. 6. Eccl. 6. 2.</NOTE> they <HI>know not</HI> who, <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">Eccl. 2. 18, 19.</NOTE> <HI>inherit</HI> the <HI>fruit</HI> of their <HI>labours.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="46" REF="29"/>
Lastly, this might teach vs <HI>not to feare death.</HI> <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ultum est ti∣mere, quod vitari non potest. P. Syr. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Ar∣rian. 1. Epict. l. 1. c. 27.</NOTE> <HI>It is a fond thing</HI> (saith he) <HI>to feare that, that cannot be</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Vse 4.</NOTE> <HI>auoided.</HI> A <HI>folly</HI> it is to <HI>trouble</HI> &amp; <HI>turmoile</HI> our selues with <HI>feare</HI> and <HI>care</HI> about that, that by no <HI>thought</HI> or <HI>forecast</HI> wee can <HI>shunne</HI> or <HI>shift off.</HI> But such is <HI>death.</HI> <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Differri potest, auserri non potest. Aug. de diuers. 36. Mortem differunt ista, non au<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>runt. Idem de verb. A∣post. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>8.</NOTE> <HI>Delayed it may be,</HI> but <HI>auoided it cannot be.</HI> And <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Sed etsi tardius quis moritur, nun∣quid ideò non mo∣ritur? Idē de temp. 74.</NOTE> be it nouer so <HI>long put off,</HI> yet <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Quid autem ad rem pertinet, qua∣diu vites, quod eui∣tare non possis? Sen. epist. 93.</NOTE> it will <HI>come at last.</HI> As an ancient Father therefore well and wisely aduiseth; <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Noli timere, quod velis, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>olis, e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>: id time, quod, si nelue∣ris, non erit. Aug. de diuers. 36.</NOTE> <HI>Feare not that, which whether thou wilt or no, will be; feare that rather, which if thou thy selfe wilt not, shall neuer be.</HI> That is, <HI>feare not</HI> this <HI>temporall death,</HI> the <HI>death</HI> of thy <HI>body,</HI> which of it selfe cannot <HI>hurt</HI> thee, and by no <HI>meanes</HI> or <HI>care</HI> of thine can be <HI>preuented:</HI> but <HI>feare</HI> that <HI>eternall death,</HI> the <HI>death</HI> of thy <HI>soule,</HI> <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">De hoc verè dici potest, <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. A∣ristot. Ethic. l. 3. c. 6. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Ep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. La<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rt. Ti∣mor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m maximus leti metus. Lucan. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>b. 1.</NOTE> <HI>the greatest of all euils</HI> that can possibly befall thee, which by mature <HI>care</HI> and <HI>diligence</HI> now vsed, may be <HI>preuented.</HI> But we are (as another well obserueth) herein, the most of vs, <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, &amp;c. Chrysost. tom. 6. serm. 43.</NOTE> like <HI>children,</HI> that are <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Persona <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> deformis <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>um facit. Sen. de constant. sap. cap 4. Laruam timent, lucernam non timent.</NOTE> <HI>afraid of a visour,</HI> but <HI>feare not the fire; shreeke</HI> and <HI>start</HI> at the one, but <HI>thrust</HI> their <HI>fingers</HI> into the other. <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Arrian. Epict. d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>t. l. b. 1. cap. 5.</NOTE> Wee <HI>feare the bodily death,</HI> but not the <HI>spirituall death,</HI> the <HI>death of the soule,</HI> the <HI>death in sinne,</HI> and <HI>dying in sinne,</HI> with∣out which the other cānot hurt. The <HI>feare</HI> of <HI>death troubleth</HI> and <HI>distracteth</HI> much our <HI>minds:</HI> but the <HI>feare</HI> of <HI>future matters,</HI> that are <HI>truly fearfull</HI> indeed, and but for w<SUP>ch</SUP> <HI>death</HI> needednot at al to be feared, doth no more <HI>trouble</HI> or <HI>affect</HI> the most, than as if
<PB N="47" REF="29"/>
no such thing were at all, or they were <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Esse aliquos ma∣nes, &amp;c. Nec pueri credunt, nisi qui nondum <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>relauan∣tur. Iu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>enal. Sat. 2. Nemo tam p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, vt ista <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>meat. Sen. epist. 24.</NOTE> <HI>babes</HI> on∣ly that <HI>beleeued</HI> them.</P>
<P>And thus much for the <HI>Generall,</HI> that from this <HI>third Branch</HI> we obserue:</P>
<P>Some <HI>Particulars</HI> follow; which I will <HI>point at</HI> rather than <HI>insist on.</HI></P>
<P>More specially therefore we may hence further obserue;</P>
<P>First, that in some cases <NOTE PLACE="marg">Point. Speciall 1.</NOTE></P>
<P><HI>To liue long is a blessing.</HI></P>
<P>It was foretold <HI>Abraham,</HI> as a <HI>fauour,</HI> that hee should <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Gen. 15. 15.</NOTE> <HI>die an old man:</HI> and it is here recorded that so he did. And it was foretold <HI>Eli,</HI> as an hea∣uie <HI>iudgement</HI> that should betide his posterity, that there should <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">1 Sam. 2. 32.</NOTE> <HI>neuer be any old man in his house. Long life,</HI> as in the <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Exod. 20. 12. E∣phes. 62. Deut. 4. 1, 40. &amp; 6 2.</NOTE> <HI>Law</HI> it is <HI>promised</HI> oft as <HI>a bles∣sing:</HI> and <HI>God</HI> where he describeth by the Prophet the flourishing estate of his people, saith, <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Esai. 65. 20.</NOTE> <HI>There shall no more be,</HI> <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Potest &amp; verti, ex eis, vt ad vtrū∣que tam infantulū quam senem, r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e∣ratur illud, Qui n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> impleat dies suos, quod &amp; Piscatori placet; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iue, cuius dies Deus non im∣pleat, vt Iun.</NOTE> <HI>from them,</HI> or <HI>goe thence, an infant of daies;</HI> that is, none of them shall die young or in <HI>infants</HI> estate; <HI>nor any old man that hath not fulfilled his daies;</HI> that is, <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Viuendi sinis est optimus, cum inte∣gra mente caeter. s{que} sensibus op<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>sa suum eadem, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> coagmentau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>∣tura d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssoluit. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> de sen.</NOTE> liued so long as in course of nature he well might: <HI>but the childe shall die an hun∣dred yeares old;</HI> that is, he that is now <HI>a childe</HI> shall liue till he be so many <HI>yeares old:</HI> (which <HI>place</HI> the rather I recite &amp; open at large, in regard of some friuolous <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Vise <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is Hieron. in Esai. 65. Greg. Mor. l. 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. c. 24. Hug. Card. &amp; Piscat. in Esai. &amp;c. Hinc emanauit Prouerbium, Puer centum annorum. Quod mirum est Drusium non aduert<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hoc loco, sed perpera<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> accept<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, mutuatum.</NOTE> <HI>crotchets</HI> that not a few haue <HI>fisht</HI> out of it, cleane beside as well the <HI>meaning</HI> as the <HI>drift</HI> of <HI>Gods Spirit:)</HI> So the <HI>shortning</HI> of mans <HI>life</HI> is
<PB N="48" REF="30"/>
<HI>threatned</HI> oft as a <HI>curse.</HI> <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Iob 15. 32, 33.</NOTE> <HI>Hee shall die</HI> <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Die non s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o, i. quem per naturam attinger<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pote<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at. I∣ta Firm. l. 8. c. 19. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rit longaeuus, in se∣necta soelix, &amp; qui sua <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e moria∣tur. Et de C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s percussoribus Sue∣ton. Nemo sua mor. Reason 1. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d functus est. Et Sen. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p. 69. Alioqui certū est quod ibid. Sen. Nemo nisi suo d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e moritur.</NOTE> <HI>before his time, as the greene grape is nipt off the Vine, and the O∣liue blossome shake off the tree;</HI> saith <HI>Eliphaz</HI> of the <HI>wicked.</HI> And, <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Psal. 55. 23.</NOTE> <HI>Hee shall not liue out halfe his daies;</HI> that is, <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">In medio dierum suorum tolletur, vt Psal. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>02. 24.</NOTE> halfe the time that he might in the course of <HI>nature</HI> haue attained to; saith the Psalmist of <HI>deceitfull and bloudie men.</HI></P>
<P><HI>And well may it be so deemed.</HI></P>
<P>For first, <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Leuit. 19. 32. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Reason 2. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Phocylid.</NOTE> <HI>Old age is honourable.</HI> Yea, as the A∣postle saith of <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Hebr. 13. 4.</NOTE> <HI>Mariage, It is honourable</HI> <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plato leg. l 9. Apud antiquissimos Romanorum, ne{que} generi, ne{que} pecuniae praestan∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>or honos trib<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> quam aetati solitus: maiores{que} natu à minoribus colebantur ad deum prope &amp; paren∣tum vicem; at{que} in omni loco, in{que} omni spec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> honoris potiores prioresque habiti. Gell. l 2. c. 15. Se∣nect<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>uentus ita cumulatum &amp; circumspectum honorem reddebat, tanquam maiores nat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ado∣lescentium communes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>atres essent. Val. Max. l. 2. c. 1. Magna <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uit quondam capitis reuerentia cani. Quid fast. l. 5. Credehant tunc grandenesas, &amp; morte pian<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>um, Si v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Iuuenis non assurrexerat. Iuuen. sat. 13.</NOTE> <HI>among all men.</HI> It is <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, &amp;c. Clem. Paedag. l. 3 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 3.</NOTE> a <HI>resemblance</HI> of <HI>Gods antiquitie,</HI> who is called <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Dan. 7. 13.</NOTE> <HI>the Ancient of daies.</HI> <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Prou. 20. 29.</NOTE> <HI>The glory of young men is their strength:</HI> (saith <HI>Solomon) and the beauty of old men is the gray-head.</HI> And, <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Prou. 16. 31.</NOTE> <HI>Old age,</HI> or <HI>the gray-head, is a crowne of glory,</HI> that is, <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plut. de sen. polit.</NOTE> <HI>a glorious crowne, where it is found in the way of righteous∣nesse.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, It is <HI>a blessing</HI> to liue to see <HI>posteritie,</HI> especially to liue to see withall <HI>Gods blessing</HI> vpon it. <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Psal. 128. 1.</NOTE> <HI>Blessed is the man that feareth God</HI> (saith the Psalmist) <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Psal. 128. 6.</NOTE> <HI>For</HI> (among other things, though it
<PB N="49" REF="30"/>
come <HI>last,</HI> yet <HI>not</HI> the <HI>least) he shall liue to see his childrens children,</HI> (that which is recorded also, as a part of <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Iob 42. 16. Reason 3.</NOTE> <HI>Iobs happinesse) and peace upon Israel.</HI></P>
<P>Thirdly, it is a matter of <HI>griefe</HI> to men <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Eurip. Alcest.</NOTE> more than ordinary, when <HI>friends</HI> are taken away from them by <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">In <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tatis flore morientur. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Sam. 2. 23. Hinc illa qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣Reason 4. rela, Immaturu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bij<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Senec. ad Marc. c. 20. Dol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> illū immatura mor∣te indignissimè rap∣tum Pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>. l. 6. ep. 6.</NOTE> <HI>immature death:</HI> when the ordina∣ry <HI>course</HI> of <HI>nature</HI> is <HI>inuerted,</HI> and they <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Nullum non a∣cerbum funus est, quod parens sequi∣tur. Sen. ibid. c. 17. Quod decuit natū patri praestar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> se∣pulto; Hoc contra nato praestitit ipse paren<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Epitaph. O∣lim parentū defunctorum liberi laudes dicebant. En rerum in nobis ordo mutatus est; &amp; in calami∣tatem nostrā perdidit sua iura natura. Quod exhibere senibus i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uenis debuit, hoc iuueni exhibemu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> senes. Hieron. ad Nepot.</NOTE> <HI>burie,</HI> those by whom they ought rather to haue beene <HI>buried.</HI></P>
<P>Fourthly, it is a great <HI>grace</HI> to a <HI>godly</HI> man, that he may doe <HI>God</HI> any <HI>good seruice.</HI> Such account it their greatest <HI>honour,</HI> as <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Act. 5. 41. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Elegantissimum oxymorum. Ca∣saub. S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Phil. 1. 29. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Ignat. ep. 12. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Idem ep. 11. Est &amp; confusionis gloria, &amp; confusio gloriosa. Ambr. in Psal. 43 Hac tempestate (D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tiano <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣uiente) certat <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in glo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>sa certamina ruebatur, multo{que} auidius martyria gloriosis mortibus quaere∣bantur, quam <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unc Epis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>opatus <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>auis ambi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ionibus appetuntur. Seuer. hist. l. 2. Rom. 5. 5. Intribula∣tionibus glorian<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r, contum<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> gloriam reputantes, opprobrium gaudium, d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>spectionem exalta∣tionem. Bern. de temp. 71.</NOTE> <HI>to suffer in Gods cause,</HI> so <HI>to be employed in Gods worke.</HI> But the <HI>longer</HI> a man <HI>liueth,</HI> the <HI>more glory</HI> may he bring to <HI>God,</HI> the more <HI>seruice</HI> may hee doe to the <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>Children of God,</HI> be he a <HI>publike</HI> person, or a <HI>priuate;</HI> not in re∣gard of <HI>occasions</HI> and <HI>opportunities</HI> onely, but in re∣gard also of <HI>aptnesse</HI> and <HI>abilitie</HI> thereunto: Since that <HI>continua<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce</HI> of <HI>yeeres</HI> bring<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Clem. p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d. l 3. c. 3. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Ibid. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Eurip. P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Beller. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Soph. O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dip. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. paedag. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Idem de sen. polit. Non omnia grandi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r aetas Quae fugiam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> habe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>: seris venit vsus abannis. Quid. Met. l. 6. Quisquis adsapientiam peruenit, annis peruenit. Sen. ep. 69. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Eurip. Hippolyt.</NOTE> <HI>wisdome</HI> and <HI>experience;</HI> and <HI>antiquitie</HI> carrying a kinde of
<PB N="50" REF="31"/>
<NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Iob 32. 4, 6, 7. Philē. 9. Apex se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e∣ctutis est aut <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ritas. Cic. de sea. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Plut desen. Senatus ergo à se∣nib<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Hin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>∣stus, Aud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te iuue∣nes sen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m, quem au∣diuere iu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣nes. Ibid. Point. Sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ciall 2.</NOTE> <HI>authority</HI> with it, procureth <HI>reuerence</HI> and <HI>respect:</HI> The former whereof fitteth men for the <HI>doing</HI> of the more <HI>good</HI> to others, the latter others for the <HI>receiuing</HI> of the more <HI>good</HI> from them.</P>
<P><HI>Long life</HI> in these <HI>respects</HI> therefore may well be deemed <HI>a blessing.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, we may hence obserue, that it is</P>
<P><HI>A great mercy of God to haue a good old age.</HI></P>
<P>It is a <HI>mercy</HI> more than ordinary for men at those <HI>yeeres</HI> to be kept free in some good measure, though not from such <HI>weaknesse</HI> as the <HI>decay</HI> of <HI>na∣ture</HI> necessarily importeth, yet from such <HI>aches,</HI> and <HI>paines,</HI> and <HI>grieuances,</HI> and <HI>diseases,</HI> and <HI>annoi∣ances,</HI> as that <HI>age</HI> is wont commonly to be annoied and pestered with.</P>
<P>For first, <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Reason I. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Sclcrias S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ob. cap. 101. Scolio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hoc citat &amp; Pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>o in Gorg. &amp; A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>ot. Rhet. l. 2. c. 22 Sed &amp; Plat. leg. l. 1. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ibid. l. 2. idem ferè babet. Quin &amp; <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Deliacamcitat Aristot. Ethi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Nicom. l <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. c. 8. &amp; Eadem l. 1. c. 1. quá <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> dicitur. Senar. Grae. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. i. mens sana in corpore sano. Iuuen. sat. 10. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>; Plato Gorg.</NOTE> <HI>Health</HI> and the enioyment of it, is at all times <HI>a great mercy;</HI> (<NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>▪ Plut. de sanit. &amp; de tranq. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Ifidor. Pel: l: 3. ep. 192. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Ariphron. Athen. lib vlt.</NOTE> no outward thing being comfortable or delightfull without it) that which nothing sheweth so well as <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Hera<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Basil. Caes, hom. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. Quid boni hav<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at sanitas, languor ostendit. Hier. n. consol. Pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</NOTE> the <HI>want</HI> of it at some times, and the <HI>inconueniences</HI> that ensue thereupon. And if to enioy it at any time then be <HI>no small bene∣fit,</HI> euen at such <HI>times</HI> wherein others are wont vsu∣ally to enioy it: how much more is it <HI>a great mer∣cie</HI>
<PB REF="31"/>
to haue it at that <HI>age,</HI> wherein most men are wont to finde a much more than vsuall <HI>want</HI> of it? The more <HI>infectious</HI> the <HI>times</HI> and <HI>places</HI> are that we liue and abide in, the greater <HI>goodnesse</HI> of <HI>God</HI> it is to vs, if we keepe <HI>free</HI> from <HI>infection:</HI> So the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ore <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">Eccles. 12. 1. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>8. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Reason 2. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Antiph. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Bion. I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ert. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Eurip. O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nom. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Eurip. Glauc. Objicit innumeris c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s lacerabile morbis. Auson. idyl. 15. circumsilit agmi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> sacto Morborum omne genus. Iuuen. sat. 10.</NOTE> <HI>old age</HI> is subiect to <HI>diseases</HI> and <HI>disasters,</HI> the grea∣ter <HI>mercy</HI> it is for <HI>old</HI> men to be kept <HI>free</HI> then from either.</P>
<P>Againe, it is not so much the bare <HI>decay</HI> of <HI>na∣ture</HI> or <HI>ab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tement</HI> of bodily <HI>strength,</HI> as either ma∣keth <HI>old age</HI> so <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>: Onus Aetna grauius. Cic. de sen. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>; Eurip. Bacch. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>; Phe∣recrat.</NOTE> <HI>cumbersome</HI> &amp; <HI>burdensome</HI> to men, and depriueth them of all <HI>alacrity</HI> and <HI>cheereful∣nesse</HI> of spirit; (you shall see <HI>old men,</HI> though so <HI>weake</HI> and <HI>feeble,</HI> that they can scarce stir from the place where they are set, yet as <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg">Plena <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st voluptatis senectus, fi illa scias vti. Sen. ep. 12. His mihi rebus le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is est s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne∣ctus; nec solum non mol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sta, sed etiam iucunda. Cato. Q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d est enim iu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>undius senectute stipata stud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>tis? <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ic. de sen.</NOTE> <HI>cheerefull</HI> and <HI>fro∣licke,</HI> as we say, and as <HI>heartie,</HI> yea much more <HI>light∣some</HI> many times, than many farre <HI>younger</HI> than themselues) or that disableth them to doing good, and to the performance of good <HI>offices</HI> for the <HI>be∣hoofe</HI> and <HI>benefit</HI> of others: (For such albeit their bodily <HI>strength</HI> be most past, yet their <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Eurip. Peleo. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. de sen. pol. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Menand. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Eurip. Ione. Non sentio in animo <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>is iniuriani, cum sentiam in corpore. Vigetanimus: illius flos senectus. Sen. ep. 26.—nec tarda senectus Debilitat vires animi, mentis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue vigorem. Virg. Aen. lib. 9.</NOTE> <HI>wits</HI> may
<PB REF="32"/>
be still <HI>fresh:</HI> and though they cannot afford much <HI>helpe</HI> of the <HI>hand,</HI> yet <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. de sen. pol. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Eurip. Melamp <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. La<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Sophocl. Thyest. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Antiphan. Philoct.</NOTE> by sage <HI>counsell</HI> and graue <HI>aduice,</HI> they may further <HI>affaires</HI> more either <HI>publike</HI> or <HI>priuate,</HI> <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Eu∣rip. A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tiop. Polyb. lib. 1. Plut. de sen. Pol. Galen. de art. Stob. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 52. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Oppian. pisc. l. 5. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Agatho. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Menand. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Gabr. Fab. Hinc Agamemnon decem Nestores potius quam Aiaces optat. Iliad. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Cic. de sen. Plut. de sen. pol.</NOTE> than many <HI>younger</HI> and <HI>stronger</HI> are a∣ble<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>doe with their <HI>hands:</HI> <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Aristoph. vesp.</NOTE> <HI>a few gray haires,</HI> saith on<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; may be more worth, than <HI>many young lockes;</HI> and a few <HI>gray beards</HI> doe more than many <HI>greene heads.</HI> It is not that <HI>decay</HI> of <HI>nature</HI> or bodily <HI>strength</HI> so much, I say, as such <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t. ibid. Non proprium senectutis est vit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>um, sed commune valetudinis. Cic. de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en.</NOTE> <HI>paines</HI> and <HI>diseases</HI> as vsu∣ally accompany <HI>old age,</HI> that are wont to make it to be either so <HI>tedious</HI> to them themselues, that they grow <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Iob 7. 15, 20. Nunc quia longa mihi grauis est &amp; inutilis aetas, viuere cum nequeam, sit mihi posse mori. Maxim. eleg, 1.</NOTE> <HI>weary</HI> oft euen of their <HI>liues,</HI> or that ma∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eth them so <HI>unprofitable</HI> to others, yea and oft so <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Menand. Tum equidem in se∣necta hoc depuso miserrimum, Sentire ea aetate esse odi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sum alteri. Caecil. Vsque adeo grauis vx<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ri, natisque, sibique, Vt captatori moueat fastidia Cosso. Iuuen. 10.</NOTE> <HI>burdensome</HI> too, that they grow as <HI>weary</HI> of them, as they are themselues of their <HI>liues.</HI> Which to be <HI>freed</HI> therefore from, either for the most part, or in some good measure, in that <HI>age,</HI> must needs bee counted no small <HI>merey.</HI></P>
<P>Thirdly, obserue wee hence, that there is a kinde of</P>
<P><HI>Satietie and fulnesse of life:</HI></P>
<P>not so much, I say, an <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Quosdam subit eadem viden∣di saciendique sati<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tas, &amp; vitae non odium, sed fastidium. Sen. ep. 24.</NOTE> <HI>irkesomnesse,</HI> and <HI>tedious∣nesse,</HI> <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>; Eurip. Menalip. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Soph. S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yr.</NOTE>
<PB REF="32"/>
as <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Habet enim na∣tura, vt aliarum omnium rerum, sic viuendi modū. Cic. de sen.</NOTE> a <HI>satietie</HI> and <HI>fulnesse;</HI> when a man, though not weary of a thing, yet he hath his <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Vixi quantum sa∣tis er at: mortem plenus expecto. Sen. epist. 62.</NOTE> <HI>fill,</HI> so much as he desireth, of it; to the <HI>godly</HI> especially; for I finde not the <HI>phrase</HI> vsed in the <HI>word</HI> but of them onely; as of <HI>Abraham</HI> here, of <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Gen. 35. 29.</NOTE> <HI>Isaak,</HI> of <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Iob 42. 17.</NOTE> <HI>Iob,</HI> of <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">2 Chron. 24. 15.</NOTE> <HI>Iehoiada,</HI> of <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">1 Chron. 23. 1.</NOTE> <HI>Dauid,</HI> of whom it is said also, that he died <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">1 Chron. 29. 28. Reason 1.</NOTE> <HI>with a good gray head, full of daies and riches, and honour.</HI></P>
<P>Now this <HI>satietie</HI> and <HI>fulnesse</HI> of <HI>life</HI> commonly befalleth such;</P>
<P>First, when some speciall <HI>promises</HI> of <HI>God</HI> haue beene <HI>made good</HI> to them, or some speciall <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Omnino rerū om∣nium satietas vitae facit satietatem. Vi∣tae autem satietas tempus maturum mortis assert. Cic. de sen.</NOTE> <HI>bles∣sings</HI> of <HI>God enioyed</HI> by them, correspondent to their owne <HI>desires.</HI> So <HI>Simeon,</HI> when he had <HI>liued</HI> so long (<NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Luke 2. 26.</NOTE> which it was foretold him he should doe) as to <HI>see our Sauiour</HI> in the flesh, he hath euen enough of this life, he desireth not now to liue an houre longer. <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Luke 2. 29, 30.</NOTE> <HI>Lord</HI> (saith he) <HI>now lettest thou thy ser∣uant depart in peace; since that mine eyes haue once seene thy saluation,</HI> my Sauiour, and the Sauiour of all mankind. So <HI>Iacob,</HI> when he saw his sonne <HI>Io∣seph</HI> againe, whom he had <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Gen. 37. 33, 35. &amp; 42 36, 38.</NOTE> giuen vp for <HI>dead</HI> and gone long agoe, not <HI>aliue</HI> only, but in <HI>honour,</HI> and not <HI>him</HI> alone, but his <HI>issue</HI> too; <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">Gen. 46. 30.</NOTE> <HI>Let me now die;</HI> (saith he) <HI>I haue liued long enough; I desire life now no longer; since I haue seene thy face, and that thou art yet aliue. For</HI> <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">Gen. 48. 11.</NOTE> <HI>I made full account neuer to haue seene thy face; and behold God hath made me see thy seed.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, where their <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Sunt pueritiae certa stud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a; sunt &amp; ineuntis adol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s∣centiae; sunt &amp; cō∣stantis aetatis; sunt &amp; extremae sene-Reason 2. ctutis: istaergò<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> occidunt, fit vitae sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. desen.</NOTE> <HI>employments</HI> here are at a <HI>full point,</HI> at a <HI>period;</HI> when they haue <HI>done</HI> their <HI>taske</HI> that <HI>God</HI> had <HI>assigned</HI> them, and there
<PB REF="33"/>
<NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">Non acerbum iam iudicant viuere, sed supersluum. Senec. epist. 24.</NOTE> seemeth to be now here <HI>no</HI> further <HI>work</HI> for them. <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Act 13. 36.</NOTE> <HI>Dauid</HI> (saith he) <HI>when he had serued his set time by God assigned him, slept.</HI> And the Apostle <HI>Paul,</HI> as <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Philip. 1. 24, 25. Ita Martinus de∣cumbens; Domine, si adhuc populo tuo sum necessarius, nō recuso laborem, &amp;c. Seuer. epist. 3. &amp; B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rn. ser. de Mart.</NOTE> he was content <HI>to stay longer in the flesh for the good of the Philippians,</HI> and the <HI>furtherance</HI> of their <HI>faith,</HI> then he desired otherwise to doe: so hee saith on the other side, that <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Act. 20. 24.</NOTE> <HI>his life was not deare to him,</HI> he cared not how soone he laid it downe, if so be that he had <HI>fulfilled</HI> but <HI>the course of his ministery,</HI> and that his <HI>worke</HI> it were once <HI>at an end.</HI></P>
<P>The <HI>Vse</HI> of which seuerall <HI>Points</HI> in a word, may be,</P>
<P>First of the two former, to admonish <HI>old men,</HI> and such more specially as through the <HI>goodnesse</HI> of <NOTE PLACE="marg">Vse 1.</NOTE> <HI>God</HI> enioy a <HI>commodious</HI> and <HI>comfortable time</HI> of it, <HI>free</HI> from many such <HI>griefes</HI> as they heare others of their yeares oft complaine of, to acknowledge <HI>Gods</HI> great <HI>mercy</HI> and <HI>goodnesse</HI> to them therein; as <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Psal. 91. 16.</NOTE> in <HI>lengthening</HI> out their <HI>life,</HI> and <HI>satisfying</HI> them with a greater <HI>number of daies</HI> then others ordina∣rily attaine vnto, by means whereof they may liue to <HI>see</HI> those <HI>brought</HI> vp vnder them, and <HI>bestowed</HI> by them, that are of their <HI>charge,</HI> and whom <HI>God</HI> hath here <HI>blessed</HI> them with: so <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Psal. 103. 5.</NOTE> in <HI>freeing</HI> of them from such <HI>annoiances,</HI> as are vsually <HI>attendants</HI> of that <HI>age,</HI> and which might make their <HI>continuance</HI> here the more <HI>tedious</HI> and vncomfortable to them: And <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plut. desen. polit. &amp; de vit. Epicur. Sene∣ctus non modò lan∣guida &amp; iners non sit, verum etiam sit operosa, &amp; semper pro eis, qua<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> habet viribus, agens ali∣quid &amp; moliens. Cic. d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sen.</NOTE> to apply themselues therefore to such <HI>holy</HI> and <HI>religious Employments,</HI> so farre forth as their present estate and condition shall permit, whereby they may bring <HI>glory</HI> to <HI>God,</HI> and doe some <HI>seruice</HI> to him, who is so <HI>good</HI> and <HI>gratious</HI> to them aboue
<PB REF="33"/>
many others in that kinde: Remembring withall, that howsoeuer <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Cognatasunt <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Eu∣stath. Il <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y∣molo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Pythag. l. acrt. Vse 2.</NOTE> <HI>old age</HI> of it selfe be <HI>an honour;</HI> yet it is nothing lesse, if it be not <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Prou. 16. 31 Ve∣nerabilis senectus; verum virtutum, non anno<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ū nume∣ro computata. Guil. de Theodor. de a∣mor. Dei. c 9. Alio∣qui nihil turpius quam grandis natu senex, qui nih. l ha∣bit, quo se prob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t diu vixisse p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aeter aetatē. Sen. de t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>āq. c. 3. Non enim cani rugae que, sed hone∣ste acta aeta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, auto∣ritatē afferunt. Ci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sen. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Philo antholog. l 1. c. 16.</NOTE> <HI>found in the way of righteousnesse,</HI> as the wise man speaketh, if it be not religiously imployed: And that, how∣soeuer to the <HI>godly long life</HI> may be <HI>a blessing,</HI> yet <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Es<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i. 65. 2<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> <HI>the wicked man,</HI> (saith the Prophet) <HI>though he liue an hundred yeeres, shall be but an accursed wretch.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, the <HI>vse</HI> of the <HI>last</HI> of these <HI>points</HI> may be to shew <HI>a difference</HI> betweene <HI>godly</HI> and <HI>worldly</HI> men. The <HI>godly</HI> haue oft euen a <HI>satietie</HI> of <HI>life:</HI> <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Bion. Stob. c 1. Rarus qui exacto con en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us tempore vitae, Cedat, vti con <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>a satur. Hor. sat 1. Cur non vt plenus vitae c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nuiuareced s Lucret. l. 3.</NOTE> As <HI>willing</HI> they are <HI>to leaue the world,</HI> as men are wont to be <HI>to rise from the bord,</HI> when they haue <HI>eaten</HI> their <HI>fill,</HI> or so much as they desire. But with <HI>worldly</HI> men for the most part it is farre otherwise: they haue <HI>neuer enough,</HI> as of <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Prou 30. 13, 14. Hab. 2 5. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Solon. Arist. polit. l. 1. c. 5. Plut. de auar. Basil. hom. 24 Stob. c. 10. Nemo est, cui foelicita<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sua, etiamsi cursu veniat, satisfaciat. Seu. ep. 115. Non potest cupjditatibus, etiamsi expleatur diui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. Ambr. de bon. mort. c. 1. Auarus an mus nullo satiatur lu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ro. P. Sjr. Seu. ep. 49. Fortuna multis dat nimis, nulli satis. Martial. l. 12. ep. 10.</NOTE> the <HI>wealth</HI> of this <HI>world,</HI> so of <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Deinde animi ingrati natu∣ram p s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere semper, At{que} explere bonis rebus, satiareque numquam; Qued faciunt nobis annorum temp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ra, circum Cum redeunt, foetusque serunt, variosque lepores, Nec tamen explemar vita<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sru∣ct. bus <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nquam. Lucret. l. 3.</NOTE> this present <HI>life:</HI> by their good will they would <HI>neuer die.</HI> It is true indeed, that some∣time, either <HI>crosses</HI> and <HI>calamities,</HI> extraordina∣rie <HI>disasters,</HI> or sore torturing <HI>paines</HI> and long lin∣gring <HI>diseases,</HI> out of a kinde of <HI>impatiencie,</HI> may make them <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Hae res vitae me, soror, saturant: Hae m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hidiuidiae &amp; s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>osunt. Plaut. Stich. 1. 1.</NOTE> <HI>weary</HI> of their <HI>liues</HI> and <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Taedio vitae ad <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ortem curritur. Epicur. Sen. ep. 24. mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bi. Plin. Sec. l. 3. ep. 3. Liboris. Cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t. l 5.</NOTE> <HI>desirous</HI> of
<PB REF="34"/>
<HI>death,</HI> which but for those <HI>grieua<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ces</HI> and <HI>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>oia<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ces</HI> they would else be farre from: Whereas the god∣ly, with <HI>Abraham</HI> &amp; <HI>Dauid,</HI> euen then also, <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Mu∣son. Stob. c. 1. Ill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> lauda &amp; imitare, quem non piget ino∣r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> cum iuuat v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue∣re Sen. ep. 54. cum v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uere aceroum nō si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Idem ep 24.</NOTE> when they haue a <HI>good</HI> and a <HI>comfortable</HI> continuance of <HI>life,</HI> accompanied and attended as well with <HI>health</HI> of body, as with <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">1 Chron. 29. 28.</NOTE> <HI>honour</HI> and <HI>wealth,</HI> yet haue their <HI>fill</HI> of it, and are as well willing to leaue it, as the other are some <HI>dish</HI> of <HI>meat</HI> that they haue <HI>eaten</HI> their <HI>fill</HI> of. Yea <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plutarc. d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tranquil. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Idem de clar. foem. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Epi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tet. S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>b. c. 120. Inter mortis metum &amp; vitae tormenta miseri fluctuant: &amp; viuere no∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unt, &amp; mori nes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iunt. Sen. ep. 4. Pati non vultis, exire timetis: quid faciam vobis? Cypr. de mortal.</NOTE> so fondly are <HI>worldly</HI> men here∣in oft affected, and their hearts so possessed with the <HI>loue</HI> of this <HI>life,</HI> that though <HI>they know not how to liue,</HI> yet <HI>they are not willing to die;</HI> though their <HI>life</HI> be so <HI>irkesome</HI> and <HI>painfull</HI> unto them, that they seeme to be <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">De <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>redico Plato <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plut. de tard. vind. Quid buius viuere est? d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u mori. Sen, ep. 101. Mortis habet vices, Lentè cum trahitur vita dolentibus. Sen. Herc. O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t. 1. 2.</NOTE> <HI>long a dying</HI> rather than to <HI>liue long,</HI> and <NOTE N="x" PLACE="marg">Morsque minus p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>nae quam mor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> mortis habet. Onid. ep. 10.</NOTE> the <HI>delay of death</HI> farre <HI>worse</HI> with them, <HI>than death</HI> it selfe could be to them, yet they desire <NOTE N="y" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Homer. Odys. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Eurip. Aulid. Debilem facito manu, Deb. lempede, coxa: Tuber adstrue gibberum; Lubricos qua∣te dentes. Vita dum superest, bene est, Me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aenas. Quod miserrimum erat, si incidisset, optatur, &amp; tanquam vitapetitur, supplicij mora. Inuenitur qui malit inter supplicia tabescere, &amp; perir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>mbratim; &amp; t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ties per stillicidia <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mittere animam, quam semel exhalare? Inuenitur, qui velit trahere <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tormenta tracturam? Est tanti habere animam, ut agam? Sen. epist. 101.</NOTE> to endure rather any extremitie of griefe and <HI>torture</HI> with <HI>life,</HI> than to haue an end put to their <HI>paines</HI> and <HI>torments</HI> by <HI>death.</HI></P>
<P>But let vs rather herein striue to be affected as <HI>Gods Saints</HI> are, especially when it hathpleased <HI>God</HI>
<PB N="57" REF="34"/>
to blesse vs with long <HI>life,</HI> with many yeeres more, than the greater number of folke are wont to at∣taine to; <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Id agendum est, vt satis vixerimus. Sen. epist. 23. Vt sa∣tis vixerimus, nec anni, nec d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es faci∣ent, sed animus. I∣dem epist. 62.</NOTE> labour to finde and feele in our selues this <HI>satiety</HI> and <HI>fulnesse</HI> of <HI>life;</HI> and be willing and content to leaue it, when <HI>God</HI> shall please to call for it, though no speciall <HI>affliction</HI> or <HI>paine</HI> enforce thereunto, not <NOTE N="z" PLACE="marg">Fastidio illis esse cepit vita. Sen. de tranq. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. 2. Est etia<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vitae ipsius nausea quaedam. Idē ep. 24. Et de Abr. in hunc locum Paraeus, Per∣taesus vitae aerum∣nosae. Quod minus buc quadr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t. Particular 4. Quo. Place, Whither.</NOTE> as <HI>a meat loathed,</HI> (which the na∣turall man oft doth) but as <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> dish,</HI> though well <HI>li∣ked,</HI> that we haue <HI>fed</HI> our <HI>fill</HI> of.</P>
<P>And hitherto also of the <HI>third Particular,</HI> to wit, <HI>time when</HI> he died.</P>
<P>The <HI>fourth</HI> and last followeth, and that is <HI>whither</HI> hee went when hee died; whereof the <HI>Text</HI> saith here, that</P>
<P><HI>He was gathered to his people;</HI> and in another place of him, that</P>
<P><NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Cap. 15. 15.</NOTE> <HI>He went to his Fathers.</HI></P>
<P>And there is nothing more frequent and com∣mon in <HI>Scripture</HI> than these and the like <HI>phrases</HI> v∣sed of persons <HI>deceassing,</HI> that <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg">1 King. 2. 10. &amp; 11 43. &amp; 14. 30. &amp; 15. 8, 24.</NOTE> <HI>they sleepe with,</HI> <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg">Gen. 15. 15.</NOTE> <HI>they goe to,</HI> <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Gen. 35. 29. &amp; 49. 33. Num. 20. 24, 26. &amp; 27. 13. &amp; 31. 2. Deut. 32. 50.</NOTE> <HI>they are gathered vnto,</HI> either <HI>their people,</HI> that is, their <HI>countrimen,</HI> or <HI>their ancestors,</HI> for that is, <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Act. 13. 36. Point. Generall 4.</NOTE> <HI>their Fathers.</HI> So that,</P>
<P><HI>Men, when they die, they goe to their people, to their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Fathers.</HI></P>
<P>That which may well be vnderstood <HI>two waies;</HI> and the <HI>Holy Ghost</HI> might well therin aime at <HI>both,</HI> because <HI>both</HI> goe vnder <HI>one generall,</HI> and the <HI>phrase</HI> as it may <HI>fit either,</HI> so <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Statum mortuo∣rum in genere. Vn∣de dieu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t Hebr. Qui moritur, ambulat per viam, per quam ambularunt patres cius. Oleast.</NOTE> it may well <HI>include both.</HI></P>
<PB REF="35"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="35"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<P><PB N="58" REF="36"/>
First in regard of the <HI>body:</HI> because <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Gen. 3. 19. Eccl. 12. 7. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Epicha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m. Ced<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> enim re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rò, de terra quod fuit an∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, In terras: &amp; quod missum est ex aethor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s oris, Id r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>∣sum coeli rellatum templa rec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ptant. Lu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ret. l. 2.</NOTE> <HI>it retur∣neth to the earth,</HI> the <HI>common</HI> <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Sic hominū terra, vt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oelum De<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; quae nos nas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>entes exci∣pit, natos abt, se∣mel{que}, editos sust<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>net s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mper, nou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssime <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>plexa gremto j<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a reliqua natura abdicates, tū maxi∣me, vt mater, operi∣ens. Plin. l. 2. c. 63. T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rra quae dedit, ipsa capit, n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>{que} d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>spendi facit hilum. Haec enim gentes omnes pepe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t, &amp; r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sum<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t denuo. Ennius Epithar. Varro deling. Lat. l. 4. capit omnia tellus Quae g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nuit. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>can. l. 7.</NOTE> <HI>receptacle</HI> of all. As <NOTE PLACE="marg">Reason I.</NOTE> it is said of <HI>Dauid,</HI> that <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Act. 13. 36.</NOTE> <HI>he was laid vnto,</HI> or <HI>laid vp, with his Fathers.</HI> For howsoeuer of <HI>Abraham</HI> it <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Paraeus.</NOTE> seeme to some, that it cannot be so meant, be∣cause <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Gen. 25. 9, 6.</NOTE> his <HI>corpes</HI> was <HI>enterred</HI> in the Land of <HI>Ca∣naan,</HI> (<NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Psal. 105. 11.</NOTE> so generally termed) in a strange coun∣trey, where his countrey-men in likelihood none of them lay: yet it followeth not thence, that it may not euen in that sense also be said of him too: since that the <HI>graue</HI> in generall, <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">See the wor∣thie Primate of <HI>Armaugh</HI> Answer to Iesuites Challenge, pag. 291 &amp;c.</NOTE> not the <HI>artificiall</HI> one, but the <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Omnibus na∣tura s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pulturam dedit. Nausragos idem fluctus, qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> expul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>peht: sussixorum corpora <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>bus in sepulturam suam d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stuunt: e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, qui v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> vr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur, poena sunerat. Sen. controu. 4. l. 8. sepelit natura relictos, Me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> apud Sen. epist. 92.</NOTE> <HI>naturall,</HI> (which <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> &amp; <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/></NOTE> the <HI>Hebrewes</HI> al∣so well distinguish) is (as <HI>Iob</HI> fitly termeth it) <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Iob 30. 23. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Greg. Naz. ad Av<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an. Omniparens, eadem re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>um commune sepulcrum. Lucret. l. 5. Sic Ca∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. ad Madl. Tro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>as, commune sepul rum Asiae Europaeque.</NOTE> <HI>the Congregation house of all liuing,</HI> that is, the <HI>place</HI> wherein they <HI>all meet</HI> together after <HI>decease,</HI> be the <HI>places</HI> of their <HI>sepulture</HI> neuer so farre asunder; yea whether they haue any <HI>sepulture</HI> or no, as <HI>Iacob</HI> sup∣posed that <HI>Ioseph</HI> had not, whom hee yet saith, hee would <HI>die, and</HI> <NOTE N="r" PLACE="marg">Gen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s. 37. 37. V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se Drus. obs<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ru. lib. 4. cap. 23. In luctu permanebo donec me terra suscipiat, vt filium meum sepulcrum <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> sus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. Al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>um. S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ra enim in Scripturae locu mul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is intelliguntur, non ea solum quae ad d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>nem humanorum corporum videntur esse constructa, vel in saxis excisa, aut in terra d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssa; sed om<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us in quo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>umque vel integrum <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>pus humanum, vel ex par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e aliqua iacet, eti∣a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>si <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t vt vnum corpus per loca <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>lta a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sp rsum sit. Origen. in Esai. lib. 8. Euseb. apolog. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Plin. lib. 7. cap. 54. Sepultus d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>citur qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>quo modo conditus; humatus, humo con∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>goe downe to, to the graue.</HI> And
<PB N="59" REF="36"/>
as well might <HI>Abraham,</HI> for his <HI>body</HI> also, be said, to be <HI>gathered to his people,</HI> though hee were <HI>buried</HI> in some other place then the most of them were, as <HI>Jacob</HI> might be said to <HI>goe to Ioseph,</HI> because <NOTE N="s" PLACE="marg">Gen. 50. 13.</NOTE> he was to be <HI>laid in the ground</HI> when he died, <HI>Ioseph</HI> being, as he supposed, <NOTE N="t" PLACE="marg">And<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Caes. in A∣po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> 16 à cambus de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oratos, conum vent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es viua stpul-Reason 2. Generall. cra sortitos. Qued <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Diogenes di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>it. Stob. c. 123. A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>t cadauer alites, alit fera<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>vivum sepul∣crum mortuo sic ob∣tigit. Et A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us A∣treo; Natis sepui∣crum est <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pse pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es. Cic. offic. l. 1.</NOTE> <HI>buried</HI> in the <HI>bowels</HI> of some <HI>beast:</HI> since that, as <HI>Solomon</HI> saith, <NOTE N="u" PLACE="marg">Eccles 3. 10.</NOTE> <HI>all goe to one common place; all returne againe to their dust.</HI></P>
<P>Secondly, in regard of the <HI>Soule.</HI></P>
<P>First <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">De commun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> gene∣ris humani (quoad vitam futuram) so∣cietate. Calu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</NOTE> in <HI>Generall:</HI> because it departeth hence indefinitely into <HI>another world,</HI> not <HI>proper</HI> and <HI>pecu∣liar,</HI> as he said <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Plut. de superst<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>. Speciall.</NOTE> each one did when hee <HI>slept,</HI> but <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. An bo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. lib. 3. cap. 6.</NOTE> <HI>common</HI> and <HI>generall:</HI> it goeth hence to the <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Anár. in Apoc. c. 63. Dicunt animas corpore liberatas <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> pe∣tere. i. licum qui non videtur. Ambr. de bon. mort. c. 10. Vide Platon. in Phaedone.</NOTE> <HI>vn∣seene world,</HI> as the <HI>Heathens</HI> termed it, or to the <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Qued Christian<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> seculum futurum, Iudaei s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uum animarum d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cunt. Brought. in Symbol. &amp; S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>indler. lexic. Pentaglot.</NOTE> <HI>world of Soules,</HI> as the <HI>Hebrew Doctors</HI> call it; to that <HI>other world,</HI> (including both <HI>Heauen</HI> and <HI>Hell)</HI> in generall, that is <HI>the Congregation House of Soules,</HI> as the <HI>Graue</HI> is of <HI>Corpses:</HI> As <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Augelum tuiis simu∣lans se Satanas, non Samuel. Aug. ad Simplic. l. 2 q. 3. &amp; de wirab. l. 2. 6. 11.</NOTE> the supposed <HI>Sa∣muel</HI> told <HI>Saul,</HI> (though he meant not, nor inten∣ded it so to be taken, that <HI>Saul</HI> should be in the same <HI>speciall state</HI> or <HI>place</HI> that <HI>Samuel</HI> was then in, when he died) <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">I Sam. 28. 19.</NOTE> <HI>To morrow shalt thou be with me;</HI> that is, in the <HI>other world,</HI> wherein both <HI>thou</HI> and <HI>I,</HI> and <HI>all</HI> other <HI>good</HI> and <HI>bad</HI> are after decease.</P>
<P>Secondly, more <HI>specially;</HI> the <HI>Soules</HI> of <HI>Gods Saints and seruants</HI> may well be said <HI>to go to their peo∣ple</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>v definit <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Greg. Nyss. in Macrin. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Theo∣phyl. in Luc. 16.</NOTE>
<PB N="60" REF="37"/>
<HI>and their Fathers,</HI> when they die; <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Ex Hebraeorum sententia Pet. Mar. tyr, &amp; Paraeus.</NOTE> because they goe to that <HI>peculiar place,</HI> where <HI>all</HI> their <HI>godly Coun∣try-men</HI> and <HI>Ancestors</HI> are; to the <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Heb. 12. 23. Q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>m <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Doctores <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>. Che<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>adam. alphab. mystic. c. 1.</NOTE> <HI>Congregation house</HI> (as the Apostle termes it) <HI>of the First-borne, and of the Spirits of the Iust.</HI> Nor doth it hinder, but that of <HI>Abraham</HI> it may so also be vnderstood, albeit that both his <HI>Country-mē,</HI> the most, it may be of them, and his <HI>Ancestours</HI> also, many of them, might be <HI>idolaters,</HI> as <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Iosh. 24 2.</NOTE> himselfe also at first was; since that many yet no doubt of both those <HI>rankes,</HI> both were <HI>pious,</HI> while they <HI>liued,</HI> and <HI>went to God,</HI> when they <HI>died:</HI> Besides that, wel also may they all be termed and stiled <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Ruth. 1. 16.</NOTE> his <HI>people,</HI> or <HI>country-men,</HI> though little of kinne to him otherwise, that were the <HI>people,</HI> while they liued, of the same <HI>God</HI> that he serued: Yea as well might <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Eorum filij diei∣mur, quorum fidem &amp; mores <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mitamur. Orig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Ezik. hom. 4. &amp; 6. Omnes hi matorcs tui sunt, si te illis dignum ges. seris. Sen. epist. 44.</NOTE> <HI>all</HI> the <HI>faithfull</HI> that went before him, be termed <HI>his Fathers,</HI> whether he were lineally and carnally descended of them or no, as <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">Mat. 3. 6. Rom. 4. 16, 18. Gal. 3. 29.</NOTE> <HI>all</HI> the <HI>faithfull</HI> that came after him, are termed <HI>his sonnes.</HI></P>
<P><HI>But to hasten to an end:</HI></P>
<P>First, this may serue to <HI>strengthen vs</HI> against the <HI>feare</HI> of <HI>death,</HI> or of what shall become of vs when we are dead: Since that, as <NOTE N="a" PLACE="marg">Ambulat per vi∣am, per quam am∣bulauerunt pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>res c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us. Hebr. ex Psal. 49. 19. O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>st. sup. Vse 1.</NOTE> we <HI>goe not</HI> any <HI>strange way</HI> when we die, such as none haue gone before vs, but a <HI>beaten path,</HI> that <NOTE N="b" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> Iosh. 23. 14. 1 King 2. 2.</NOTE> <HI>all,</HI> euen <HI>good,</HI> haue <HI>gone;</HI> so we <HI>goe not</HI> to any <HI>strange place,</HI> where either <HI>none</HI> are already, or none that we haue any <HI>acquaintance</HI> withall; but we goe to our <HI>Christian friends,</HI> to our <HI>religious Fore-fathers,</HI> <NOTE N="c" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Antiphan. St<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>b. cap. 124.</NOTE> to a place, where we shall
<PB N="61" REF="37"/>
<HI>meet</HI> againe with all those, that wee <NOTE N="d" PLACE="marg">Consecuturi prae misimus. Senec. ad Marc. c. 19 Eô cito peruenturi, qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> illi peruenerint. Idem ep. 63. 2 Sam. 11. 23.</NOTE> <HI>sent</HI> from hence before vs, hauing <HI>deceased in the faith.</HI> It is that indeed that much troubleth men and women many times, when they are enforced to trauell in∣to strange countries, and to change the places of their wonted and ancient abode; to fore-thinke, what an vncouth thing it wil be, to come among <HI>a strange people,</HI> where they <HI>know none,</HI> and <HI>none know</HI> them. It would haue troubled <HI>Iacob</HI> not a lit∣tle to haue remoued into <HI>Aegypt,</HI> had he not beene <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Gen. 45. 58. &amp; 46. 3, 4.</NOTE> sure to finde <HI>Ioseph</HI> there. But the <HI>godly</HI> need not be troubled with any such thoughts, when they are to <HI>remoue</HI> hence: For they shall goe to <HI>their owne people, their Friends, their Fathers:</HI> they shall be sure to <NOTE N="e" PLACE="marg">Mutamus ami∣cos, non r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>linqu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Hieron. in Nepot.</NOTE> finde <HI>country-men, kindred, acquain∣tance</HI> enough in <HI>heauen,</HI> that will be <NOTE N="f" PLACE="marg">Praestolatur n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s Ecclesia primitiuo∣rum: de siderant no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sancti; expectant nos iusti. Desidere∣mus ergò de sideran∣tes nos: pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>remu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ad praestolātes nos: expectantes nos vo∣tis prae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>upemus. Bern. de temp. 98. Vse 2.</NOTE> readie to <HI>re∣ceiue</HI> them, to <HI>welcome</HI> them thither, to <HI>giue</HI> them the <HI>best entertainment</HI> that can be there. Yea this should make vs the rather <HI>desirous to die</HI> and to go hence, <NOTE N="g" PLACE="marg">Equidem efferor studio patres ve∣stros, quos colu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> &amp; dilex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, vid ndi. Ne{que} verò eos solum con∣u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nire aueo, quos ip∣se cognoui, sed illos etiam de quibus au∣diut &amp; legi. Cie. de. sen.</NOTE> that we may goe to, and be with those <HI>worthies,</HI> whom either hauing knowne here our selues, or hauing read of, or heard report of from others, we haue <HI>admired,</HI> and <HI>desired</HI> either to <HI>see,</HI> or to <HI>liue with,</HI> while they liued here.</P>
<P>And lastly, if we desire to <HI>goe</HI> to them when we <HI>die,</HI> let vs be sure to <HI>follow</HI> them while we <HI>liue.</HI> <NOTE N="h" PLACE="marg">Psal. 119. 63.</NOTE> <HI>Adioine</HI> thy selfe to them, <HI>associate</HI> thy selfe with them, while thou <HI>liuest here,</HI> if thou desirest to <HI>be with</HI> them, and to <HI>partake</HI> with them, when thou <HI>departest hence.</HI> <NOTE N="i" PLACE="marg">Rom. 4. 12.</NOTE> <HI>Walke</HI> thou must <HI>in the steps of faithfull Abraham,</HI> while thou <HI>liuest,</HI> if thou lookest to haue a place <NOTE N="k" PLACE="marg">Luke. 16. 22.</NOTE> <HI>in Abrahams bosome,</HI> when thou
<PB N="62" REF="38"/>
<HI>diest,</HI> and <NOTE N="l" PLACE="marg">Matth. 8. 11.</NOTE> <HI>sit downe with him,</HI> after this life, <HI>in the kingdome of heauen. Oh</HI> (it may be that some of you will s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y of this our blessed Brother now de∣ceased) <HI>that my soule were where his is: that I might be sure to die as he did, and to goe whither he is gone, when I die.</HI> Heare what the Apostle saith; he poin∣teth thee the way, he telleth thee how it may so be, how thou maist haue thy desire. <NOTE N="m" PLACE="marg">Hebr. 13. 7.</NOTE> <HI>Think vpon those</HI> (saith he) <HI>that haue had the ouersight of you, and that haue declared the word of God vnto you; and follow their faith, considering what the end of their life hath beene.</HI> Be not like <HI>Balaam,</HI> <NOTE N="n" PLACE="marg">N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m 23. 10.</NOTE> that wished to come where the godly were, but <NOTE N="o" PLACE="marg">Imp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s &amp; foe∣lix si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> simul esse cu∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>t, V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, ius es∣se, velit tamen ess<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> bea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us: Quod ni∣tura negat, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ra∣tio patitur. De Ma∣eria. apud Iul. Ca∣pitol. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. Isidor. Pel. l. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. epist. 168. Bonum quaeris; malum fa∣cis; in contrarium curris: quando per∣nenis? Aug. nom. de Stoic. &amp; Epic. c. 3.</NOTE> had no minde to goe the <HI>way</HI> that they went. But <NOTE N="p" PLACE="marg">Hebr. 13. 17.</NOTE> follow the <HI>rules</HI> that he <HI>taught</HI> thee, <NOTE N="q" PLACE="marg">Philip. 2. 17, 20.</NOTE> goe the <HI>way</HI> that he <HI>led</HI> thee, by <HI>life</HI> as well as by <HI>lesson,</HI> while he liued; and then shalt thou be sure to <HI>go to him</HI> when thou diest, and to <HI>enioy there with him</HI> and other the faithfull gone before thee, those <HI>ioyes</HI> and that <HI>blisse,</HI> that with <HI>God</HI> and <HI>Christ</HI> they are there fully possessed of al∣readie.</P>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="errata">
<PB REF="38"/>
<HEAD>Faults escaped.</HEAD>
<P>PAge 18. line 21. reade <HI>walked.</HI> p. 32. l. 11. r. <HI>stranger.</HI> p. 27. l. 2. r. <HI>with wind.</HI> p. 28. l. 18. r. <HI>hardly he discerned.</HI></P>
<P><HI>In the Margine.</HI></P>
<P>PAge 20. l. <SUP>a</SUP> <HI>peritat.</HI> p. 22. l. <SUP>d</SUP> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. p. 23. l. <SUP>s</SUP> <HI>seu quod.</HI> p. 25. l. <SUP>k</SUP> <HI>sicut cum.</HI> p. 26. l. <SUP>c</SUP> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. l. <SUP>i</SUP> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. p. 27. l. <SUP>a</SUP> <HI>dissip<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</HI> p. 28. l. <SUP>l</SUP> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>. p. 29. l. <SUP>a</SUP> <HI>sap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r{que} &amp;c. &amp; ibid. famil. a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rae.</HI> p. 30. l. <SUP>•</SUP> <HI>cae∣t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rorum.</HI> p. 32. l. <SUP>p</SUP> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/> <HI>&amp; ibid.</HI> <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</P>
<P><HI>Adde p. 49. l. 9. after, haue beene <HI>buried.</HI></HI></P>
<P>In regard whereof that <NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Craesus apud He∣rodot. lib. 1.</NOTE> great <HI>King</HI> sometime, though then none, preferred <NOTE N="†" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> <HI>peace</HI> before <HI>warre;</HI> for that <NOTE N="“" PLACE="marg"><GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</NOTE> in time of <HI>peace</HI> vsually <HI>Children burie</HI> their <HI>Parents,</HI> whereas in time of <HI>warre Parents</HI> are wont to bury their Children.</P>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

